<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The two witnesses: their prophecy, slaughter, resurection and ascention: or, An exposition of the eleventh chapter of the Revelation wherein is plainly proved that the scriptures of the Old and New Testaments, are the witnesses there spoken of, who have prophesied in sackcloth one thousand two hundred and sixty years compleat; that they are already slain, revived, and ascended. That the tenth part of the city is fallen by our late earthquake, wherein seven thousand names of men were slain. The second wo is past. This is the first part of the chapter, the second part follows. By Tho. Tillam, a weak labourer in the Lords Harvest.</title>
            <author>Tillam, Thomas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1651</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 229 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 90 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62540</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T1168</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R219308</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99830791</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99830791</idno>
            <idno type="VID">35245</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62540)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 35245)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2082:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The two witnesses: their prophecy, slaughter, resurection and ascention: or, An exposition of the eleventh chapter of the Revelation wherein is plainly proved that the scriptures of the Old and New Testaments, are the witnesses there spoken of, who have prophesied in sackcloth one thousand two hundred and sixty years compleat; that they are already slain, revived, and ascended. That the tenth part of the city is fallen by our late earthquake, wherein seven thousand names of men were slain. The second wo is past. This is the first part of the chapter, the second part follows. By Tho. Tillam, a weak labourer in the Lords Harvest.</title>
                  <author>Tillam, Thomas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 168 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R.W. for Giles Calvert, and are to be sold at the [b]lack spread Eagle at the west end of Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1651.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title page is on verso of first leaf.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication conjectured by cataloger.</note>
                  <note>A poem, titled "The seventh angel sounding" follows title page.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>Title page torn, affecting imprint.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Revelation XI --  Commentaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:35245:1"/>
            <p>THE Seventh Angel ſounding, Preſents A glimps of the glorious Raign of Jeſus Chriſt, whoſe perſonal appearance is royally attended with theſe fifteen Changes full of wonder, as ſo many Trophie's of his abſolute victory and univerſal ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraignty.
<table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1. The Saints Deceaſed</cell>
                     <cell>Royal Jeſus Brings.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>2. The Reſt Releaſed</cell>
                     <cell> mount on Angels wings.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>3. To Iſrael mourning</cell>
                     <cell> ſounds a glorious Call,</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>4. To Babel burning</cell>
                     <cell> an eternal fall.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>5. The world Combined</cell>
                     <cell> hath a fatal blow,</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>6. Satan Confined</cell>
                     <cell> to his Den below.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>7. The whole Creation</cell>
                     <cell> finds a full releaſe,</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>8. And every Nation</cell>
                     <cell> flouriſhes with peace.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>9. The Mount aſunder<lb/>(That vale of wonder</cell>
                     <cell> cleaves t' enlarge the Plain,<lb/> where the Lord muſt raign)</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>10. The glorious City</cell>
                     <cell> from Gods throne doth glide,</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>11. The Nuptial ditty</cell>
                     <cell> uſhers in the Bride.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>12. Thus Saints regaining</cell>
                     <cell> an immortal ſtate,</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>13. In glory reigning</cell>
                     <cell> while the Sun bears date,</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>14. The Nations bending</cell>
                     <cell>Virgins voyces Raiſe,</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>15. (All Duties ending)</cell>
                     <cell> in joy, love, and praiſe.</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Joel 3.9.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p> Proclaim ye this among the Gentiles.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Zech. 14.5, 9.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p> The Lord my God ſhall come, and all the Saints with thee: And the Lord, ſhall be King over all the earth; in that day ſhall there be one Lord, and his name one.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal. 102.16.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p> When the Lord ſhall build up Sion, he ſhall appear in his glory.</p>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:35245:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Two Witneſſes: Their Prophecy, Slaughter, Reſurecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Aſcention: OR, An Expoſition of the eleventh Chapter of the <hi>Revelation,</hi> wherein is plainly proved that the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of the Old and New Teſtaments, are the witneſſes there ſpoken of, who have Propheſied in Sackcloth one thouſand two hundred and ſixty years compleat; That they are already ſlain, revived, and aſcended. That the tenth part of the City is fallen by our late Earthquake, wherein ſeven thouſand Names of men were ſlain. <hi>The ſecond wo is paſt.</hi> This is the firſt part of the Chapter, the ſecond Part follows.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Tho. Tillam,</hi> a weak Labourer in the Lords Harveſt.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 4.20.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p> We cannot but ſpeak the things which we have ſeen and heard.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>.11.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p> We ſpeak that we do know, and teſtifie that we have ſeen, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> and ye receive not our Witneſs.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed by <hi>R.W.</hi> for <hi>Giles Calvert,</hi> and are to be ſold at the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>lack ſpread Eagle at the Weſt end of <hi>Pauls,</hi> 1651.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:35245:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:35245:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:35245:3"/>
            <head>TO My Honoured Col. <hi>George Twiſsleton,</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> Governor of <hi>Denbigh.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eſides your many favors confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red upon my unworthy ſelf for a thankful acknowledgement; I am alſo many ways (as I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive) obliged to preſent unto you this Treatiſe, as having its ſpring and firſt appearance under your Command, where your faithful endeavours are imployed for the advancement of the glory of God, in your many encouragements to thoſe under your charge, to be daily exerciſed in ſuch
<pb facs="tcp:35245:4"/>duties and ſervices, as being religiouſly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved, will be your Crown and their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in the day of the Lord Jeſus, when all preſent ſhadows of honours will be ſwallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up in that immortal glory, which is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for all ſuch as are free in laying out themſelves for the honour of this King of Glory, as your ſelf (dear Sir) have of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten been, in improving your intereſt with Chriſt on the behalf of this Commonwealth and our Neighbour Nations, upon emergent occaſions: Another motive enducing me to prefix your name, is your affection to thoſe Changes that attend the coming of Chriſt, as they are digeſted in the Title Page, which your Worſhip cauſed me to write down in a Book which I am perſwaded you dearly love above all the world.</p>
            <p>Sir, I doubt not you will be more affected to finde each of theſe wonderful Changes di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly cleared and proved by the Word of Truth, (as I ſuppoſe they are in this lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Book.)</p>
            <p>Truly Sir, The holding of them forth hath coſt me dear, upon the riſing of a ſpirit of emulattion in ſome, who could not brook that applauſe which was openly gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to theſe Truths upon the delivery thereof.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:35245:4"/>
            <p>But I have heard ſuch expreſsions from you, which have ſavored of another ſpirit, as loving Truth for Truths ſake by whomſoever declared.</p>
            <p>One word from you hath made a deep im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsion upon my ſpirit, by which I deſire my affections may be regulated; namely, <hi>Of loving men for Religions ſake, and not Religion for any mens ſake:</hi> theſe, with other of like nature, have raiſed my affections to preſent this Treatiſe to your much honored name: if you find Truth evident, I have confidence you will give it entertainment: and though any thing herein ſhould ſeem to be <hi>New Light,</hi> yet I hope it will not be the leſs welcome, if it appear <hi>True Light.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, I might have inlarged this Epiſtle upon good and ſubſlantial grounds in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to you, as your unwearied Service, and conſtant fidelity (as of all your flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing Family) to this State; your preſent Employments in the faithful adminiſtration of Juſtice, and the like.</p>
            <p>But for ſundry reaſons I forbear, Cloſing with my unfeighned deſires of the wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare of your pretious ſoul, that it may flouriſh in that full Society of Glorified
<pb facs="tcp:35245:5"/>Saints in New <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> as it is dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly expected to be manifeſted in Power by</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your real faithful ſervant</hi> Tho. Tillam.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="commentary">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:35245:5"/>
            <head>An Expoſition of the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth Chapter of the <hi>Revelation.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Lord by a ſpecial Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, guiding me to a Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple daily exerciſed in reading his Word, and opening the the ſame (in order;) now having before them the eleventh Chapter of the <hi>Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> they deſired my help in Expound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this Myſterious piece; which ſudden and unexpected motion, did ſomewhat ſurprize me, as knowing that it hath been accounted one of the hardeſt knots in the revealed will of God: and withall, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering how various the Opinions of Writers are upon the ſubject matter there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and how little ſatisfaction I had ever received from any of them;</p>
            <p>I therefore intended to ſpeak a word or two from the two firſt verſes, and to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover my ignorance of the great My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:35245:6"/>of the Witneſſes by paſſing it over in ſilence.</p>
            <p>But while I was reading the Chapter, I was moſt ſweetly warmed by a ſecret heavenly heat, quickning my ſpirit, which was (as it were) tranſported by this ſoft gale of life and light, and even con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to declare this, which with full and cleer evidence was communicated to me; which alſo making ſome notable im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion upon the ſpirits of the moſt judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious hearers, they importuned me to give it them in writing; at whoſe requeſt I ſet to the work, and in the review of theſe impreſſions upon my heart, comparing them with ſuch Eccleſiaſtical Hiſtories as till then were unknown to me, I found ſuch harmony, ſo ſweet conſent, in Time, Place, Perſon, every thing, that hath left no place in my ſpirit for any further diſputes, reaſonings, or objections againſt the truth of theſe teachings.</p>
            <p>And the Lord ſo open the Readers un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, that he alſo may receive the like full and ſweet ſatisfaction in this Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Myſtery; and ſo may obtain the bleſſing promiſed to ſuch as read, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.3.</note> hear, and obey the words of this Propheſie.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:35245:6"/>
               <head>The eleventh Chapter of the <hi>Revelation.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe great God cals it a <hi>Revelation:</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.1.</note> Who are they that dare any longer term it an allegory? Doth he that is <hi>Alpha and Omega</hi> delude his poor creatures, in declaring it as his revealed will, when (if many may have credit that affirm it) it is a concealed Myſterie, not to be med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with? <hi>Let God be true, and every man a lyar.</hi> And let my ſoul flouriſh with thoſe truly ſpiritual Saints, <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.</note> who judge all things by that ſpirit which ſearcheth all things, yea the deep things of God, to whom be glory for ever.</p>
               <div n="1" type="verse">
                  <head>The firſt Verſe. <hi>And there was given me a Reed like unto a Rod; and the Angel ſtood, ſaying, Riſe, and meaſure the Temple of God, and the Altar, and them that worſhip therein.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>That which I intended chiefly to inſiſt upon in the reading of this Chapter, namely the two firſt verſes, I ſhall now run over briefly, and haſten to the great
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:35245:7"/>myſtery of the two Witneſſes.</p>
                  <p>The firſt thing given to the Apoſtle <hi>John</hi> here, is a Reed, that he as a wiſe Maſter-builder might exactly meaſure his work and leave a Pattern to all Believers, as thoſe that muſt work and walk by Rule; This Reed is the ſame with that mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring line;
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Zech.</hi> 2.1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 4.10.</note> The Plummet in the hand of <hi>Zerubbabel,</hi> by which <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> (in all Ages) muſt be meaſured;
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iſay</hi> 36.6. <hi>Mat.</hi> 27.29</note> tis not an <hi>Egyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian</hi> Reed, (too weak for ſuch a work) nor ſuch a Reed as was put for a mock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcepter into the hand of our Crucified Lord.</p>
                  <p>But this holy Reed is that Royal Scepter of Chriſts Kingdom, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 145.6.</note> whereby he ruleth his Princely ſubjects, which he hath won by Conqueſt from Death and Hell, being none other then the ſword of the Spirit which is the Word of God, put into the hands and hearts of his faithful Miniſters, <note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.2. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.15.</note> whom he hath au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorized to direct, guide, and govern his ſelect ſheep until his ſecond com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming.</p>
                  <p>This Royal Reed is that ſtaff of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and Rod of Diſcipline, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 23.4.</note> which was the great joy and ſolace of Kingly <hi>Davids</hi> ſoul:</p>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:35245:7"/>
                  <p>This is the ſtaff of beauty and the ſtaff of bands, <note place="margin">Zech.</note> with which the Lord led and fed his flock of old, and with which he will have the Goſpel-Temple, and the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar and every Worſhipper therein exactly meaſured now.</p>
                  <p>As Chriſt the foundation was (in all his actions) meaſured by this line of truth, (that the Scriptures might be fulfilled, as it is written according to the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and the like;
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.12. <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.24, 31. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.3, 4. <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.14. 1 <hi>Kin.</hi> 17.18, <hi>&amp;</hi> 6.7.</note>) ſo muſt every living ſtone, every true branch be ſquared, ruled, and meaſured by the ſame Reed; <hi>Ye are my friends if ye do whatſoever I command you:</hi> Thoſe ſtones that were admitted into <hi>Solomons</hi> Temple, were firſt hewed, ſqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, prepared, coſtly ſtones: And can it be imagined that a promiſcuous heap of rug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, polluted, deformed, unpoliſht ſtones, ſhould be fit matter for this ſecond more glorious Temple? Is it probable that Chriſt will admit of ſcandalous, ignorant, prophane perſons, (neither reſembling, nor in a capacity of diſcerning his bleſſed body) as choyce materials for this <hi>true Tabernacle which the Lord hath pitched and not man?</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.7, 8. <hi>Ezech.</hi> 22.26. <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.2.</note> Would ſuch dirty patches be ſeemly in his ſeamleſs Coat? the Lord abhorreth ſuch a mixture.</p>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:35245:8"/>
                  <p>The true glory of this Goſpel-temple conſiſts in the purity of the materials, <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving lively ſtones, exactly meaſured, and fitly framed together, <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.5. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.21.22. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.9.</note> growing to an holy Temple in the Lord; An habitation of God through the Spirit: A choſen Generation, a royal Prieſthood, an holy Nation, a peculiar People.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Not ſuch as challenge intereſt by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of cohabitation; not a Pariſh houſe of ſtone, as the Prelatical Hierarchy inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted us; this holy Reed was never preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Angel to <hi>John</hi> to meaſure Pariſh bounds.</p>
                  <p>He that intends this work, muſt not be idle. <hi>Riſe and meaſure the Temple,</hi> is the voyce the Spirit.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="verse">
                  <head>The ſecond Verſe. <hi>But the Court which is without the Temple leave out, and meaſure it not; for it is given unto the Gentiles, and the holy City ſhall they tread under foot forty and two months.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>The Romiſh Conclave became this outward Court, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.5. <hi>An.</hi> 304.</note> immediately after the birth of the man-child <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> when ſuddenly with caſe, peace, and tranquillity,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:35245:8"/>there crept in ambition, contention, covet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs attended with abominable Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, Superſtition, Idolatry, <note place="margin">Bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. <hi>Rev. Apoc. pag.</hi> 75.</note> and all kinde of luxury, and prophaneſs, which ruſhed like waves one on the neck of another, ſuddenly overwhelming and devouring that ſweetneſs, humility, charity, chaſtity, and purity which lately were the royal or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments of this now defiled, polluted, Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And now the true and ſincere ſervants of Chriſt, obſerving this diſmal darkneſs gradually ſurprizing her, and obſcuring her former luſtre and true beauty, dare no longer drink of her polluted ſtreams, nor partake of her defiled Ordinances; but withdraw and ſeparate themſelves from ſuch abominations, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.6.</note> creeping into corners (any Wilderneſs condition) where they may enjoy the pure Ordinances of Chriſt, and be nouriſhed with the pure milk of the breaſts of the heavenly Witneſſes.</p>
                  <p>(Like as the Saints lately did in the times of Prelatical perſecution; and as many a poor Chriſtian is even now con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to do, from the pride, and other prophaneſs of ſome diſorderly ſocieties.)</p>
                  <p>And thus the true Church flying into the Wilderneſs, all ſilent and ſolitary, is
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:35245:9"/>trampled upon by the outward Court of proud Prelats, who have learnd to Lord it over her, which they purſue through the whole courſe of her exile; and yet maugre all this malice of Antichriſt, though ſhe hath continued in her exiled, mournful, Wilderneſs eſtate, ſcarce da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to appear in her true glory through the whole term of 1260 years (in which ſhe hath been ſecretly ſupported by her Witneſſes in Sack-cloth) yet hath he, (who is glorious in holineſs, fearfull in praiſes, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Exod.</hi> 15.11.</note> doing wonders, whoſe promiſes are <hi>Yea</hi> and <hi>Amen</hi> in his Chriſt) at length brought (through all ſtorms, oppreſſions and miſeries,) this his pure lovely Spouſe with her diſtreſſed Witneſſes to a bleſſed haven of glory and honour: That God bleſſed for ever who did aſſure them (ſome thouſands of yeers ſince) that though they lay among the Pots, yet he would give them the wings of a Dove covered with ſilver and feathers of yellow gold,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 68.13.</note> hath ſo gloriouſly fulfilled his Royal Word, that now Saints may ſecurely ſit and ſweetly ſing, (as a Chorus to the voyce of their Beloved,) <hi>Lo the winter is paſt, <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.11, 12.</note> the rain is over and gone, the flowers ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear on the earth, the time of ſinging of birds is
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:35245:9"/>come, and the voyce of the Turtle is heard in our Land.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="verse">
                  <head>The third Verſe. <hi>And I will give power unto my two Witneſſes, and they ſhall Propheſie one thouſand two hundred and threeſcore dayes clothed in Sackcloth.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>All the rage and malice of Antichriſt, ſhall not be able to ſtop their mouthes till toward the end of their Teſtimony; they ſhall propheſie all along, though it be not in that external pomp and glory where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with Popes, Cardinals, and the reſt of the Antichriſtian rable rout now flouriſhed; but all forlorn, retired, obſcured, in mournful Sackcloth, yet they ſhall Propheſie; &amp; the Temple, even in the midſt of the outward Court (that is, the Apoſtatized Church of <hi>Rome</hi>) is given to them, and even there do they worſhip the Lord in purity, but ſo covertly and obſcurely that they are not eaſily diſcerned; eſpecially, by the Pope and his ſcarlet Conclave, whoſe eyes are dazled with external pomp and glory.</p>
                  <p>Thus is the Virgin Spouſe of Chriſt and her heavenly Witneſſes (which in the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:35245:10"/>midſt of Heathen Perſecutions was clothed in the Royal Robes of her ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Husband) now become an object of ſcorn and contempt to thoſe wicked watch-men, who (what in them lay) ſpoyled and depraved her of that heavenly ſimplicity and Goſpel-purity ſhe lately ſhined in. <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.13.</note> Now is ſhe become the true Antitype of the Church of <hi>Pergamos,</hi> dwelling (in obſcurity) where Antichriſts throne is, and there ſhe holdeth faſt the Faith, and denyeth not the name of her crucified Lord, which ever and anon doth coſt ſome faithful <hi>Antipas</hi> his life. And here the bleſſed Witneſſes nouriſh her, and Propheſie againſt her Adverſary: that proud Scarlet Strumpet did ſo defile, darken, wrack, wreſt, and pervert the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scriptures to uphold their abominable Idolatry and Superſtition, that no other veſture appear'd upon them but ſable weeds of ſorrowful Sackcloth; and when (in deſpight of their fond Allegories and ſenſual conceits,) theſe two Witneſſes ſpake to their faces againſt the dreadful abominations creeping in ſo faſt; this Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot not able to bear their reproof, hating to be reformed, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.17.</note> and rejecting inſtruction, did at length caſt behinde them into ſecret
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:35245:10"/>holes and corners theſe bleſſed Scriptures of truth: ſo that in the midſt of all this Papal Tyranny (which daily increaſed) they remaind ſecretly, nouriſhing the true Church even where the Beaſt reigned, yea, in the heart of his dominions, the whole term of their teſtimony in Sack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloth, <hi>viz.</hi> 1260 years; during which time, this is the Character which is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of the Romiſh Harlot, <note place="margin">Mich. Cec. contr. Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannid. Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pae. Mornaus Myſt. Iniq. Bez. quaest.</note> 
                     <hi>There were within the Papal Territories two Churches, the one of the wicked ſort flouriſhing wherein the Pope reigned; the other of godly and good men, and this he perſecuted; ſo that the Church was under (or within) the Papacy, but the Papacy was not the Church.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now this being clear in the word of truth, that the true Church remains alive in the midſt of this dead ſea, and is preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved like <hi>Jonah</hi> in the belly of this mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous <hi>Leviathan;</hi> What will become of that empty flouriſh of a vaunting Jeſuite, <hi>Where was your Church before Luther?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>We ſee (to the high prayſes of our eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal King) that it was in the Ark in the midſt of the great Deluge; in <hi>Goſhen</hi> in the midſt of the <hi>Egyptian</hi> darkneſs; in the den amidſt thoſe roaring Lyons in the furnace, ſafe and ſecure in the extremeſt
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:35245:11"/>heat of Popiſh perſecution: And is now come forth of that great Tribulation, as pure gold out of that fiery Tryal, as a Crown of Glory in the hand of the Lord,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iſai.</hi> 62.3.</note> and a Royal Diadem in the hand of our God. But who can marvel at this fooliſh queſtion of blinde Papiſts, when the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty, obſcurity and ſimplicity of the True Church, and her abſtruſe Witneſſes is conſidered? how could their eyes (ſo groſly blinded with the black ſcales of am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, pomp, &amp; luxury, behold, or diſcern, ſuch contemptible objects as the Church in her exile, and her Witneſſes in their Sackcloth? Did not their Fathers the Scribes and Phariſes grope in the ſame Egyptian darkneſs, when they could not diſcern a <hi>Meſsias,</hi> though working won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders even in the very midſt of them? their Holineſſes lookt too high to behold Chriſt in a Carpenters coat, even like His prophane wickedneſs, who ſitting in that Chayr of peſtilence at <hi>Rome</hi> could not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the holy City under his feet, nor the heavenly Witneſſes in their mournful habit: of both which their Predeceſſors and themſelves are alike wilfully ignorant to this day.</p>
                  <p>O the diſtinguiſhing love of a gracious
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:35245:11"/>Father! Why ſhould not we be thus blind and ignorant! ſhall we ſee the cauſe, <hi>Luke</hi> 10.21. <hi>I thank thee, O Father, Lord of heaven and earth, that thou haſt hid theſe things from the wiſe and prudent, and haſt revealed them unto babes: even ſo Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for ſo it ſeemed good in thy ſight.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="verse">
                  <head>The fourth Verſe. <hi>Theſe are the two Olive-trees, and the two Candleſticks ſtanding before the God of the earth.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> ſaith, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Clav. Apoc. pag.</hi> 11. 12.</note> there lieth hidden in theſe words, an Hebraiſm, having this ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification, viz. <hi>The two Olive-trees, [at, or beſides,] the two Candleſticks;</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Annotat. Zech.</hi> 4.3. they are ſaid to ſtand by the ſides of the Candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick.</note> or as the <hi>London</hi> Miniſters have it, <hi>With the two Candleſticks or Churches;</hi> ſo that the Churches are one thing, and the Witneſſes feeding them another thing. Theſe two Olive-trees are plainly called the word of the Lord, <hi>Zech.</hi> 4.6. not <hi>Zerubbabel</hi> and <hi>Joſhua,</hi> as ſome imagine; nor <hi>Enoch</hi> and <hi>Elias,</hi> as others conjecture; nor Chriſt and his Saints, as a third conceive; nor <hi>Burton</hi> and <hi>Prynne,</hi> as hath been confidently af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed, but all with as much ſhow of truth as that the two Houſes of this
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:35245:12"/>preſent Parliament ſhould be them; but all theſe conceits and all other fancies of like nature are not worth the Anſwer, as having not the leaſt ground or warrant in that bleſſed Rule, that is able to make the man of God wiſe unto ſalvation; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers have ſuppoſed that they are the Word and Spirit: And our Engliſh Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet Mr. <hi>Brightman</hi> thinks they are the holy Scriptures, and the Churches of the Saints: But this may not be granted for theſe reaſons.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The Scriptures and the Saints can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not die one kinde of death; and there is not the leaſt appearance in the Word, of any difference or diſtinction in their ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and we muſt be ſure to keep cloſe to the Reed that was given <hi>John</hi> to meaſure all true Believers by.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The Saints cannot be ſaid (in any cleer ſence) to riſe again three years and a half after their ſufferings, at the time men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned by Mr. <hi>Brightman.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. It is evident, that the Saints ſuffered as great miſery, and were as vehemently perſecuted after his ſuppoſed reſurrection, as at any time before; which were abſurd, (and without any Scripture ground) to conceive of the Witneſſes after their revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving.</p>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:35245:12"/>
                  <p n="4">4. <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.6.</note> The Saints are the woman or Church, and the Witneſſes diſtinctly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for her aid, ſuccour and ſupport in her exile 1260 dayes or years: Therefore the Saints and the Scriptures both, cannot be the Witneſſes.</p>
                  <p>But ſome who have thought that theſe two Witneſſes are the Word and Spirit, do come neareſt the truth, and in ſome ſence this is truth, of which more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non.</p>
                  <p>The two Olive-trees which we are enquiring of, are called the Witneſſes di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct from the Candleſticks; for though our Tranſlators have coupled them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the conjunction <hi>[and]</hi> yet we have been enformed, that <hi>[at, or beſides,]</hi> is more proper and ſignificant according to <hi>Zech.</hi> 4.3. But I have determined never to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive any teſtimony of man how excellent ſoever, unleſs it be ſtrongly backt and ſubſtantially ſupported by that cleer fountain of life the teſtimony of Truth; <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iſai.</hi> 8.20.</note> 
                     <hi>To the law and to the teſtimony; if they ſpeak not according to this word, it is becauſe there is no light in them:</hi> And this teſtimony, even this very word diſcovers more heavenly light then I was aware of; for in this Text the Scirptures are plainly cald a Teſtimony or
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:35245:13"/>Witneſs; Let the anſwer to <hi>Zechary</hi>'s queſtion cleer the truth hereof more fully; the Prophet having a Viſion of theſe two Olive-trees (which are plainly ſaid to ſtand by the Candleſtick,) <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Zech.</hi> 4.3.</note> asketh the Angel what they were? to which he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, <hi>This is the word of the Lord;</hi> that is to ſay, the Scriptures which before are called the Law and the Teſtimony; and this word of the Lord held forth by two Olive-trees, is purpoſely produced for the cheriſhing and eſtabliſhing of that Temple-work that <hi>Zerubbabel</hi> had in hand, as if the Lord ſhould ſay, Let this enform and aſſure you, that though mountains of difficulties appear,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Neh.</hi> 6.1.</note> though <hi>Tobiah</hi> and <hi>Sanballat</hi> (the exact type of Pope and Cardinals) and many falſe brethren uſe all means to hinder and deſtroy my Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple-work; though my Candleſtick be now in a low, mean obſcure condition; yet my work ſhall go on and proſper; the Word is gone out of my mouth, it is upon record in the writings of my Prophets, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore cannot fail; but theſe Scriptures of truth ſhall continually ſtand by my Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleſticks like two Olive-trees, conveying by my ſeven ſorts of Inſtruments as by ſo many Pipes, ſuch plentiful nouriſhment
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:35245:13"/>as ſhall be able to ſupport my Churches in the moſt forlorn exiled wilderneſs eſtate: this was the condition of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed Church oppoſed by Potent Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, aſwell in the time of the great builder <hi>Zerubbabel,</hi> as in the time of the great builder <hi>Conſtantine;</hi> and this alſo is worth our conſideration, that neither the Enemies of the Jews then, nor the Enemies of the true Saints now, were ſuch profeſſedly, but made a great ſhow of friendſhip; <hi>Come ſay they; we will build with you,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ezra.</hi> 4.2.</note> for we ſeek your God, as ye do.</hi> But they ſecretly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired againſt the Jews, endevouring by all poſſible means to hinder the work: And this was the ſpeech, and thus was the practice of that <hi>Iobiah</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> and thoſe other ſecret Enemies, in the time of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And now the word of the Lord is the only viſible ſupport, and ſupply of the poor diſtreſſed woman; and this word of the Lord ſtands like two Olive Trees on each ſide the Candleſticks, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Zech.</hi> 4.11.12. <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.6.</note> or true Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, yielding conſtant nouriſhment to the Saints in their 1260. years miſery, all which being diligently compared, and ſeriouſly conſidered, raiſeth my appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions to theſe concluſions.</p>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:35245:14"/>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>The two Olive trees, are the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, or Two Teſtaments.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>The Candleſticks are the Churches of the Saints.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>The two Branches of the Two Olive Trees, are Doctrine and Diſcipline.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. <hi>The Golden Pipes of the Candleſticks are the Miniſters of the Churches.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For the clearing of theſe, I ſhall make my addreſs to that Chryſtal fountain, from whence one cleer teſtimony is to me of more validity then all the Arguments in the world.</p>
                  <p>This light the Spirit of truth is pleaſed to Communicate in this 4. Verſ. of the 11. Chapter. of the Revelation; that theſe witneſſes are two Olive Trees; which muſt be ſo underſtood, as Chriſt is a Vine, a Door, a Stone, a Nail, &amp;c. That is not really,
<note place="margin">Though I depend not upon mans teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, yet you may note, that <hi>Auſtin</hi> (the flower of Antiquity) was fully of this judgment.</note> but figuratively: ſo theſe bleſſed witneſſes have the ſame uſe, and therefore are fitly compared unto Olive Trees.</p>
                  <p>Firſt That theſe two Olive Trees are expreſly called the word of the Lord, hath been already proved from <hi>Zech.</hi> 4.6. and though this might abundantly ſatisfie being joyned with that of <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8.20. yet for the further Evidence of this truth, let
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:35245:14"/>us conſider the nature of the Olive tree, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.17.</note> from which the Jews were broken off, and I believe it will cleerly appear, that the Olive Tree there mentioned is none other but the word of God growing up, and drawing ſap from the eternall word the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, the root of this tree, whereof faithful <hi>Abraham</hi> was only a Type.</p>
                  <p>And that the breaking off the unbelie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Jews was their ſeparation from, (pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured by their contempt of) the doctrine of ſalvation contained in the Scripture; theſe, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.2. <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.5.6. <hi>Acts.</hi> 11.19.13.46.</note> and only theſe were the children of the Kingdome, to whom only the pure Oracles of God were committed, to whom only the Goſpel was Commanded to be preached, and to whom only for a long time it was Preached, till they rejecting this heavenly juyce, putting away the ſap and fatneſs of this Olive Tree, thereby judged themſelves unworthy of ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting life. So that this Act of theirs in putting from them the word of God, (cauſing thoſe words of <hi>Paul, and Barnabas, Lo we turn to the Gentiles</hi>) was the break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them off from the Olive Tree (the eternal word) it is worth our conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that the Apoſtle cals it their own
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:35245:15"/>Olive Tree, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom</hi> 11.24. <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.26.</note> as the Lord Jeſus alſo cals the word of Salvation their bread.</p>
                  <p>They are here ſaid to be cut off from the Olive Tree upon which they did grow; and we are graffed upon that ſtock, or tree from which they were cut; now it is plain that we are built upon the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the Apoſtles, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.02.</note> and Prophets, which I am ſure are the two Teſtaments that make out the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who is the root of this Olive Tree.</p>
                  <p>For the further Illuſtration of this truth (that it was the doctrine of ſalvation con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined in the Scriptures, from which theſe Jews were broken off, and conſequently that this Olive tree is none other then the word of God) let us examine what thoſe two ſtaves in <hi>Zachary</hi> are with which the Lord himſelf fed this ſtiff-necked obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate People, and this will plainly appear to be the holy Scriptures, or word of God: and leaſt it ſhould be deemed the humane fancy of a conceited Brain, take the naked words as they lie in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. <hi>I took unto me two ſtaves, the one I called beauty, and the other I called bands, and I fed the flock.
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Zech.</hi> 11.7.</note> And I took my ſtaff, even beauty, and cut it aſunder; and it was broken in that day, and ſo the poor of the flock that waited
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:35245:15"/>upon me, knew that it was the word of the Lord.</hi> That then from which theſe ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born Jews were broken off, is the word of the Lord, or the holy Scriptures; but the Jews were broken off the true Olive Tree; therefore the true Olive Tree is the word of the Lord, or the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
                  <p>All which being compared, it will evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently appear, that the two Olive Trees in this of the <hi>Revelation,</hi> and that of <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cariah,</hi> are none other then the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, or word of God.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, It is as plain that the bleſſed Scriptures are the proper Food and Nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſhment of Saints; ſpoken of <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.6. <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iſa.</hi> 25.6. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 36.</note> what elſe is that feaſt of fat things, that Wine on the Lees well refined, that fat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Lords houſe wherewith he ſatisfieth the ſouls of his Saints, thoſe Rivers of pleaſures he makes them drink of, and to which the Lord Jeſus ſo freely invites them? <hi>Eat O friends, Drink, <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.1.</note> yea Drink abundantly O beloved.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But I paſs this briefly, as not to be deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that the holy Scriptures are the proper Food and Nouriſhment of the Saints: For which employment theſe holy witneſſes are deſigned,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.6.</note> namely to feed the Church
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:35245:16"/>in her exiled Wilderneſs eſtate 1260 years.</p>
                  <p>But if any ſhall cavill, that I attribute that to the Scriptures, which is peculiar to the Spirit of God; I have this to ſay, that I have no thought of the Scriptures without, or beſide the Spirit of God; I receive all Scriptures as the Lord Jeſus delivered them. <hi>The words that I ſpeak unto you, <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.63. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15. <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.12.</note> they are Spirit, and they are life, able to make wiſe unto ſalvation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And therefore the bleſſed Scriptures are the proper, fit, ſutable nouriſhment for the Saints, and particularly for the Church in her afflicted deſpiſed wilderneſs eſtate.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, That the holy Scriptures are called witneſſes, and which is yet more plain, theſe very witneſſes of Chriſt, will appear in the peruſal of ſeveral Scriptures; And firſt that the Law is called ſo; <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Deut.</hi> 31.26.</note> 
                     <hi>Take this book of the Law and put it in the ſide of the Ark of the Covenant of the Lord your God, that it may be there for a Witneſs againſt thee.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And it appears as cleerly to me that the Goſpel is ſo called alſo. <note place="margin">1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.9.</note> 
                     <hi>This is the Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God which he hath teſtified of his ſon.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If it be objected, that it is the Spirit &amp;c. that is here called the Witneſs; tis readily
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:35245:16"/>granted, neither dare I call the Spirit one thing, and the word another thing (except it be ſaid that the Scriptures are the minde of the Spirit) it is above noted that the Lord Jeſus ſaith they are both one thing, <hi>The words that I ſpeak, they are Spirit;</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Scriptures have ordinarily the ſame Appellations, and operations aſcrib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to them, as are to the Spirit it ſelf; the Spirit is called Truth, ſo alſo the word is called Truth; <note place="margin">1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.6. <hi>Joh</hi> 17.17.</note> the Spirit is ſaid to ſanctify, ſo the word is likewiſe ſaid to ſanctify and the like; and certain I am, that the properties aſcribed to the word, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.12.13.</note> are not Communicable to any eſſence below the Spirit of God.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For the word of God is quick and Powerful, and ſharper then any two edged ſword, pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing even to the dividing aſunder of ſoul and Spirit, and of the joynts and marrow, and is a diſcerner of the thoughts and intents of the heart, &amp;c. Therefore have I hewed them by the Prophets, <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 6.5. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 11.4. compared with <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.5.10.</note> I have ſlain them by the words of my mouth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>When I compare theſe Scriptures with the fifth and tenth verſes of this eleventh of the <hi>Revelation,</hi> it doth ſo wonderfully cleer this truth to me, that the Scriptures of the two Teſtaments, and only theſe, are
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:35245:17"/>the two Witneſſes; that if there were no other ground but this, it would abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly ſatisfie, and confirm me in the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of this abſtruſe and wonderfull myſtery.</p>
                  <p>To conclude, this truth ſo manifeſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, is yet further cleered by thoſe bleſſed Lips where never guile was found; the Lord Jeſus Chriſt himſelf affirms it in theſe words, <hi>Search the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, for in them ye think ye have eternal life, and they are they that teſtifie of me.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>John.</hi> 5.39.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Where it is plain, that they are not only called Witneſſes, but theſe very Witneſſes here ſpoken of; for the words carry with them this cleer ſound, <hi>Search the Scriptures, for they are my Witneſſes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thus, as theſe bleſſed Witneſſes teſtify of Chriſt, ſo Chriſt alſo giveth teſtimony to them, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Fulk. Contr. Mart. Preſ. Pag</hi> 5.</note> as to his Witneſſes, and ſo puts the point in hand beyond all diſpute: That the holy Scriptures of the Two Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and only theſe, are the two Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes here ſpoken of. And yet one word more for the more ample diſcovery of the tranſcendent excellency of theſe hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Witneſſes, (the Scriptures of truth) from the cleer evidence the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> gives; who having declared the excellent
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:35245:17"/>glory of Chriſt in the mount which he ſaw; and the audible voice,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.17.</note> from the higheſt Majeſty, giving Invincible teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of his ſon. <hi>We have alſo</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>a more ſure word of Propheſie, whereunto ye do well that ye take heed, &amp;c.</hi> What? the Scriptures more ſure then the voice of God himſelf from heaven? yes, a more certain Infallible voice now in theſe Goſpel daies, then any miraculous extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary voice whatſoever; and here we may admire the wiſdome, care, and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of our Royal Lawgiver, who know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that many falſe Prophets would ariſe, and deceive many; and conſidering how Satan uſually transformeth himſelf into an Angel of light; <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.13. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.14. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 29.</note> and that his eldeſt Son Antichriſt would come after the working of this Prince of darkneſs, with all Power, and ſigns, and lying won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</p>
                  <p>But eſpecially foreſeeing that monſtrous impiety (which ſo many of his Servants have warned us of, as) that ordinances would be ſlighted, vilified, &amp; rejected, that many foul beaſts would defile, pollute, and at length totally depart from thoſe pure Chryſtal ſtreams that make glad the City of God, even the bleſſed Scriptures of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:35245:18"/>truth, <note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.21. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2.1.</note> immediately flowing from that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Ocean, of all fulneſs.</p>
                  <p>That many of them would <hi>deny</hi> (in part, (as the divinity) others abſolutely) <hi>the Lord that bought them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And that the Divel would ſo far pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail with ſome whom he would mount to ſuch a height of blaſphemy, as to affirm that they are Chriſt, the Spirit, the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Father, that their words are the words of God; and when you hear them ſpeak, it is God that ſpeaks, for they are God, and God is them, &amp;c. To deteſt this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtable wickedneſs, and moſt dreadful blaſphemous abomination, ſo frequently belched forth in theſe dayes of Satans power,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.16. <hi>Luk.</hi> 29.13. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.26. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.25. <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.8.</note> hath our eternal King left his Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al will and pleaſure upon Record, as a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain rule for his Subjects to walk by, till his ſecond Perſonal appearance, denoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing <hi>Anathema</hi> to all ſuch as ſhall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to preſcribe any other rule, or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend any voyce or viſion, revelation or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration, beſide or againſt this ſure word of Propheſie.</p>
                  <p>Here we ſee the tranſcendent excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and unparallel'd Dignity of theſe glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Witneſſes of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt; upon this ſure foundation we are built; to
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:35245:18"/>this ſure Word we do well if we take heed, it being the Character of a truly bleſſed man to make theſe teſtimonies his delight, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1.2.</note> and to meditate herein continually, abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Witchcrafts, Sorceries, and cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly deviſed Fables of ſuch as come with all plauſible, ſweet, affable carriage, and mild pleaſant behaviour, lieing in wait all the while to deceive with inticing words ſmooth as oyl, ſaluting the Lord Jeſus Chriſt with a <hi>Hail King of the Jews, thou art moſt excellent, the chief of ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand, full of grace are thy lips; pleaſant, yea moſt lovely is thy voyce; all thy odours are fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grant, therefore the Virgins love thee,</hi> and the like expreſſions: Here's a beautiful cup indeed: who would dream there ſhould be any Poyſon in it? But amongſt all theſe heavenly truths, comes up ſecret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly one little horn, or a beaſt having two horns like the Lamb, but he ſpeaks like the Dragon, bringing in ſuch an expreſſion as this (as he finds a fit opportunity when he hath pretty well wrought upon his Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditory) <hi>Oh ſaith he</hi> (of Chriſt) <hi>thou art the moſt glorious Creature in heaven or earth; who would not run after thee, who would not be raviſht with thine excellency thou chief among all the Gods? &amp;c.</hi> And now hath many a
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:35245:19"/>filly fiſh ſwallowed this pleaſant bait, hook and all, and little dreams of a foundation here laid to deſtroy the divinity, and eternal diety of Chriſt, and to make him a Creature-God.</p>
                  <p>Theſe Jeſuitical Principles are plainly detected in ſome that would go for Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel preachers in theſe daies; whom the Lord Jeſus (whom they thus diſhonour) will ſhortly conſume with the breath of his Noſtrils, and utterly deſtroy with the brightneſs of his comming, except they repent.</p>
                  <p>But to return, having cleerly (as I conceive) proved the holy Scriptures, or two Teſtaments to be the two Witneſſes of Chriſt, or the two Olive-trees ſpoken of, by <hi>Zachary,</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> I deſcend to the other concluſions mentioned, as,</p>
                  <p>Secondly, That the Candleſticks are the Churches of the Saints; which in <hi>Zechary's</hi> time was but one National Church of the Jews, and therefore by him ſaid to be but one Candleſtick; but in Saint <hi>Johns</hi> time they are ſometimes called two, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Zech.</hi> 4.2. <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.4.1.20. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.33.</note> ſometimes ſeven, that is, many ſeveral Congregations of Saints, ſpringing from the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, (the Root of the Olive tree, or the bowle of the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:35245:19"/>Candleſtick) being daughters of that heavenly mother, <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> that is above, <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>.26. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.15. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 12.22.</note> or the whole family in heaven and earth, the general aſſembly and Church of the firſt born; the ſeveral congregated Churches in Goſpel order, as ſo many Branches of this great Candleſtick; which alſo are themſelves called Candleſticks, growing and increaſing by the heavenly Artifice of thoſe Inſtruments that Chriſt hath deſigned for this building, till we all come in the unity of the faith,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.13.</note> and the knowledge of the Son of God, unto a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect man, unto the meaſure of the ſtature of the fulneſs of Chriſt; and this is the Catholique or univerſal Church; and not any other Churches (neither National, Provincial, or any other deviſe of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt) have the leaſt appearance in the Goſpel, ſave only (I ſay) thoſe parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular congregated Churches which <hi>are planted together in the likeneſs of his death,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 6 5.</note> being as ſo many ſimilar parts of this uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Church of Chriſt, his compleat glorious body.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, The two Branches of the two Olive-trees are the Doctrine and Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline of the Churches; theſe two are the Rod, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 23 4.</note> and the ſtaffe with which the Lord
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:35245:20"/>did lead and feed his ſervant <hi>David;</hi> and when the abominable wickedneſs of thoſe Idol Shepheards (which he placed over his ancient People) was ripe for deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Zech.</hi> 11.7.</note> the Lord himſelf (pittying the Flock that had eſcaped the ſlaughter of thoſe wicked Shepheards) takes his beautiful ſtaff of Doctrine, and his ruling Rod of Diſcipline, and with theſe he feeds the poor of the Flock, till by their ingratitude and high provocations, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Acts</hi> 13.46.</note> rebelliouſly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecting the tenders of Grace, and the word of Salvation, they ſo exceedingly incen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Lord againſt them, that he takes his beautiful ſtaff of Doctrine and cuts it aſunder; and it was broken in that day, when the dreadful word was uttered, <hi>Lo we turn to the Gentiles:</hi> Now was the Doctrine of ſalvation (which they had ſo long ſlighted and abuſed) hid from their eyes, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luk.</hi> 19.42.</note> of which the Lord Jeſus had warned them with ſtrong cryes and tears, (as pittying the obſtinacy of this his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.) Indeed there remained yet among them ſome external forms and ſhadows; a body without a ſoul, a Lanthern with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Candle: The rod of Diſcipline, (or ſtaff of Bands) was not yet broken, and this they reſted on, crying, <hi>The Temple of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:35245:20"/>the Lord, The Temple of the Lord;</hi> but (as they regarded not, ſo) the knowledge of the moſt High was departed from them, and at laſt a total rejection and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute excluſion of this rebellious people by the Lords breaking his other ſtaff of bands; and this was done by the deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of that Temple they ſo much truſted in, and ſo groſly abuſed by Prophaneſs and Idolatry.</p>
                  <p>Thus was the prediction of our bleſſed Lord fulfilled by <hi>Veſpatian</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> (fourty yeers after his Aſcention) when the Temple being fired, could not poſſibly be quenched by any induſtry of man; yea, ſo eminently and remarkably did the hand of God appear againſt this Place and Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that the heathen <hi>Titus</hi> confeſſed, That he had only lent his hands and help to God in this work.</p>
                  <p>Now did the Lord give them a bill of divorce, upon which they were expoſed to ſuch direful plagues and woful miſeries, as never befel to any People, as Hiſtories do abundantly teſtifie; <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.21.</note> (according to the Scriptures.)</p>
                  <p>And thus I have delivered what I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend to be the ſence and meaning of the two Branches of the two Olive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trees,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:35245:21"/>namely the Doctrine and Diſcipline of the Scriptures, which pour out of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves that golden oyl continually, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Zech</hi> 4.12. <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.6.</note> by which the Churches of Chriſt are fed in all Ages.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, The laſt general concluſion, from this fourth of <hi>Zechary,</hi> is, that the golden Pipes are the Miniſters of the Churches, through which the golden Oyl is conveighed from the two Olive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trees (the two Teſtaments) by the branches of Doctrine and Diſcipline, into the Candleſtick (the Church) to feed and nouriſh her. <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.6.</p>
                  <p>Theſe Pipes in the ſecond Verſe of this fourth of <hi>Zechary,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Zech.</hi> 4.2.</note> are ſaid to be ſeven, which in the twelfth Verſe are called <hi>The eyes of the Lord, which run too and fro through the whole Earth.</hi> Now what theſe ſeven eyes are, may be found out by that means which the Lord Jeſus hath appointed, <hi>viz.</hi> ſearching the Scriptures.</p>
                  <p>S. <hi>John</hi> will tell us that theſe ſeven eyes ſent forth into all the Earth,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.6. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.4. <hi>Rev.</hi> 8.2.</note> 
                     <hi>are the ſeven Spirits of God which are before his Throne, &amp; that theſe thus ſtanding before him, are the ſeven Angels with Trumpets:</hi> which are none other then the Miniſters of the Churches, as they are plainly called, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.20.</p>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:35245:21"/>
                  <p>They are called the ſeven Spirits, becauſe as they are abundantly filled, ſo they are imployed by the Spirit which ſo mightily over-powers them, that they ſeem many times to be nothing but Spirit, taking their denomination from the moſt noble part in them, which is the Spirit, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>Not 1, <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.10. <hi>Act.</hi> 15.28. <hi>Mat.</hi> 5 14.</note> but the grace of God which was with me.</hi> Theſe ſeven eyes are the light of the world, appointed by the Lord Jeſus (that corner ſtone upon which they ſtand, <hi>Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chary</hi> 3.9.) for the building of his Church, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.11, 12, 13. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.6, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </note> for the perfecting of his Saints, for the work of the Miniſtry, for the edifying of the body of Chriſt. And theſe ſeven are thus diſtinguiſhed in the holy Scriptures (thoſe faithful Witneſſes of truth.)</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. <hi>Prophets.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. <hi>Apoſtles.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. <hi>Evangeliſts.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>4. <hi>Paſtours.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>5. <hi>Teachers.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>6. <hi>Ruling Elders.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>7. <hi>Deacons.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p>Theſe are the ſeven ſorts of Officers, or ſeven Pillars, that the Lord Jeſus Chriſt (the wiſdom of the Father, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Prov.</hi> 9.1. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2 9.</note>) hath hewn out for the building of his great houſe the Church.</p>
                  <p>Theſe are his golden Pipes, ſo called by
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:35245:22"/>the Spirit of the Lord, as conveighing this precious liquor, this divine Treaſure of the heavenly word for nouriſhment to the poor Church as well in her Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs condition, as in all Ages; though theſe bleſſed inſtruments of Chriſt term themſelves but earthen Veſſels, that ſo the excellency of this heavenly Treaſure which is conveighed through them, <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.7.</note> may the more redound to the glory of God, yet the Spirit cals them golden Pipes.</p>
                  <p>Theſe ſeven mentioned in the ſecond Verſe, are more comprehenſively reduced unto two golden Pipes, verſ. 12. anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able whereunto thoſe ſeven ſorts of Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers mentioned, are comprehended un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the two chief; <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.20.</note> that is, <hi>Apoſtles and Prophets, upon whoſe foundation we are built, Jeſus Chriſt himſelf being the chief corner Stone.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And thus I ſuppoſe it is evident, that I have not preſumed without clear warrant from the Law and the Teſtimony to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm;</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>That the two Olive-trees are the two Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaments, or thoſe Witneſſes of Chriſt appointed to feed the Church, as in all Ages, ſo through the whole courſe of Papal Perſecution,</hi> viz. <hi>one thouſand two hundred and threeſcore years.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:35245:22"/>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>That the Candleſticks are the Churches of the Saints.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>That the two Olive-branches are Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and Diſcipline.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. <hi>That the golden Pipes are the Miniſters of the Churches.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="verse">
                  <head>The fifth Verſe.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And if any man will hurt them, fire proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth out of their mouth, and devoureth their Enemies; and if any man will hurt them, he muſt on this manner be killed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Pope and his Paraſites had power enough, and did exerciſe that power to the utmoſt, in killing and ſpoyling, torment<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and harraſing the poor Saints in this time of their exile; and therefore the Saints cannot poſſibly be the Witneſſes, as ſome have conceived; many a precious ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant of Jeſus loſt his life for the Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes ſake, that is for holding cloſe to the Law &amp; to the Teſtimony, (thoſe Witneſſes of Chriſt) againſt the Antichriſtian Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of their bloody perſecutors; but to the wonder and amazement of the World, (&amp; to the high praiſes of our God, be it for ever acknowledged) they had no power to overcome or ſuppreſs the Scriptures
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:35245:23"/>till toward the end of their propheſie, or fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing their teſtimony in Sackcloth.</p>
                  <p>I know many had an earneſt deſire to deſtroy them; they wanted no will to the work, but maugre all their rage and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, though they dig'd as deep as Hell, leaving no ſtone unturnd that might ſeem to conduce to the ſupport of their Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical Antichriſtian State: yet whether they judged the Scriptures of no weight, or ſlighting them as below the glory of their Babel; or whether the terror of the Curſe, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.18.</note> like fire in their bones deterred them, or what other ſecret operation it was, I know not: but by the mighty power of God, theſe heavenly Witneſſes have been wonderfully preſerved in this Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loniſh Captivity, through the whole courſe of their Propheſie in Sackcloth 1260 years.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="verse">
                  <head>The ſixth Verſe.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Theſe have power to ſhut heaven, that it rain not in the days of their Propheſie; and have power over waters to turn them into bloud, and to ſmite the earth with all plagues, as often as they will.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>While the Saints are in <hi>Goſhen,</hi> the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:35245:23"/>of Antichriſt is ſmitten with ſundry plagues (the effects of the Saints prayers) but none ſo dreadful as that univerſal thick darkneſs that ſoon over-ſpred the whole Land of the Beaſt: <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.10.</note> while the holy Spouſe of Chriſt (troden under-foot) enjoys the light of her Beloveds ſhining face, to whom it is given to know the myſtery of the Kingdom of God, but the ſcarlet Strumpet in the midſt of all her brags, (that ſhe is no widdow but the wife of Chriſt, that her eldeſt ſon is his Vicar, that ſhe is Infallible and cannot be deceived,) is given up to a ſpirit of ſlumber and ſtrong deluſions, to believe lyes; <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mark.</hi> 4.11.</note> that ſeeing they might ſee and not perceive, and hearing they might hear and not underſtand, leſt at any time they ſhould be converted, and their ſins ſhould be forgiven them.</p>
                  <p>No dew of Grace deſcends upon thoſe curſed Families; the waters of the San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary are now by little and little ſtopt from them; at firſt, the great burning Mountain (the Beneficence of the great <hi>Conſtantine</hi>) being caſt into the Sea of <hi>Rome,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rev</hi> 8.8, 9.</note> a third part preſently became blood, and the third part of the Miniſters in that Church (with their adherents) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from the Faith: a while after, the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:35245:24"/>whole Sea was generally poyſoned, and became as the bloud of a dead man;
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rev.</hi> 16 3.</note> and ſo there was an univerſal revolt from the doctrine of ſalvation to lying Fables, vain Superſtitions, Miracles, Signs and Wonders, with all deceivableneſs of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs; and every living foul that drank this poyſon in the Cup of her abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations, preſently dyed.</p>
                  <p>How the fire that proceeded out of the mouthes of the Witneſſes hath devoured their Enemies, and how they have ſmote their Enemies with all manner of plagues, is very remarkable. Multitudes of Examples might be produced, of which take a taſte: Surely the fiery indignation of the Lord hath been wonderfully manifeſted againſt theſe deſperate Antichriſtian Enemies in their curſed Attempts, to race, deface, corrupt, or any way to hurt theſe Divine Witneſſes (the holy Scriptures) in their 1260 years Sackcloth.</p>
                  <p>The Emperour <hi>Valence</hi> (infected with the Arrian Hereſie) oppoſing the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and the Divinity of Chriſt, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ruff. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 13.</note> after a ſhamefull flight before the Enemy, got in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a little houſe, which being ſuddenly ſet on fire, conſumed this curſed miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creant.</p>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:35245:24"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Diocleſian</hi> for burning the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, <note place="margin">Ruff.</note> having been tormented with ſundry diſeaſes in his body, and his houſe burned with fire from Heaven, at laſt (being terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with Thunder) fell mad and killed himſelf.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Olimpus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Carthage</hi> (an Arrian Heretick) blaſpheming the holy Trinity, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Paul Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con. Ann.</hi> 510.</note> was immediately ſtruck dead with a three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forked thunder-bolt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anaſtatius Dicorus</hi> a grievous Enemy to the Lord and his bleſſed Witneſſes,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Zenoras, lib.</hi> 3.</note> (the holy Scriptures) was diſtroyed with Thunder and Lightning.</p>
                  <p>For this ſame deteſtable wickedneſs, the City of <hi>Antioch</hi> was conſumed with fire from Heaven, in the ſeventh yeer of <hi>Juſtinus</hi> the Emperour.</p>
                  <p>Other Hereticks (in the time of Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the Third) denying the Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and defiling the holy Scriptures with Urine, &amp;c. were deſtroyed at once by War and Fire, to the number of 100000.</p>
                  <p>A Treaſurer of <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtate, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Chryſoſt. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 34.</note> as he was mocking and deriding at the holy Word of God, fell a vomiting up his own blood, his privie parts rotting, putrifying, and conſuming with lice; he died therewith moſt miſerably.</p>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:35245:25"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Arrius</hi> (that arch-Heretick) having blaſphemed the Lord Jeſus and his bleſſed Word, <note place="margin">Theodor.</note> and after pretending a recantation of his Errors, and ſubſcribing his name to the truth; from whence having quickly revolted again; he was ſmitten ſuddenly with ſuch horrible pangs in his guts, that ſeeking to eaſe himſelf, his breath was ſtopt, and his guts ran out of his funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ſo he dyed upon his own excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
                  <p>Pope <hi>Leo</hi> the Tenth, a prophane ſcoffer at the holy Scriptures, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Theatr. Judg. pag.</hi> 144.</note> calling the Goſpel a Fable; was in the midſt of his horrible blaſphemies ſurprized by death from the immediate hand of God.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Neſtorius</hi> the Heretick, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ceph. lib.</hi> 3 <hi>cap.</hi> 36.</note> oppoſing the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity of Chriſt, and blaſpheming the Scriptures, (in his baniſhment) was tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented with ſuch a fearful diſeaſe, that his blaſphemous tongue was gnawed in pieces by worms, and the Earth ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned her mouth and ſwallowed him up.</p>
                  <p>Pope <hi>Julius</hi> (a notable deſpiſer of Gods Word, <note place="margin">Pale.</note>) was another like object of his fierce wrath.</p>
                  <p>So <hi>Julian</hi> Apoſtata, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Theodor. lib.</hi> 3 <hi>c.</hi> 11</note> jeering and ſcoffing at <hi>Maries</hi> Son and his bleſſed Word and Ordinances, had his entrals ſecretly
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:35245:25"/>rotted, and vomiting up his excrements he died.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Denterius</hi> (an Arrian Biſhop) baptizing in a blaſphemous manner contrary to the Scripture, <hi>viz. I baptize thee in the Name of the Father through the Son in the holy Ghoſt;</hi> the water ſuddenly vaniſhed: the like alſo befel to <hi>Paulus</hi> a <hi>Novation</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Cerinthus</hi> (the Heretick) obſcuring the everlaſting Goſpel, <note place="margin">Euſcb.</note> was overwhelmed with the ſudden fall of an hot-Houſe.</p>
                  <p>In the year of our Lord 420. many thouſands were diſtroyed for the like in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignities offered to the holy Scriptures, (as an evident teſtimony of the great power of theſe bleſſed Witneſſes.)</p>
                  <p>Doctor <hi>Whittington</hi> (in the raign of <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> the Seventh) having miſerably afflicted a Chriſtian woman in <hi>Chipping-Sadbury</hi> for her uſe of the Scriptures,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Theatr. Judg. pag.</hi> 60, 61.</note> and having paſt the ſentence of death upon her as an Heretick; a Bull breaking looſe from a place far diſtant, ran violently through the throng of people (without hurting any) till he came to the Doctor, thruſting him at the firſt blow through the paunch, and after often goring him, trailed his guts upon his horns about the Street, while the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:35245:26"/>people ſtood aſtoniſhed with admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                  <p>Thus by a few Examples of many that might be produced, is the wrathfull indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of a mighty offended Majeſty evidently demonſtrated againſt ſuch as durſt preſumptuouſly attempt to hurt the bleſſed Witneſſes (the holy Scriptures) during the time of their 1260 years Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie in Sackcloth.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="verse">
                  <head>The ſeventh Verſe. <hi>And when they ſhall he about</hi> (for ſo the word is to be tranſlated) <hi>to finiſh their teſtimony, the Beaſt that aſcendeth out of the bottomleſs Pit, ſhall make war againſt them, and ſhall overcome them, and kill them.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Let us now look back again, and before we ſpeak of the finiſhing; let us conſider diligently, when they began their teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny in Sackcloth.</p>
                  <p>That they began to put on Sackcloth at that time exactly and preciſely, when the Church fled into the Wilderneſs, is cleer, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Apoc.</hi> 12.6.</note> and that they ſhould continue with her (propheſying in Sackcloth) in her exile, <note place="margin">Ibid.</note> and affliction, the whole term of
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:35245:26"/>1260 yeers, is cleer alſo: And I believe there is none (but Papiſts and their Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows) but will readily grant, that the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man is the Primitive Churches,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iſa.</hi> 51.16.61.10.60.19.</note> covered with Chriſt her Husband the true Son of Righteouſneſs, and trampling upon all inferiour ſublunary things,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Acts</hi> 2.45.4.34, <hi>&amp;c. Phil.</hi> 3.7, 8.</note> crowned with her twelve bright infallible Stars, whoſe heavenly Doctrine and Diſcipline made her eminently glorious in thoſe Primitive times, before the forth of mens invention had ſoyled her pure garments, thoſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Robes of Righteouſneſs where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with ſhe was moſt richly adorned by her Royal Husband, looking upon all earthly glory with an eye of ſcorn and contempt.</p>
                  <p>And now her pregnant womb being become fruitful, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iſai.</hi> 54.1.61.10.</note> (and her former barren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs taken away) according to thoſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Promiſes made unto her, <note place="margin">The ten Primitive Perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note> ſhe travels and labors through many a bitter pang of heathen perſecution, crying in pain to be delivered; which that ancient Enemy of mankind perceiving, he ſtands ready before the diſtreſſed, afflicted, perſecuted Church, to devour her child as ſoon as it was born.</p>
                  <p>At the end of three hundred years, her long looked for hour came, when to the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:35245:27"/>exceeding great joy of all true Saints, ſhe was delivered of a Man-child,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ann.</hi> 304.</note> (<hi>viz.</hi> the firſt Chriſtian Emperour <hi>Conſtantine</hi>) who breaking forth like the Sun-beams in glorious raies, for the diſpelling of thoſe diſmal clouds of bloudy perſecution, which had ſo miſerably harraſed the Churches, he openly taking upon him the patronage of the Goſpel, performed moſt glorious exploits for the honour of the Lord Jeſus, and by the martial prowis of a victorious Arm, bleſſed by many wonderful Atchievements, he ruled all the Nations with a Rod of Iron; the weight whereof <hi>Maxentius</hi> and <hi>Licinius</hi> (among many others) did feel to purpoſe.</p>
                  <p>But all this while the Dragon roars won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully, having drawn to his Party the third part of the Stars, endeavouring by all poſſible means to devour this manly Son of the Church, firſt by his inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments <hi>Diocleſian</hi> and <hi>Galerius,</hi> who expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing him to the rage and fury of the <hi>Sama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritans,</hi> and failing herein of their deſign by his unexpected victorious return, they contrived a way to devour him by en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaging him with a Lyon under a pretence of trying his valor; many other ſnares were laid to take away his life; but none
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:35245:27"/>ſo dangerous as that Arrian gulf, wherein the Dragon with the third part of thoſe fallen Stars endeavoured to ſwallow him.</p>
                  <p>From all which curſed deſigns, he was wonderfully, and even miraculouſly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, by that gratious hand, who took him up to his Throne, <hi>viz.</hi> the Royal Thorne of the Empire; the higheſt honor and dignity in the world, and to make his glory compleat indeed, he was (from his former Idolatry) caught up to the chaſt imbraces of the Spouſe of the Lord Jeſus, that bleſſed holy Throne where the great <hi>Jehovah</hi> delighted to ſit; while it conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued pure.</p>
                  <p>To this and all other Churches of Saints, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rev</hi> 8.8. Now was that voyce from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven heard, <hi>viz.</hi> this day is poyſon powred forth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Church, for now Chriſts is death ſlighted; and er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors &amp;c. prevail a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly.</note> he preſently became not only a famous Protector, but a moſt bountifull bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factor; heaping mountains of Royal favours upon them, in ſo much as he is ſuppoſed (through his fervent zeal mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted in wonderfull beneficence) to be that burning Mountain caſt into the ſea, upon which the third part of the ſea of <hi>Rome</hi> ſuddainly became blood, that is the third part of her doctrine, and diſcipline was corrupted by the third part of the Stars that the Dragon drew down after him: which fallen ſtars being now at reſt
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:35245:28"/>and peace, this peace producing plenty, and that luxury, all which beget ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous deſigns, which having the bounty of a Royal Emperor, as a fit object before them, they not knowing how to manage ſuch a proſperous eſtate, having been ſo long preſſed down with cruel perſecutions and deep afflictions, do ſuck in this libera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity with ſo much greedineſs, that they ceaſe not ſwelling till they burſt with it, into ſuch exceſſive pride, pomp, ſtate, cruelty, luxury, and all kind of wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that they force the poor woman, (even as ſoon as ſhe hath but newly brought forth her man-child) to flie into the Wilderneſs, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.5, 6.</note> that is into holes and corners; anywhere to enjoy her Beloved in the purity of his Ordinances, with which ſhe is fed and nouriſhed by her two Witneſſes (the holy Scriptures propheſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Sackcloth with her) 1260 yeers.</p>
                  <p>And now that an open gap might be made for the man of Sin to be ſet up in his Chayr of Peſtilence, the Royal man-child tranſlateth his Imperial Throne from <hi>Rome</hi> to <hi>Conſtantinople;</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.7. Comment of the <hi>London</hi> Miniſters.</note> and ſo the let, ſpoken of by S. <hi>Paul</hi> (being by the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of moſt of the ancient Doctors of the Church, the <hi>Romane</hi> Empire) by this
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:35245:28"/>removal of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> taken out of the way, Pope <hi>Sylveſter</hi> (taking hold of this opportunity of the Emperours abſence,) laden too heavily with many royal favors, layes the foundation of Babel, but yet ſo ſecretly, privily, covertly and obſcure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that a very curious diligent eye could hardly diſcern it in theſe beginnings; and indeed had it not wrought ſo obſcurely and almoſt indiſcernably, it could not have been the Myſtery of Iniquity; and therefore the Prophet <hi>Daniel</hi> (though throughly acquainted with this working of the man of Sin) is brought in, dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently obſerving, and prying very nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly before he could diſcern him; ſo ſecret and obſcure were his beginnings, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Dan.</hi> 11.21. <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.8.</note> hardly ſuſpected of any, as being a horn too little (at firſt) to be feared, but as lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle as it is, it loſeth no time to make it ſelf great, but partly by flatteries &amp; ſubtile in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuations, highly raiſing the ſame &amp; merit of ſuch as were bountiful and liberal to the Churches, vehemently exciting others to the like beneficence, till at laſt he is heightned (by obtaining of Kingdoms and Provinces) to an open diſcovery of himſelf to be that great Antichriſt.</p>
                  <p>Thus in his Infancy he begins to erect
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:35245:29"/>the Chayr of Peſtilence; for no man denyeth (ſaith <hi>Guicciardin</hi>) that the Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation of the Empire, was the firſt cauſe of the Popes Authority.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Hiſt. Trent. pag.</hi> 833. <hi>Hakewil Apol. pag.</hi> 473.</note> For now the people of <hi>Rome</hi> withdrew their obedience from the Emperors, by occaſion of their ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence; and it is the confeſſion of the Jeſuits themſelves, that the Empire was (not only then tranſlated, but even) long ſince diſſolved, and ſo the great Let re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved, and an open door ſet for the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Kingdom to be elevated by degrees to its heigth of impiety, which muſt likewiſe by degrees come to utter ruine and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, as the foundation of <hi>Babel</hi> is now laid upon the tranſlation of the Empire from <hi>Rome;</hi> ſo the poor woman (the true Church of Chriſt perceiving the Myſtery of Iniquity beginning to work) not able to ſide with the pomp, pride, ambition, ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition, and all kinde of wickedneſs, that the moſt are drownd in; ſhe flies into the Wilderneſs; which is no other then the few faithful Saints that kept cloſe to the Rule, aſſociating together in ſome private corners, even in the midſt of <hi>Rome,</hi> (the outward Court,) as alſo many precious ſocieties of Saints did in <hi>London,</hi> and other places in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Wales,</hi> in the late
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:35245:29"/>dayes of bloody Antichriſtian Prelates) giving up themſelves to the Lord, and one to another.</p>
                  <p>Even ſo did this virgin Spouſe of Chriſt keep cloſe to the Faith, holding faſt to her firſt love, being fed and nouriſhed with the pure lively Oracles, (theſe heavenly Witneſſes of Chriſt) in theſe ſecret cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners and retired covert places, in the midſt of <hi>Pergamos</hi> where Satans ſeat was.</p>
                  <p>And this is that Wilderneſs condition and obſcure hiding place, that God pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for her and her Witneſſes, that there ſhe might be ſecurely preſerved from the unfaithful Watch men, who having learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to lord it over Gods Heritage, and to ſmite their fellow ſervants, and to eat and to drink with the drunken, and to abuſe this ſimple Spouſe of Chriſt, and take away her vail; theſe and ſuch like actions as theſe, is the treading underfoot the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly City by theſe degenerate Romiſh Gen. tiles (the outward Court) which are now generally infected with the Arrian Hereſie and other dreadful abominations. <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Taylor. Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert. pag.</hi> 141. 143.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>This is the Revelation of our Engliſh Prophet, <note place="margin">Bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. <hi>Rev. Apoc. p.</hi> 79.</note> who ſaith that
<q>no ſooner did ſome peaceable conditions begin to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, and Heatheniſh Tyranny ceaſe,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:35245:30"/>but ſtraightway did the Biſhops begin to be ſet on fire with ſpiteful diſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, &amp;c.</q> the Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> (even ſo early) boaſting with brags of pride in <hi>Peters</hi> Chayr and ſucceſſion from him, upon whom they affirm the foundations of the Church is laid; and this fooliſh con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit produced that preſumptious Edict, that <hi>Tertullian</hi> (who lived in the third Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tury) condemned; I hear (ſaith he) that there is a peremptory Edict ſet forth of late, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Trap. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. pag.</hi> 291.</note> 
                     <hi>Thus ſaith the chief Prieſt, the Biſhop of Biſhops, &amp;c.</hi> I hate (ſaith <hi>Baſil</hi>) the pride of that Weſtern Church. And thus by this exceſſive pride of theſe Romiſh Gentiles, boaſting of their external glory and luſtre, they do plainly declare to the world that they are none of the true Church hid in this ſecret covert.</p>
                  <p>By all which it is evident, that imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly after the birth of the man-child,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.5.6.</note> the woman fled into the Wilderneſs (or ſecret corners, with her heavenly Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes the ſweet Scriptures of truth) and this is that Inner Temple that was exactly meaſured and prepared by God for her, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.1.</note> where ſhe is fed, nouriſhed, and ſupported by them, through her ſaddeſt, darkeſt, Wilderneſs courſe of 1260 prophetical
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:35245:30"/>dayes, which in Scripture language, is ſo many years, as is cleer by <hi>Ezeck.</hi> 34.6. and other Scriptures.</p>
                  <p>In all which term of time the holy City lies troden underfoot by the Gentiles in the outward Court, even thoſe who were but yeſterday (as it were) come out of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and miſery themſelves, having been the objects of Heathens ſcorn and deriſion, and ſubject to their rage, malice, &amp; cruelty; having obtaind a little reſt, and the ſweet gales of peace now breathing upon them, they turn this grace into wantonneſs and cruelty, ſmiting their fellow ſervants, and lording it over their brethren, even as others do to this day, who think them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the true Churches of Chriſt, rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing them of all external comforts, while they cleave to, and dare not relinquiſh the Goſpels ſimplicity; and ſoo <hi>Rome,</hi> (lately a true Church of Chriſt) is the firſt that preacheth and practiſeth cruelty, force, violence and perſecution.</p>
                  <p>And did <hi>Rome</hi> do ſo? <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Taylor. Libert. pag.</hi> 26.</note> and is <hi>Rome</hi> ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular in theſe ungoſpel-like dealings? have not <hi>Englands</hi> Watch-men learned the ſame leſſon, and pretty well con'd it by heart? Look upon the late Prelats, ſee what their practice was, ſoon after the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:35245:31"/>bloody <hi>Marian</hi> dayes. Many living te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies can yet bear witneſs againſt the monſtrous cruelties of them and their Succeſſors; but they are gone out like the ſnuff of a tallow candle, and no doubt but their name will ſoon periſh, though the ſtinke remain.</p>
                  <p>How happy had it been if <hi>Diotrephes</hi> had periſhed with them! but alas our mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery! our brethren who ſuffered with us under the late Antichriſtian perſecution of the Prelates, have now laid and do already act upon as violent principles of Tyranny and cruelty as either of the former; and had not the Lord wonderfully raiſed up a faithful Magiſtracy for the ſupport of his Saints, baniſhment had been their gentleſt puniſhment.</p>
                  <p>Had it been an open Enemy that had done this, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſa.</hi> 55.13.</note> I could have born it; but it was thou, a man mine equal, my guide and mine acquaintance, with whom I took ſweet counſel, and walked unto the houſe of God in company; this cuts to the quick.</p>
                  <p>All theſe, Pope, Prelates, Presbyters, and ſome mounted a little higher, while they were under the <hi>ferula,</hi> accounted perſecution unlawful; but being out of
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:35245:31"/>the danger of a Pile and a Faggot them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, they quickly change their opinion, and become as bloody perſecutors as their Predeceſſors.</p>
                  <p>But to return, to conſider the exact time when the Witneſſes began to propheſie in Sackcloth, it is cleer, I hope proved by full evidence from Scripture, &amp;c. that no ſooner did the Churches begin to take breath from Heatheniſh Perſecution by the birth of the man-child <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> but the Dragon caſt out of his mouth ſuch a horrible flood of Arrian cruelty, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Clav. Apoc. pag</hi> 47.</note> that (as one ſaith) it did ſeem to equal that of the Heathens, if not far exceed it, while the poor Saints (with a wonderful conſtant reſolution) ſadly ſigh forth this Swan-like Song, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Moulin. Theoph. pag.</hi> 278.</note> 
                     <hi>We are burned for reading the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, while we burn the more in love to read them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Theſe bleſſed Witneſſes (the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures) were at firſt collected by the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial Edicts of the Royal man-child <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> immediately upon his birth (I mean his ſpiritual birth all along) and though many other Writers came in under the names of the Apoſtles, yet only thoſe were received for Authentick, of which evident proof was made to be truly theirs.
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:35245:32"/>And theſe being compleated in one Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumn together, were called the <hi>New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> and joyned to the other Scriptures of <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets, which were called the <hi>Old Teſtament.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>So that now, and not till now, were the <hi>Two Teſtaments</hi> apparantly viſible: For what by reaſon of thoſe ten bloody Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions, their extream poverty, their continual labouring for life, &amp;c. the poor Chriſtians had neither leiſure nor liberty to collect the Scriptures into one Volumn, (they being alſo deprived of that benefit of Printing which we, now enjoy) &amp; withal conſidering the far diſtant places each from other to which the Goſpels and Epiſtles were written, it cannot well be imagined how the poor diſtreſſed Churches ſhould accompliſh ſo great a work as this, of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piling this holy Book; this was a deſign reſerved (and a work only fit) for the royal man-child to accompliſh.</p>
                  <p>So that at this inſtant, the two Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes received the power promiſed to them;
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.3.</note> and no ſooner did they receive this Authority, but preſently they began to propheſie in Sackcloth; <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 304.</note> for now the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> that was lately ſo famous in their ſufferings, raiſed with the proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:35245:32"/>gales of the Emperors breath, do ſail with ſuch a full clew of peace, tranquillity, honor, wealth, &amp;c. that being hereby lul'd faſt aſleep, the grand Enemy who is ever waking and watching for ſuch an oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity, now ſows his curſed tares of Superſtition, Idolatry and Hereſie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them; <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Tulk. Rhem. Teſt. p.</hi> 657. Dr. <hi>Homes</hi> new world <hi>pag.</hi> 14.</note> but ſo ſecretly and cunning<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as is declared, that this Cockatrice did not ſuddenly appear to open view.</p>
                  <p>But preſently theſe tares grew apace (as ill weeds will do) ſo that with eaſe and proſperity they ſoone degenerate into Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror and all kinde of vanity; and as vice encreaſeth,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Hoſea</hi> 4.7. <hi>Brightman. Rev. apoc. pag.</hi> 112.</note> ſo (the foſter mother) the falſe Church encreaſeth, and quickly grows very ample and ſpacious, while the true Church lies hidden, obſcure in corners, with her ſorrowful Witneſſes in ſable Sackcloth; ſo that the major part laying aſide the ſimplicity of the Goſpel, betake themſelves wholly to advance their out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſtate; and the bleſſed Word of Truth, that prohibites affectation of great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, lordlineſs, and outward pomp, is ſlighted, and contemned, by this Apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized Chuch of <hi>Rome,</hi> who being now full and compleat (in their own conceits) lacking nothing, tread underfoot the holy
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:35245:33"/>City, and by degrees mounting from po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty to all outward felicity, and her Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor from being an honeſt poor Miniſter, riſeth to the ſtate of a Lordly Dioceſan Prelate; from thence to be Primate and Metropolitan of <hi>Italy;</hi> and at length by fawning and flatteries he obtaineth the Kingdom, even the Province and City, denominating the Emperor;
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.7. <hi>Dan.</hi> 11.12.</note> and now this Let being taken out of the way, that only obſtructed the Revelation of Antichriſt, the Popiſh Authors (little ſuſpecting their lord god the Pope to be the man) begin to wonder where this king of pride is; what ſhall we ſay (ſaith one) to this, that long ſince the Nations fell away from the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, and yet Antichriſt is not Come? Before the comming of Antichriſt, the Nations were to fall away, <note place="margin">Thomas. Lyra.</note> as we ſee it already done ſaith another; but as their Fore-fathers, the Scribes and Phariſes ſeeing the Scepter departed from <hi>Judah,</hi> wondred that the Meſſias came not, when he was working wonders amongſt them all the while, and they could not diſcern him: Even ſo theſe blind Popiſh Guides were gaping after the Revelation of the ſon of Perdition, when he was all the time of their ſeeking for him (and long
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:35245:33"/>before) ſitting in his Pontificalibus, exalt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf above all that is called God; being mounted by almoſt inſenſible de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees from a little horn,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Fulk. Rhem. Teſt. pag.</hi> 329.</note> &amp; a vile contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible condition to command (as he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends) all the Kings and Kingdoms in the World; as to inſtance a little in ſome par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Zacharias</hi> Pope of <hi>Rome</hi> having depoſed <hi>Childerick</hi> King of <hi>France,</hi> and abſolved his Subjects from their Oath of Fealty, he gave the Kingdom to <hi>Pipin,</hi> who afterward he made to kiſs his feet.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Gregory</hi> the Second, excommunicated the Emperor <hi>Leo</hi> the Third, becauſe he was an enemy to Images; and while the good Emperor was caſting down theſe Idols, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Field</hi> of the Church, <hi>pag.</hi> 623.</note> this ſon of Perdition made Decrees for the people to revolt from their obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to him.</p>
                  <p>Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the Seventh, depoſed <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth, and made him, his wife and child, wait three dayes bare-foot at his Palace Gate.</p>
                  <p>What ſhall be ſaid to that exceſſive pride of Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the Third, treading upon the neck of <hi>Fredrick</hi> the Emperor, ſpurning from the head of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Imperial Crown, making others
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:35245:34"/>hold his bridle, his ſtirrop, kiſs his feet? the Emperors being water to waſh his hands, carry the firſt Diſh to his Table, bear his Cup, his Train, carry him upon their ſhoulders, &amp;c. call him our lord god the Pope; yea to this day, the Elect Emperors by order are to worſhip the Pope at his Coronation.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Paul</hi> the Third ſaid, that he was above all Princes in the World; that he could change Kingdoms at his pleaſure; that no Prince ſhould be his Companion, but all Subjects under his feet, as it was fit they ſhould, by the will and appointment of him who had built his Church upon <hi>Peter</hi> his Predeceſſor; that he would die, over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw all, and ſet the World on fire, rather then be baſe; and yet as much as he ſcornd baſeneſs, he was not aſham'd nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid of that deſperate ſin of Perjury, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Boniface</hi> went in Proceſſion attired with the Crown Imperial.</p>
                  <p>Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the Sixth, was ſo en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged with burning luſt to his own Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that he could not endure any man to enjoy her but himſelf, and therefore he diſſolved her Marriage from two Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands, that ſo he might wholly engroſs her to his Inceſtuous luſt, which yet he
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:35245:34"/>fell ſhort of; for his own two Sons, the Duke of <hi>Candia,</hi> and Cardinal of <hi>Valentia,</hi> did alſo ſhare with their Father in the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtuous enjoyment of their Siſter, for whoſe ſake <hi>Valentia</hi> murthered his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
                  <p>Yea, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>In Vita Pauli</hi> 5.</note> ſo generally wicked and abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble were the Popes of <hi>Rome,</hi> that <hi>Papirius Maſſonius</hi> (a Popiſh Writer) ſaith, no man expects any ſanctity in Popes now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayes; they are thought to be excellent Popes if they have never ſo little honeſty, or be not ſo wicked as other men uſe to be. Is it not miraculous that the great and holy God, the fountain of Juſtice hath ſo long endured ſuch dreadful and abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble wickedneſs? If it be ſaid that ſome Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> were accounted holy men, in the fourth and fifth Century, and ſome Councels of thoſe times were well approved of; and therefore Antichriſts riſing could not be ſo early as the yeer 304.</p>
                  <p>I anſwer: Antichriſt and his kingdom, is the Myſtery of Iniquity (as hath been ſhewed,) and therefore the Prophet <hi>Daniel</hi> conſidereth diligently, and ſearcheth curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly before he could eſpie him, ſo dark &amp; obſcure were his beginnings, in ſheeps
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:35245:35"/>cloathing, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat.</hi> 7 15. <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.11. <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.24.</note> with horns like a Lamb, yet ſpake like a Dragon, and raven'd like a Wolfe.</p>
                  <p>Neither do I believe that all the Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> immediately after <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> had knowledge of what they did (as to the furtherance of this work of darkneſs) or that their ſeat was the Chayr of Peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence. Nay, I do think that ſome of them did with great confidence abominate, and would with abundance of zeal and reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, have deteſted the thought of being inſtrumental in the ſetting up of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt.</p>
                  <p>The Jews and Gentiles that put the Lord of glory to a ſhameful death, <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.8.</note> little knew what they did; <note place="margin">2 <hi>King</hi> 8.12.13.</note> when the Prophet <hi>Eliſha</hi> fore-told <hi>Hazael</hi> of that horrible wickedneſs that he ſhould do to the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> he was amazed at the thought of ſuch abominations, &amp; replyed with great reſolution in deteſtation of it, <hi>But what is thy ſervant a dog, that he ſhould do this great thing!</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Acts</hi> 22.4.</note> Little did <hi>Paul</hi> think what he was about when he was going to <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſcus</hi> againſt the Saints.</p>
                  <p>I dare not think that all the Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> did promote this work knowingly and reſolvedly; it is cleer that <hi>Gregory</hi>
                     <pb n="65" facs="tcp:35245:35"/>oppoſed <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> in his at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt to be made univerſal Biſhop; and I believe he little dreamd how irrecovera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly the Chayr he ſate in was poyſoned with the infection: <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Trap. Comment. pag.</hi> 292.</note> And yet tis well known that himſelf did moſt baſely inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuate, and earneſtly deſire the ſame title from the bloody Emperour <hi>Phocas.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Brightman</hi> conſidering the monſtrous pride and worldly pomp that followed upon the Enjoyments of that glorious peace that was now eſtabliſhed, thinks it no great wonder that this defection ſhould ſo ſlily creep in, even whilſt they were fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent in promoting and advancing Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity; becauſe that at the ſame inſtant, many were ſwoln big with contentions, others gaped after honors, ſome were delivered of deſperate hereſies,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rev. Apoc. pag.</hi> 112.</note> and the Generality heaped up ſuperſtitions with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out meaſure.</p>
                  <p>And all this while the obſcurity of the true Churches encreaſed every day more and more; the ſimple plaineſs and ſincere purity of the Scriptures were more and more ſlighted, defiled, obſcured, wre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted and perverted by idle and fond Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gories, and abſurd Expoſitions; Reliques were adored, and Religion placed in
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:35245:36"/>toys and trifles, while all kind of iniquity got ground.</p>
                  <p>And therefore we may not conceive that the man of ſin was at firſt to be openly manifeſted; for how then ſhould it be a Myſtery of Iniquity? <hi>Rome</hi> was not built in a day; the Myſtery was working in the Apoſtles days, but never got a feat in the Church till the Arrians bore ſway, when the Chriſtian world ſeemd to turn here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique; and though the Chayr of Peſtilence was now erected, and the true Church with her true witneſſes now exiled: yet it was long before the man of ſin was openly diſcovered; for as the true Church of Chriſt (after ſhe had conceived) travailed with child 300. years to bring forth a Chriſtian Emperour, ſo this degenerate Church of <hi>Rome</hi> (the ape of the true Church) travelled alſo 300 yeers, ſtill ſwelling, and by inſenſible degrees growing bigger and bigger, till at laſt ſhe brought forth the ſpurious birth of a univerſal Biſhop; in the reign of the bloody Emperor <hi>Phocas, Anno Dom.</hi> 600. And now is the great Antichriſt open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enthroned at the ſame time when the Empire is divided and broken into ten Kingdoms. <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.12.</note> 
                     <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:35245:36"/>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. <hi>Brittons.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. <hi>Saxons.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. <hi>Franks.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>4. <hi>Burgundians.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>5. <hi>Wiſegothes.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>6. <hi>Swedes.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>7. <hi>Vandals.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>8. <hi>Aſtrogoths.</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Mede A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poc. cap.</hi> 8.</note>
                     </item>
                     <item>9. <hi>Almans.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>10. <hi>Greeks.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p>Of which ten, three fall quickly before the Beaſt according to <hi>Daniels</hi> Propheſie;
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.8. <hi>Park. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phe. p.</hi> 28.</note> and thoſe were the <hi>Greeks, Longobards</hi> and <hi>Franks;</hi> and to theſe, <hi>Pipin</hi> adds another temporal dominion.</p>
                  <p>And now this king of pride, <note place="margin">A brief Expoſition of part of <hi>Dan.</hi> 11.22.</note> (as with the arms of a Flood) bears down all before him, exalts himſelf againſt the Prince of the Covenant, with all power and lying wonders; yea, with all deceivableneſs of unrighteouſneſs: <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Verſ.</hi> 24.</note> Entring upon the fatteſt places of the Provinces; whereupon he founds his Superſtious prophane Abbeys, Nunneries, Monaſteries, &amp;c. where he fats up his Locuſts, thoſe Idols drones, belly-gods, that in huge ſwarms have fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led all his Dominions, even the choyceſt fatteſt places thereof, as is obvious to every eye that will but look upon the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cayed ſuperſtitious Places in our own Land where the Swine have ſwilled: he wageth war with the King of the South,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:35245:37"/>and overcometh all thoſe Southern Kings that dare oppoſe him,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Dan.</hi> 11.25.</note> as <hi>Soliman</hi> in <hi>Aſia, Caſsianus</hi> in <hi>Syria,</hi> the <hi>Egyptian Caliph</hi> in <hi>Judaea;</hi> which exploits were performed by that incarnate Devil <hi>Hilderbrand,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Verſ.</hi> 26. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 28.</note> who returned with great ſpoyls and abundance of Treaſures, he fals on with rage, fury and violent perſecution againſt the poor <hi>Waldenſian</hi> Proteſtants; and at length by open hoſtility he deſtroys many thouſands of this covenanted people, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Verſ.</hi> 30.</note> in a moſt bloody, fierce and cruel War.</p>
                  <p>After this, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Verſ.</hi> 31.</note> is the breaden god, (the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bomination that maketh deſolate) ſet up amongſt them, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Via Tuta, pag.</hi> 118.</note> the Idol doctrine of Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation eſtabliſhed for an Article of Faith,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Verſ.</hi> 32.</note> and the true Sacrifice taken away.</p>
                  <p>In the midſt of all this Pride, Tyranny and Perſecution, the Lord preſerves him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a peculiar people (as in <hi>Elias</hi> time) e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in the heart of <hi>Romes</hi> Dominions; a people that cleave cloſe to the Lord, whom he ſtrengthens in the midſt of their ſorrows, ſo that they do glorious exploits (of the higheſt nature, like the Son of God) while they overcome by ſufferings: Theſe <hi>Waldenſian</hi> Proteſtants were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly that people here ſpoken of, <hi>that know their God and underſtand his will,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Verſ.</hi> 33.</note>
                     <pb n="65" facs="tcp:35245:37"/>and therein inſtruct many thouſands both by doctrine and ſufferings, by the ſword, by flame, by ſpoyl, and by Captivity, whereunto they know they were appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the reſt of their brethren for many daies, even 1260 years, which they go through with wonderful conſtancy, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Verſ.</hi> 34.</note> patience and reſolution.</p>
                  <p>But at laſt they ſhall be holpen with a little help, ſome ſmall weak unlikely means; for what was <hi>Luther, Calvin, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancton,</hi> and a few ſuch in compariſon of that great Potentate, and his Scarlet Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clave? and yet this little help ſtrikes a good ſtroak, &amp; wonderfully refreſheth the poor waſted Churches, but abates little of the pride and cruelty, luxury and abominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Antichriſt, who is ſtill as deſperate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wicked as any of his Predeceſſors; what wickedneſs was formerly acted, that <hi>France, Spain, Italy,</hi> &amp;c. is yet reformed of?</p>
                  <p>Did <hi>Clement</hi> the Sixth poyſon the good Emperour <hi>Lodowick?</hi> Did Pope <hi>Joan (alias Gilberta)</hi> openly diſcover her ſelf to be a notorious Strumpet in the open ſtreet? what may be ſaid to <hi>Ticell,</hi> affirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that though a man ſhould lie with the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> he could by the Popes power freely pardon the ſin.</p>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:35245:38"/>
                  <p>What may be thought of the Tyranny, Perjury, Murther, Extortion, Adultery, Inceſt, and other monſtrous villanies of Pope <hi>John</hi> the Thirteenth, who lay with <hi>Stephana</hi> his Fathers Concubine, defloured ſeveral Virgins, ſet houſes on fire, put out the eyes of <hi>Benedict,</hi> drank to the Devil, &amp;c. What a goodly Tenet was that of <hi>Boni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face,</hi> That whoredom is no more a ſin then the rubbing of the hands together.</p>
                  <p>Theſe and many ſuch like are the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples that grow in that filthy Lake of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> to this day, as they that have any ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience in <hi>Romes</hi> Territories do wel know; what fearful Tragedies, what deſperate villanies, what inhumane beſtialities are ſtill riſe within theſe Confines? ſcarce a night paſſeth, but in moſt Towns of Trade in <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>Italy,</hi> ſeveral loſe their lives; and no wonder, when for a Royal of ſix pence value, a <hi>Brave</hi> will undertake to diſpatch any mans life, and when he hath done, flie but to the Popiſh Church and he is ſecure; how abominably is the Lords day prophaned by Mercats, Plays, &amp;c. what multitudes of filthy Stews doth this man of Sin yeerly receive vaſte ſums of money from, for their al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance? God forbids whoredom, and
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:35245:38"/>appoints marriage: the Pope that he may ſhew himſelf to the life to be Antichriſt, expreſly forbids marriage, and allows whoredom.</p>
                  <p>But this ſin is venial (indeed they ſay) in compariſon of that more dreadfull, beaſtly, Sodomitical abomination main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained amongſt them, and defended in books, and prayſed in Songs, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>A Cardinal ſeeing two men led to Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution, ſaid they ſhould not die; but he would deſire their lives of the Duke his Brother; when it was told him what villany they had committed, The one be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a wretched Murtherer, he ſet him free, but the other being condemned for Sodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, he preſently cryed, <hi>Away with him to Execution! Baſe Peaſant that dare preſume to meddle with the pleaſures of a Prince.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Of the like ſtamp was that other Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, who having a Bitch, that he had long abuſed himſelf with, and the Bitch at laſt dying, he buryed her with much coſt in his Garden, and built a ſtately Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment over her, and upon it wrote theſe two lines:
<q>
                        <l>This Tomb for thee dear Bitch I builded have,</l>
                        <l>Who fitter wert for Heaven then a grave.</l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:35245:39"/>
                  <p>But how have I forgot my ſelf in raking this filthy Jakes; but the abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable wickedneſs that mine eyes have ſeen practiſed amongſt them (with much, much more) hath even forced this digreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion from me.</p>
                  <p>I ſhall now return to the further diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of this man of Sin from the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth of <hi>Daniels</hi> Propheſie. Who was ſo far from Reformation upon the diſcovery of Light by <hi>Luther,</hi> (that little help ſpoken of) that now he grows more enraged, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Dan.</hi> 11.34.</note> mad and fierce then ever, witneſs thoſe horrible butcheries, Maſſacres, Martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms of poor Saints in <hi>Germany,</hi> and other places.</p>
                  <p>What? ſuch a contemptible fellow as <hi>Luther,</hi> preſume to meddle with his Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let Holineſs, that exalteth himſelf above every God; yea, magnifieth himſelf and ſpeaketh marvellous things againſt the God of gods! <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Verſ.</hi> 36.</note> for what God commands expreſly in his ſacred Law, they can eaſily finde ſome device or other to evade, or elſe to diſpence with; whereas the commands of this ſon of perdition muſt be exactly obeyed, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Europae ſpec. p.</hi> 52.</note> and the breach of any of them (eſpecially his late twelve diabolical Trent Articles) accounted a ſin unpardonable.</p>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:35245:39"/>
                  <p>And thus he muſt go on and proſper till the indignation be accompliſhed;
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Dan.</hi> 11.36.</note> for before this Scoene changes, it is ſo deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined by the Higheſt, that he muſt over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the bleſſed Witneſſes, as will be cleerly proved.</p>
                  <p>Neither ſhall he regard any God, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Verſ.</hi> 37.</note> nor the deſire of women (in a lawful way.)</p>
                  <p>His Forces and ſtrong Holds are the gods he reſts upon; <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Verſ.</hi> 38.</note> his ſumptuous Monaſteries and ſwarms of Locuſts, in them are his ſtrength; the great riches (gold, ſilver, precious ſtones, and pleaſant things) that by the ſuperſtitious devotion of his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luded Creatures have been offered to Pictures and Images are his delight; and thus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e muſt frolick it according to the Wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d, till he be ripe for deſtruction, which will eminently begin at the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the Witneſſes.</p>
                  <p>The reſidue of this eleventh Chapter of <hi>Daniel</hi> foretels, that the Turk ſhall invade Antichriſt on the one hand, and the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour of <hi>Germany</hi> on the other hand, with their various exploits. <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Dan.</hi> 11.44.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>But while this ſon of perdition is thus embroyled in fierce Wars; tidings out of the Eaſt ſhall trouble him, that is, the Jews (the Kings of the Eaſt) being now
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:35245:40"/>moved by the Spirit of God to return to their own Land (before whom the great River <hi>Euphrates</hi> is dryed up, to make way for them to their ancient habitation) this news ſhall ſo exceedingly amaze them, that now theſe great Enemies, Turk, Pope, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ezech.</hi> 33. <hi>&amp;</hi> 39. <hi>Chapters. Zach.</hi> 14.2.</note> &amp;c. (that have ſo long kept the poor Jews in ſlavery) ſhall joyn their Forces altogether, and go forth with one conſent to deſtroy with great fury this poor di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed unarmed people;
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Dan.</hi> 11.45.</note> and having now begirt and ſurrounded them in the holy Land, with intent to devour them at once, as being now fully in their power in the midſt of this miſerable, helpleſs, hopeleſs condition, up ſtands <hi>Michael</hi> the great glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Prince, diſcomfits this great and mighty Hoſt, and delivers his diſtreſſed ancient people out of their hands; and not only ſo, but he alſo puts ſuch courage into his peoples ſpirits, that they fall upon their Enemies, and obtain a wonderful Victory; all their oppreſſors by this mighty Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt being now made their Captive ſlaves according to promiſe. <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iſai.</hi> 14.2.</note> This is that glorious day in which the Lord Jeſus Chriſt by the brightneſs of this his glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous appearance will utterly diſtroy this man of ſin.</p>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:35245:40"/>
                  <p>And thus from the eleventh Chapter of <hi>Daniel</hi> we have had a ſhort ſurvey of the riſe, raign, and ruine of Antichriſt; of which we may have a more full diſcovery afterwards.</p>
                  <p>I ſhall now return to proſecute the ſtory of the bleſſed Witneſſes, as they are now about to lay aſide their Sackcloth. <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Dan.</hi> 5.1.2, 3, 4, 5.</note> Now while Antichriſt is in the midſt of his pomp, power, and ruffe of Pride, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſing (like <hi>Belſhazzar</hi>) the holy things of the Lords Temple, feaſting, and prayſing his gods of ſilver and gold, in this his heigth of jollity, comes forth the hand writing againſt him; for now by the appearance of <hi>Luther, Calvin, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancton, &amp;c.</hi> he perceives that the Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes are about to finiſh their Teſtimony; wherefore he adreſſeth him with all power and policy to overcome them: Let us therefore more diligently enquire;</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Of the time when theſe bleſſed Witneſſes were to finiſh their Teſtimony.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Of the nature of the War made by An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt againſt them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>How they were overcome and killed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. <hi>The preciſe time when they were over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Firſt, The woman began to creep out of
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:35245:41"/>corners, and her faithful Witneſſes to leave their Sackcloth, at that time when the little help (wherewith they were holpen) appeared in <hi>Luther, <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Dan.</hi> 11.34.</note> Calvin,</hi> &amp;c. by whoſe endeavors (bleſſed be the Lord) the holy Scriptures riſing from the dark Dens of obſcurity wherein they had ſo long con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued, feeding the Church in her Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs condition, began now to draw near to the finiſhing of their teſtimony in Sack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloth. <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Clav. Apoc. pag.</hi> 115.</note> Now do many Princes, Provinces, and Kingdoms renounce communion with Antichriſt, and embrace the Goſpel of ſalvation, breathing in life and glory to their ſouls: But it muſt be conſidered that their Sackcloth is not yet laid aſide; they are yet but about (in the way) to finiſh their Teſtimony; the day only begins to break, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.17.</note> and Romiſh ſhadows to flie away.</p>
                  <p>For now the Beaſt laies about him to purpoſe; how doth he rage, and tear, curſe, and blaſpheme? how do his roaring Buls and thundring Anathema's flie about the World? now he declares himſelf Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt to the life, ſhewing himſelf as god (nay, above all that is called God,) ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving Subjects from their Allegiance, promiſing heaven to murtherers to deſtroy Princes, caſting others to the Devil by
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:35245:41"/>Excommunications, that either counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, encourage, or embrace the Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments by whom the holy Scriptures are brought to light.</p>
                  <p>And becauſe it was hoped that a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Councel might be a means to obtain a right underſtanding of differences; how many ſhifts and ſtratagems are found to divert it?
<note place="margin">Conſ. Trid. Epiſt.</note> the Pope and his Creatures be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as fearful of a general Councel, as our late Prelates were of a Parliament; for they had ſome ground to ſuſpect that their pomp, and pride, and luxury would hereby be detected; but when it was reſolved upon, what devices, what ſubtilties were contrived to procure a majority of voyces; and thus the pretended Vicars of Chriſt are found the moſt pernicious Juglers in the world. At the length after 24 years ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation, the curſed Conventicle of <hi>Trent</hi> was jumbled together, <hi>Ann.</hi> 1545. not to redreſs thoſe foul enormities complain'd of, but to overcome and ſuppreſs the Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, now about to finiſh their Teſtimony, which is the firſt thing.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, The nature of the War made by Antichriſt againſt the holy Scriptures, is lively deſcribed, <hi>Dan.</hi> 11.36. <hi>And the King ſhall do according to his will,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Dan.</hi> 11.36.</note> and he ſhall
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:35245:42"/>exalt himſelf, and magnifie himſelf above every God, and ſhall ſpeak marvellous things againſt the God of gods.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This War then is his blaſpemous lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage and curſed Decrees againſt the Scriptures,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rhem. Teſt. Preſ. Sect.</hi> 7.</note> while under a pretence of a high eſteem and reverence of them, he cuts out their tongues, and ſuffers not the people to have them in their own lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage; thus with all deceivableneſs of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs, with the kiſs of a <hi>Judas,</hi> and the ſalute of a <hi>Joab,</hi> he ſtabs theſe bleſſed Witneſſes under the fifth rib, belching forth theſe daggers of deſtruction againſt the holy Scriptures, that there are in them a thouſand lyes, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Acts and Mon. Epiſt. Via Tuta, pag.</hi> 289.</note> that they are dead Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters without life, a ſhell without a kernel, a leaden rule, <hi>Sphinx</hi> his Riddles, a wood of Thieves, a ſhop of Hereticks, imperfect, obſcure, full of perplexities: with theſe weapons the man of Sin fighteth againſt the holy Scriptures, <hi>ſpeaking great words againſt the moſt High,</hi> (one of the Scarlet crew cryes out before the Pope, <hi>Fie upon Peter, fie upon Paul,</hi> with a great deal more of ſuch blaſpemous ſtuff.) <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.25. <hi>Eraſm. de Lat. Conc. lib.</hi> 3.</note> And that he may throughly declare himſelf to be that great Antichriſt, he daringly meets the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus at his own weapons.</p>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:35245:42"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I will make war and fight with mine ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies Gog and Magog, <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Apoc.</hi> 2.16.19.15.</note> with the ſword of my mouth,</hi> ſaith Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I will make war againſt mine enemies the Scriptures, with the Sword of my mouth,</hi> ſaith Antichriſt.</p>
                  <p>And he is as big as his word, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Hiſt. Coun. Trent.</hi> 155.</note> witneſs their accurſed dealing with the Scriptures in their Conventicle of <hi>Trent;</hi> where, though clear proof was made of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of the Hebrew and Greek Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals (to the full ſence whereof they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs the Latin cannot attain) yet leſt the cauſe ſhould be yielded to the Proteſtants, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rhem. pref. ſect.</hi> 57. <hi>Counc. Tre. pag.</hi> 156.</note> the vulgar Latin is preferred, and they pronounced Hereticks that refuſe it.</p>
                  <p>And it is there blaſphemouſly aſſerted, that the Holy Ghoſt, who did dictate the Scriptures to Prophets and Apoſtles in Hebrew and Greek, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pag.</hi> 156.</note> doth as truly dictate to the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> the vulgar Latin, as more beloved then the reſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">158.</note>That there can be no hope of ending controverſies, if popular Licence be gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to read the Scriptures.</p>
                  <p>That the Doctrines of Faith were ſo well cleared by the Pope and School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, that we ought no more to learn them out of Scripture.</p>
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:35245:43"/>
                  <p>That it was (indeed) formerly read in the Church, for inſtruction of the people: but now it was needleſs to ſtudy it any more.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">159.</note>That Scriptures muſt be interpreted, <note place="margin">C. Cuſanus.</note> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to what articles of faith are eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed by the Church.</p>
                  <p>That the Church may vary in Expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Scripture according to the times.</p>
                  <p>That it was fit to bridle the ſawcineſs of ſuch as ſhould attempt to add any good thing to former Expoſitions of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">160.</note>That if any thing were diſcovered to any ſingular ſpirit,
<note place="margin">C. Facceco.</note> he ſhould be enforced to conceal it.</p>
                  <p>And after all theſe and ſuch like deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate blaſphemies againſt the Scriptures, their Latin Tranſlation is approved, and none other to be received; And upon pain of Hereſie it is forbid to ſay there are Errors in it; <note place="margin">161.</note>and that none ſhall dare to refuſe it, though it be plainly proved that they have blaſphemouſly corrupted the Text in many things (in that corrupt tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation) as changing <hi>Ipſe</hi> into <hi>Ipſa,</hi> thereby to make way for their Idolizing the bleſſed Virgin. <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Fulk Cont. Mart. p.</hi> 19</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Their deſperate wounding the 4. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:35245:43"/>reading it in this Diabolical Dialect, <hi>Remember to ſanctifie the holy dayes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the Latin Bible upon <hi>Deut.</hi> 4. <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Via tuta, pag.</hi> 280.</note> where it is obſerved, that God forbids the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of Graven Images, their Jeſuitical <hi>Index Expurgatorius</hi> hath caſt it out; as all ſee they have moſt ſhameleſly dealt with all the writings of the Fathers; <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rhem. Teſt. pag.</hi> 328.</note> which hath provoked Doctor <hi>Fulk</hi> to exclaim againſt them, <hi>Out upon you Antichriſtian Hereticks, void of all truth and honeſty.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But their ſhameful and blaſphemous re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches of theſe heavenly Witneſſes, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed all bounds of civility and humanity, charging them with inextricable obſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, inſufficient, imperfect, and what not.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Paul</hi> muſt be cenſured for a hot-headed perſon, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Europ. spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culum, pag.</hi> 164, 165.</note> of whoſe aſſertions there is no great reckoning to be made; that 'tis dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous to read him, <note place="margin">Fulk Rhem. Teſt. Epiſt. to the Qu.</note> as ſavouring of He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie; upon theſe and ſuch like pious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſions the Sacred Bible hath the honour of the firſt place in their Catalogue of Books prohibited;
<note place="margin">Via Tuta.</note> theſe Monſters endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to their utmoſt power to hinder that any ſound of Scripture ſhould poſſeſs the people.</p>
                  <p>This is the nature of that curſed war,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:35245:44"/>raiſed by the Beaſt againſt the Scriptures, as they are about to finiſh their Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony.</p>
                  <p>What ſhall be given unto thee, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 120.3, 4.</note> or what ſhall be done unto thee, (for this thy Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy) thou falſe tongue?</p>
                  <p>What reward ſhalt thou have for the marvelous things thou haſt done againſt the moſt High? <hi>Sharp Arrows of the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, with coals of Juniper.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thirdly, the manner how theſe heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Witneſſes were overcome and killed, muſt not be imagined to be a ſhedding of blood, foraſmuch as theſe two Olive trees are uncapable of ſuch ſuffering.</p>
                  <p>But as the working of their enemy is the myſtery of iniquity, <hi>ſo are the weapons of this warfare ſuch as may carry a reſemblance of the weapons that the Lord Jeſus uſeth in his Kingdom,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.4</note> whoſe Vicar the Beaſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to be.</p>
                  <p>So that the Victory obtained by Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt over the ſacred Scriptures, is by the exerciſe of his power in <hi>ſuſpending, ſuppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, prohibiting</hi> the Tranſlation of them into the vulgar Languages, not permitting them to live or breath in the ſtreets of his great City. Indeed they are not buried, (that is beyond the power of Antichriſt)
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:35245:44"/>they are ſtill above ground, but 'tis in a dead letter, <note place="margin">They take out the Candle, and give the Lant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horn to guide ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant people in a dark night. <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.2. <hi>&amp;</hi> 28.14.</note> the life and ſtrength of them is taken away, nay the very heart of them is pulled out; for they have (to their ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting ſhame) excluded the ſecond Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment from the Decalogue.</p>
                  <p>Thus void of fear of that dreadful curſe which the Lord hath denounced againſt ſuch deſperate wickedneſs, and without the leaſt apprehenſion of the terrors of the Almighty &amp; his fierce wrath againſt that abhorred ſin of Idolatry, which did ſo often provoke the eyes of his jealouſie to puniſh his ancient people, hath this infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal beaſt not only preſumed to blaſpheme, <note place="margin">Fulk Rhem. Teſt Epiſt.</note> mangle, ſuppreſs and prohibit the eternall Word, but hath alſo moſt deſperately cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted the ſence of it, leaſt the deep ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of theſe bleſſed Witneſſes (thus cloi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtered within the walls of an unknown Language) ſhould break forth into loud clamors againſt his deteſtable wickedneſs; you have beheld him tearing out their ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry heart (as it were) in diſcarding the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Precept from their Adulterate De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calogue; and this (by their deteſtable Councel of <hi>Trent</hi>) is declared good Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique Doctrine. <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Europ. ſpec. p.</hi> 185. <hi>Taylor Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert. pag.</hi> 115.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Much like that Antichriſtian expreſſion
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:35245:45"/>of Pope <hi>Clement,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Perſwaſ. from Pop. p.</hi> 15.</note> who ſhameth not to vaunt of that deteſtable Decree of his bloody Inquiſition, <hi>That no Lay man muſt be permitted to have the Bible, or any part thereof in the vulgar Tongue;</hi> and this he preſcribeth to be inviolably kept.</p>
                  <p>But from Decrees they at length come down to downright blows, &amp;c. for after they have dealt with theſe bleſſed Witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, as their Predeceſſors did with the Lord Jeſus, <hi>Mat.</hi> 26. with moſt bitter reproaches, calling them a dead and dumb thing,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Jewel Def. Apol. p.</hi> 552. <hi>Act. Mon. p.</hi> 1133.</note> a black Goſpel, inken Divinity, dumb Judges, &amp;c. they bring them to the ſtake; and this was done by the Popes Inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors in <hi>Paris,</hi> and in <hi>England,</hi> where by Proclamation they were burned.</p>
                  <p>And yet theſe Monſters while they burn the Scriptures, are more wicked in abuſing them, to warrant their deteſtable practice, producing that bleſſed word, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.</note> 
                     <hi>Give not holy things to dogs,</hi> to juſtifie the with-hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Scriptures from the common People.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, The exact time when theſe ſacred Witneſſes were overcome and kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, was in the year of our Lord 1564. when after the Conventicle of <hi>Trent</hi> (who as Judges in the Popes Aſſizes) had blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemed,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:35245:45"/>arrained and condemned this Word of truth, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Bulla Pii</hi> 4. 1564.</note> Pope <hi>Pius</hi> the Fourth acted the part of the Executioner by his Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian Decree, abſolutely ſuppreſſing them, and denouncing Excommunicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons againſt any that ſhould dare to uſe them; and now theſe bleſſed Witneſſes having propheſied ſo many years in Sack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloth, as their Lord and ours, had been preaching dayes in the time of his fleſh, <note place="margin">The pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of <hi>Rome</hi>
                     </note> they are overcome and killed by the ſame power that killed him, and are to lie unbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried about ſo many years as our Lord lay in grave; and ſome certain ſpace of time after to aſcend into Heaven, in imitation of his Aſcenſion, as ſhall with the gracious Aſſiſtance of this Lord of life be ſhewed in its place.</p>
                  <p>By this time I hope it appears with ſome clearneſs,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Apoc.</hi> 12.6</note> 
                     <hi>That the woman was no ſooner delivered of the manchild</hi> Conſtantine, <hi>but immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (through the violence of</hi> Arrian <hi>Perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, &amp;c.) ſhe flies into the wilderneſs in the time of Pope</hi> Sylveſter. <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Anno</hi> 308.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>That at the ſame inſtant the ſacred Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes began to Propheſie in Sackcloth, and to feed the woman in her exile, as being her only ſupport, ſuccour, and ſuſtenance, the whole
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:35245:46"/>courſe of her wilderneſs condition,</hi> viz. 1260. <hi>years.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>That the holy City began even then to be trodden underfoot by the</hi> Romiſh <hi>Gentiles, (the myſtery of Iniquity being now acting in the Chayr of Peſtilence) but ſo obſcurely and ſecretly, that it was hardly diſcernable at firſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. <hi>We have alſo ſeen a glimps of the exceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive Pomp, Pride, Luxury, and Cruelty of the man of ſin all this diſmall time of black ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurity.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">5. <hi>The nature of the War raiſed and proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted, to the overcoming of the Witneſſes, as they were about to finiſh their teſtimony.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">6. <hi>How, and when they were overcome and killed by thoſe ſoul-murdering Butchers in the Slaughter-houſe of</hi> Trent, <hi>and the bellowing Bull of Pope</hi> Pius <hi>the</hi> 4. <hi>Ann.</hi> 1564. <hi>And if we add hereunto the three years and half of their lieing dead in the ſtreets of the great City, which will be terminated in the year</hi> 1568. <hi>we ſhall fit (from the time of</hi> Sylveſter, <hi>when they put on their ſackcloth,</hi> Anno 308. <hi>to this time of</hi> Pius, <hi>when they put it off,</hi> Ann. 1568) <hi>the Account exactly perfected,</hi> viz. 1260 <hi>years of the womans exile, and the Witneſſes Propheſie in Sackcloth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For it cannot be imagined (I ſuppoſe) that
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:35245:46"/>their Propheſie ſhould ceaſe (in Sackcloth) till they had ended their ſufferings at their Reſurrection.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="verse">
                  <head>The eighth Verſe. <hi>And their dead bodies ſhall lie in the ſtreets of the great City, which ſpiritually is called Sodome and Egypt, where alſo our Lord was crucified.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>That is, the City of <hi>Rome,</hi> by whoſe power our Lord alſo was crucified under <hi>Pilate</hi> the <hi>Roman</hi> Governor; through the ſtreets or Provinces of this ſpiritual <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Egypt,</hi> are the mangled, <note place="margin">A fit Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter for that Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let Strum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet, except it fall too ſhort, in regard of her more dreadfull abominations then either <hi>Sodoms</hi> filthineſs or <hi>Egypts</hi> groſs Idolatry or inhuman cruelty.</note> maſſacred bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of theſe Witneſſes hurried and tum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in a dead letter, which the people underſtand not.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="verse">
                  <pb n="84" facs="tcp:35245:47"/>
                  <head>The ninth Verſe. <hi>And they of the people and kindreds, and tongues, and nations, ſhall ſee their dead bodies three dayes and an half, and ſhall not ſuffer their dead bodies to be put in graves.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>The kindreds and tongues aſſembled in the Conventicle of <hi>Trent</hi> having overcome and killed them, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Brightman</hi> ſaith, that unleſs the Angel had named the Councel of <hi>Trent</hi> in expreſs words, he could not have ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken more plainly, <hi>pag.</hi> 119.</note> as hath been declared, they now (as aſſured they have taken their life and power away) caſt them out (thus mangled in a dead Character) to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and Nations, devoted to the Whore, and all agree to keep them out of Graves, that they may exult and rejoyce in the tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph of their victory over them.</p>
                  <p>Will you have a brief Character of this accurſed Crew in their Slaughter-houſe of <hi>Trent</hi> where the Witneſſes were ſlain? <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Conc. Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>nt. pag.</hi> 840.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Councel of <hi>Trent</hi> was a meer pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Sepulchre with a beautiful outſide of ſpecious pretences, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Bp.</hi> 5 <hi>Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, pag.</hi> 849.</note> nothing within but rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenneſs and putrefaction; or as one of their own Biſhops ſaid, the Councel ſeemed to conſiſt, not of Biſhops, but of diſguiſed Maſquers, Images rather then men, all ſtriving to maintain the Popes inordinate
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:35245:47"/>and ſhameful domination; here poyſon was carouſed in a golden Cup.</p>
                  <p>Or to uſe the words of the <hi>French</hi> Queen Mother, nothing but a fair appearance of Flowers, without any fruit at all, their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings being quite contrary to their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, two thirds of the Biſhops con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiring and ſubſcribing to hinder Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>In this filthy heap of mud and dirt whited over, are theſe bleſſed Witneſſes ſtrangled, and then (not ſuffered to remain in this painted Sepulchre, nor by the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to be finally buried) they are expoſed to the ſcorn, deriſion and reproach of their enemies, with their tongues cut out, their breath ſtopt, overcome and killed.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="verse">
                  <head>The tenth Verſe. <hi>And they that dwell upon the earth ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce over them, and make merry, and ſhall ſend gifts one to another, becauſe theſe two Prophets tormented them that dwelt on the earth.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>If you have taken notice of the dealings of the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> with <hi>Samſon,</hi> you have a picture drawn to the life of theſe Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:35245:48"/>miſcreants, in their abominable practices againſt the Scriptures, in the Councel of <hi>Trent,</hi> whereat they ſmile to this day in their triumph of their own wits, as at a Maſter-ſtratagem; let us compare them together.</p>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="parallel_quotations">
                     <body>
                        <q>
                           <bibl>
                              <hi>Judg.</hi> 16.19.</bibl>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Delilah</hi> betrays him into the hands of the <hi>Philiſtines.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>They cut off his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven locks wherein his great ſtrength lay, whereby he had done ſuch high exploits.</p>
                           <p n="21">
                              <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="21"/> They put out his eyes, and brought him down to their Great City.</p>
                           <pb n="87" facs="tcp:35245:48"/>
                           <p>They bind him with fetters of Braſs, and he did grinde in the priſon houſe.</p>
                           <p>
                              <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="24, 25"/> The <hi>Philiſtines</hi> feaſt, and rejoyce over <hi>Samſon,</hi> who had vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and tormented them.</p>
                           <p>After a certain time <hi>Samſons</hi> locks did grow again, and his ſtrength returned to him.</p>
                           <p n="30">
                              <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/> And he overthrew the houſe of <hi>Dagon.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>And there were ſlain of Nobles, &amp;c. 3000.</p>
                        </q>
                        <q>
                           <pb n="86" facs="tcp:35245:48"/>
                           <bibl>Revel. 11.</bibl>
                           <p>
                              <hi>The great whore of Rome betrays theſe holy Witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes into the hands of his Butchers, in his Slaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-houſe of</hi> Trent.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Theſe cut out their tongues, and ſuffer them not to ſpeak in thoſe known Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages wherein they had wrought wonders.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Theſe put out the eyes of the Scriptures, and ſo caſt them into the ſtreets of their great City.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <pb n="87" facs="tcp:35245:48"/>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Theſe bind the Witneſſes with their curſed Decrees of</hi> Trent, <hi>and of Pope</hi> Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us <hi>the</hi> 4. 1564. <hi>and then cloyſter them up in their Monaſteries &amp; Convents, and there wreſt them at their pleaſure.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <bibl>Apoc. 11.10.</bibl> 
                              <hi>And they ſhal rejoyce over them, and make merry, &amp;c. becauſe theſe two Prophets tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented them, &amp;c.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p n="11">
                              <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> 
                              <hi>And after three years and a half the ſpirit of life from God entred into them, and they ſtood upon their feet.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p n="13">
                              <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="13"/> 
                              <hi>And the tenth part of the City fell.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p n="13">
                              <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="13"/> 
                              <hi>And there were ſlain of Names of men</hi> 7000.</p>
                        </q>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <p>Thus run theſe grand Enemies of Truth exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly parallel in their Actons, and are therefore de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd to the like ruine.</p>
                  <pb n="88" facs="tcp:35245:49"/>
                  <p>I ſhal not further enlarge upon this verſe, ſave onely on the latter part of it a little; and were there no other ground to evince the truth of what hath been delivered, this paſſage would abundantly ſatisfie that the Witneſſes are none other then the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scriptures; for theſe two Prophets tormented them that dwelt on the earth.</p>
                  <p>And what is it that hath power to tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the conſciences of wicked men on earth, but the Word of God? this, and only this (being the engine of the ſpirit) tormenteth them that dwell on the earth; <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.12.</note> 
                     <hi>For the Word of God is quick and powerful, and ſharper then any two-edged Sword, pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing even to the dividing aſunder of ſoul and ſpirit, and of the joynts and marrow, and is a diſcerner of the thoughts and intents of the hearts:</hi> No wonder if earthly men rejoyce and make merry at the overthrow of ſuch oppoſites as theſe. At the hearing of the Word <hi>Ananias</hi> fell down dead, <hi>Foelix</hi> trembled, the Officers that came to appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend Chriſt fell backward to the ground; and by this Word ſhall wicked men be judged; and therefore no marvel that Antichriſt and his Adherents ſhould ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alt, rejoyce, be glad, and ſend gifts one to another, when theſe bleſſed Witneſſes that
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:35245:49"/>have ſo tormented them, are overcome and ſuppreſſed.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="verse">
                  <head>The eleventh Verſ. <hi>And after three dayes and a half the Spirit of life from God entred into them, and they ſtood upon their feet, and great fear fell up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them that ſaw them.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Three years and a half they continued in a dead letter ſuſpended, ſuppreſſed, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited by Antichriſt; and after this, in deſpight of all his Thunderbolts, the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of life from God entred into them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing tranſlated into many common Langua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges about this time, and amongſt the reſt into <hi>Engliſh;</hi> yea the Papiſts themſelves at <hi>Rhemes</hi> (ſeeing the multitude of people depart from them, and embrace the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures) were at laſt conſtrained to tranſlate them alſo, though in a corrupt manner and with moſt abominable Annotations upon them; yet even from hence did many a precious ſoul draw life and ſalvation, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting that into Honey which was the bane and poyſon of others; and it is won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful to me, that at this very exact time, both this and many other Tranſlations of
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:35245:50"/>the Scriptures ſhould come abroad in the open view of the world,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pref. Rhem. Teſt. Sect.</hi> 1. Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with title page. <hi>Fulk. cont. Mar. Epiſt. Dedic.</hi>
                     </note> received and countenanced by many Chriſtian Princes, to the great fear and terror of their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies who ſaw them thus raiſed from the dead.</p>
                  <p>But as yet, they aſcended not into Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; only they were raiſed and lived, and ſtood upon their feet; that ſo in every thing they might reſemble the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus (their Fountain,) who after his Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection ſtood alſo upon his feet on this Earth fourty days, before he aſcended up to Heaven; ſo theſe having ſtood a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable time upon their feet, not in that glory they were to have, but in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of it.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="verse">
                  <head>The twelfth Verſe. <hi>And they heard a great voyce from Heaven, ſaying unto them, Come up hither. And they aſcended up to heaven in a cloud, and their enemies beheld them.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>That the two Teſtaments are the Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, and that they were overcome, lay dead, and roſe again (as hath been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared) I have good ground to be confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently aſſured of; but how long they
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:35245:50"/>ſtood upon their feet before they aſcended up into Heaven, I am not ſo clear in; yet if I may deliver what my ſerious thoughts (grounded upon fair probabilities) prompt me to, I ſhall declare; namely, the great voyce, calling up the Witneſſes, is this preſent famous and renowned Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> which I believe for ſundry reaſons.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, The Scriptures never appeared in their true luſtre, ſplendor and glory (ſince their ſuppreſſion) till now, that this bleſſed voyce hath called them up to the Throne where theſe Worthies ſit.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, <hi>They aſcended up to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in a cloud</hi> of much trouble, won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull Commotions, and violent oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, <hi>Their Enemies beheld them,</hi> and would gladly have pulled them down; which they endeavored by all poſſible in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry, policy and violence; and to their perpetual ſhame be it ſpoken, they never beheld them but as Enemies; King, Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, Papiſts, and the whole rabble of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valliers, reſtleſs in their ſpirits, from the firſt aſcending of the Witneſſes into Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to this very day.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="verse">
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:35245:51"/>
                  <head>The thirteenth Verſe.</head>
                  <p>Fourthly, <hi>And the ſame hour was there a great earthquake.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Which certainly cannot be forgotten; the whole Land, yea, the three Nations trembled; nay, which of the Kingdoms of <hi>Europe,</hi> were free from Commotions? ſo great was the Earthquake this ſame hour of the Witneſſes aſcenſion.</p>
                  <p>Fifthly, <hi>And the tenth part of the City fell.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Great <hi>Brittain</hi> (the tenth part of <hi>Romes</hi> Dominions) had long before ſeparated from Antichriſt in Doctrine, but never fell from <hi>Rome</hi> totally till now; we kept cloſe to her deteſtable Diſcipline till this happy Parliament; (the joy of Saints, &amp; the honour of Chriſt:) Now the day breaks, and ſhadows fly away; down go Croſſes, Altars, Images; away pack Surpleſs, Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice-Book, Organs, and the whole bundle of Popiſh Superſtitious Ceremonies.</p>
                  <p>Sixthly, <hi>And in the Earthquake were ſlain of names of men ſeven thouſand.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Arch-biſhops, Dioceſan Biſhops, Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellors, Commiſſaries, Deans, Chapters,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:35245:51"/>Arch-deacons, Ordinaries, Prebends, Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, Choriſters, Parrators, Parſons, Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cars, Curats, Clarks, and I know not how many names deviſed by Antichriſt.</p>
                  <p>He that ſhall diligently conſider the particular perſons in this Land diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed by theſe and ſuch like Babyloniſh Titles, will finde no leſs a number then ſeven thouſand, all ſlain in this terrible Earthquake.</p>
                  <p>Seventhly, <hi>And the remnant were affrighted, and gave glory to the God of Heaven.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The late terrible Earthquake (that great Commotion) wherein the ſeven thouſand names of men were ſlain, did ſo affright the reſt of the long Robe, that they were glad to change their names, and their clothes; and inſtead of that of Parſon, Vicar, &amp;c. to call themſelves Miniſters of the Goſpel; and get into the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments favour for a Benefice; their laſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge was the craft of the <hi>Gibeonites;</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Joſhu.</hi> 9 4.</note> if this wile prevail not, they ſee they are undone, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Verſ.</hi> 6.</note> and therefore (ſay they) we are not of the Prelatical Faction; <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Verſ.</hi> 8. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 10.</note> we are the Parliaments friends, that rejoyce in the ruine of their Enemies; by theſe and the like expreſſions,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:35245:52"/>many a crafty <hi>Gibeonite</hi> got both protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and proviſion.</p>
                  <p>But after a little time they are diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to have only denyed their names,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Verſ.</hi> 16.</note> but retain the natures of thoſe ſeven thouſand, by bowing the knee to Chriſt, whilſt they lay Principles of perſecution againſt his poor members.</p>
                  <p>They were (ſaith the Text) affrighted; my fear is that their profeſſion of Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation was more out of fear then love, as their perſecuting Principles declare, and their practiſes verifie; but the time is at hand that our Princes who were beguiled by them, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Verſ.</hi> 19.</note> to confer favors upon them, ſhall cut them ſhort of their expected flouriſhing Eſtate: Yea, their own deſigns ſhall reduce them to a low and mean con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition: For why ſhould they be foſtered in the Parliaments boſome, who refuſe ſubſcription and ſubjection, and upon the riſing of every Scottiſh miſt, may again attempt their ruine and deſtruction? But through the Lords goodneſs, moving this renowned Parliament, the Decree is gone forth for the extirpation of the vileſt ſort of theſe, (as the infection, rape and poyſon of poor ſilly ſheep) in <hi>Wales</hi> and the Northen Counties, and is expected all
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:35245:52"/>over <hi>England.</hi> Upon theſe grounds (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong others) I am induced to believe that this preſent unparalleld Parliament is the great Voyce, which hath (to their ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting honour) calld up theſe bleſſed Witneſſes, (the Scriptures) to a heavenly freedom, and bleſſed flouriſhing eſtate in the Heaven of the Saints Society. And long may theſe Worthies ſit together, flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing with true Felicity, and all bleſſings of peace and piety; and let their indefati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gable labors and dear expreſſions of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>exampled love, and faithfulneſs to the poor members of Jeſus Chriſt, with their oppoſition and final ejection of thoſe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven thouſand names of men of the Train of Antichriſt, be recorded in golden Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters, among their ſucceſsful and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful Achievements, with that excellent piece of Juſtice, in cutting of the late Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, (with ſome chief Incendiaries) which ſhall eternize their names and make them famous by the acclamations of all true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearted Saints, while they have power to pray or ſpirits to prayſe, which alſo raiſed and with joy tranſported the ſpirit of their faithful profeſſed ſervant, to Pen theſe plain Verſes, upon the death of the late
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:35245:53"/>bloudy, perjured, perſecuting Tyrant King.</p>
                  <q>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>The King of Kings muſt Reign; Let every land,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>With horror and amazement trembling ſtand:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>While mighty Potentates come tumbling down</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>As ſturdy Traytors to th'Emperial Crown.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Great</hi> Charls <hi>of</hi> England <hi>marches in the Van,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>(Fluſh'd in the bloud of thouſands) here's the man,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Whoſe adamantine heart could not relent,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Though dreadful judgements to aſtoniſhment</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Came thundring down, but could not pierce his eare;</hi> 
                           <note place="margin">2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 28.22. <hi>Liſle, Lucas.</hi>
                           </note>
                        </l>
                        <l>This is that King <hi>did never ſpend a tear:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Yes, once he wept for two arch Traytors death,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Whom Martial Juſtice had depriv'd of breath.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>But for the thouſands murdered by his hands,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>For all the Widdows, Orphans, made i'th lands,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>For all out-ragious ſpoyles and cruelties,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Inhumane rapes, and dreadful villanies,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Fair Towns and Cities that his rage did burn,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>For theſe fell crimes who ever ſaw him mourn?</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>O man of miſchief, let me now deplore</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>At thy ſad Corps weltring in crimſon gore:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Not for thy bloud, but for thoſe thouſands ſlain,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Which die thy conſcience in a ſcarlet grain.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <pb n="97" facs="tcp:35245:53"/>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Not that the hand of Juſtice does thee wrong,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>But that their pitty let thee live ſo long.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Mans doom is paſt; <hi>thy wife &amp; children now</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Shake hands with thouſands in this land of wo.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>But what an anſwer will thy Conſcience make,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>At that Tribunal, where the Judge will take,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>No bribes, nor Lawyers Fees? where thou muſt ſtand</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Equal with pooreſt Peaſants in the Land:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And hear this dreadful voyce,—</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Traytor, appear,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Hold up thy bloudy hand, thy judgement hear.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Thou haſt conſpir'd againſt the ſoveraignty</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Of heavens great King, his crown and dignity.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Not ſatisfied in three fair Realms to reign,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>O're bodies and eſtates: Thou didſt ordain</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Laws to compel the conſcience, thus preſuming</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>T'uncrown</hi> Jehovah, <hi>his high power aſſuming.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Thou haſt polluted and prophan'd his day</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>By Laws commanding men to diſobey;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And thoſe dear Saints, who publiſht not theſe laws,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Thou didſt give up to the devouring jaws</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Of High-commiſsion wolves: who tear &amp; rend,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Impriſon, whip, crop, them to exile ſend.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Thou didſt agree with</hi> Romes <hi>black complices,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>To perſecute theſe Saints t' a wilderneſs,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Thou gav'ſt the reverend ſtile and honour too,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Which from a child is to the Parent due,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <pb n="98" facs="tcp:35245:54"/>
                        <l>
                           <hi>To</hi> Romes <hi>great vicar-General: nay, compli'd</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>To yield thy power to that King of pride.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>How didſt thou court, embrace, admire, adore,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>That queen of ſtrumpets,</hi> Romes <hi>proud ſcarlet whore!</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Why didſt thou wed a Romiſh brat, could ſhe</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Have gain'd thy love, if thou hadſt loved me?</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>There is a monſtrons ſin, cald Patricide;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Art Thou not guilty? <note place="margin">At York.</note> can it be denide?</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>That dreadful Curſe, which Thou didſt wiſh might fall</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>On thee, and thy Poſterity withall,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>May fill th'amazed world with awful fear,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And force them yield</hi> Johovah <hi>hath an ear.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Thou didſt in words abjure</hi> Romes <hi>traytrous crew,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Yet, who like thoſe that very inſtant knew</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Thy choyceſt ſecrets? Thou didſt freely yield</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Power to thoſe Iriſh monſters, who have kild</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>With ſuch unheard of barbrous horrid rage,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Thouſands of Loyal Subjects: that no age</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Did ever parallel; yet theſe are made</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Fit Inſtruments for thy accurſed ayd.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Ten times ten thouſand have thy furious hands</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Cut off in theſe thy three diſtreſſed lands;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Whereof ſome thouſand Saints, dear in mine eyes,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Whoſe precious bloud aloud for vengeance cryes.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <pb n="99" facs="tcp:35245:54"/>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Thus are thy monſtrous foul detected facts,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>(Beſides vaſt volumes of concealed acts;)</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Before th'Impartial Juſt</hi> Jehovah <hi>come;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>What canſt thou plead, why an eternal doom</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Paſs not upon thee?—Lord I leave the reſt,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>As ſecrets treaſur'd in thy royal breaſt.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Be wiſe ye Kings that yet alive remain,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>The day's at hand, the Lord alone muſt reign:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>You all muſt bow, or break; for he alone</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Muſt be exalted on his glorious Throne.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>The prayers of Saints ſhall make ſuch thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring work,,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Shall raiſe ſuch dreadful ſtorms 'gainſt Pope and Turk,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And all their dark Confederats, which ſhall</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Level their pride;</hi> For Babylon muſt fall.</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And you Grand Sir; with your</hi> Seraglio <hi>too,</hi> 
                           <note place="margin">The Turk.</note>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Muſt trudge to</hi> Tophet, <hi>'tis prepar'd for you.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Thus ſprings the gladſom day of Saints releaſe,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And ſo enſues an everlaſting Peace.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div n="14" type="verse">
                  <pb n="100" facs="tcp:35245:55"/>
                  <head>The fourteenth Verſe. <hi>The ſecond wo is paſt, and behold the third wo cometh quickly.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>And if I may deliver my judgement, I think the ſecond wo is paſt indeed, in the ſlaughter of thoſe ſeven thouſand names of men, with the death of the Tyrant, and many other grand Enemies in the three Nations, who had ſo long oppreſſed the Reformed Churches.</p>
                  <p>And I do alſo conceive that the third wo (yet to come) doth properly belong to, and ſhall miſerably torment the Antichriſtian Train, and all prophane wicked men and falſe Profeſſors, who will ſlight, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, and contemn the voyces of the fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth Angel.</p>
                  <p>For the ſeventh Viall, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.17.</note> which will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce this wo, is to be poured forth into the common Ayr, in which all the curſed brood do breath.</p>
                  <p>So that thoſe who will not receive &amp; em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the voyces of the ſeventh Trumpet (proclaiming the Lord Chriſts perſonal Reign now at hand) muſt ſhortly, quickly, (whether they will or no) receive the voice of the ſeventh Vial; and that wil be a dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful,
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:35245:55"/>direful voyce, ſaying, <hi>It is Done;</hi> That is, all power of the Enemy is deſtroyed, <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon</hi> is ruined, and all the Propheſies and Promiſes made to Saints are accompli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, in this glorious coming of our King, and the utter ruine of the king of pride.</p>
                  <p>And that which makes this voyce woful and dreadful to purpoſe, is, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Math.</hi> 25.10. <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.19. with <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.19</note> that it is attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with that ſoul-confounding voyce, that will reach the hearts of thoſe fools, that now ſlight the Goſpel of Grace, viz. <hi>The door is ſhut.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Mercies door is ſhut, never to be opened any more; nothing remains now, but Thunders, Lightnings, terrible Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes (ſuch as never was) fierceneſs of wrath, blackneſs of darkneſs, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Jude</hi> 13.</note> wo and alas for evermore.</p>
                  <p>Wherefore my humble adviſe, and earneſt requeſt is, that you will diligently hearken to, receive, embrace, and walk up to the enſuing voyce of the ſeventh Trumpet; Ah dear friends, <hi>The door will be ſhut!</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="102" facs="tcp:35245:56"/>
                  <p>THus have I endeavoured to hold forth the Light I have received (by thoſe ſoft, ſweet, ſoul refreſhing gales of the bleſſed Spirit) concerning this deep Myſtery of the Propheſy, Slaughter, Reſurrection and Aſcention of the two Witneſſes.</p>
                  <p>With the riſe, raign, and ruine of Antichriſt, which will be fully com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleated in the days of the Voyce of the ſeventh Angel.</p>
                  <p>Whereof I ſhall now ſpeak, as of the ſecond part of the eleventh Chapter of the <hi>Revelation.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="15" type="verse">
                  <pb n="103" facs="tcp:35245:56"/>
                  <head>The Fifteenth Verſe. <hi>And the ſeventh Angel ſounded, and there were great voyces in heaven, ſaying, The kingdoms of this world are become the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms of our Lord, and of his Chriſt, and he ſhall reign for ever and ever.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>TO give an account of my judgement concerning the Seals, Trumpets, and Vials; it appears cleer to my underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that the opening of each Seal is the Diſcovery of ſome Goſpel-light, one glorious Truth after another as the day approacheth; and no ſooner is one Goſpel-Truth made known (by the ſecret brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>things of the Spirit according to his word) but preſently the Trumpet ſounds; that is, The Miniſters of the Goſpel pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh it abroad, as the Prophet ſpeaketh, <hi>The Lord gave the word, <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pſal.</hi> 68.11.</note> great was the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of thoſe that publiſhed it.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thus did <hi>Luther</hi> (upon the diſcovery of new Light) ſound ſuch an alarum, as made the Throne of the Beaſt to ſtagger like a drunken man; I will not ſay the firſt Seal was opened to <hi>Luther,</hi> nor that he was the firſt Trumpet; but this I can ſpeak
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:35245:57"/>that a further degree of Goſpel-glory (new light, though the word be odious amongſt ſome) was diſcovered to <hi>Calvin;</hi> and after him, to others, who as they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived it, preſently became the Lords Trumpets to declare it to the world, upon whoſe refuſal of it, the Vials are ſucceſſive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly poured forth; ſo that firſt a Seal is ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; ſecondly, a Trumpet ſounds, decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the truth diſcovered within that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened Roll; thirdly, a Vial of wrath is poured forth upon thoſe that hear and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject it: but becauſe the Seals, Trumpets, &amp; Vials are not contained in this Chapter, I ſhall forbear to enlarge upon them at this time, and proſecute the work of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Chapter.</p>
                  <p>If we look back to the former Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of the Witneſſes, and conſider the ſeven thouſand names of men (there diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered to be) ſlain or ſuppreſt by this preſent Parliament, and obſerve the ſweet conſent of things attending, it will be no harſh or improbable Concluſion, that the ſeventh and laſt Trumpet is at this inſtant ſounding; yea, ſounding (at preſent) ſuch an Alarum that there are ſcarce any other voyces heard among watchful Saints, but the Lords at hand, the Bridegroom is
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:35245:57"/>coming, <hi>The Kingdoms of this world are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the Kingdoms of our Lord, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Which as it is the earneſt expectation of all waking Virgins, and the unſpeakable ſupport of many a poor dejected, diſconſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, drooping ſoul, to think (in the midſt of afflictions, temptations and fiery tryals) My Lord is a coming to put an end to all my ſorrows, to wipe all tears from mine eyes, to tread Satan under his feet, to ſet me free from ſin and ſorrow; and ſo I ſhall (by way of improvement of my ſmall Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, leaſt it be found hid in a Napkin) for the augumentation of the joy of every waiting, longing, breathing, panting ſpirit; and for the information of ſuch poor ſouls (belonging to Chriſt) who are yet in the Dark, as touching this great Myſtery, hold forth what the Lord hath entruſted in this earthen veſſel, of the unconceivable Glory of this his univerſal ſoveraignty: In which glorious diſcovery I ſhall ſhew,</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. <hi>That he will come to reign upon earth.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. <hi>How, and in what manner he will come.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. <hi>Where he will eſtabliſh his Throne at his coming.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>4. <hi>When he wil take his great power &amp; reign.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>5. <hi>The ſignes of his coming.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>6. <hi>His ends in thus coming.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>7. <hi>Events ſucceeding.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>8. <hi>The uſes we are to make of all.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p>And if theſe and each of theſe ſhall be fully cleared by the pure Word of the Lord without wreſting, or any other ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile invention of mans brain; then let all the ſons and daughters of <hi>Sion</hi> with joy embrace them as intelligence and ſweet tokens of love from their King and Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, whoſe bowels yearn, whoſe high endeared affections are upon the wing, unſatisfied with his preſent glory in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven till the fulneſs of time come that he may be inebriated and overcome with the ſoul raviſhing embraces of his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed Spouſe on Earth. But if any cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance belonging to this glorious Subject ſhall be found wanting of cleer teſtimony from the fountain of truth, Let it be deteſted, abhorred, and rejected, as the froath and vanity of a deceived and deluded creature; but to the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, That the Lord Jeſus Chriſt (who did aſcend into Heaven) ſhall come again to reign upon the Earth, is clear from di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Scriptures; <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.6.33.16. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 4.2.</note> firſt, that of <hi>Jeremiah, Behold the days come ſaith the Lord, that I will raiſe unto</hi> David <hi>a Righteous branch, and
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:35245:58"/>a King ſhall reign and proſper, and ſhall exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute Judgement and Juſtice in the Earth,—and he ſhall be called the Lord our Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi> Secondly, That in <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.10. where the glorified Saints in Heaven do exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly exult and rejoyce, not only that they are redeemed from amongſt men and poſſeſt of heavenly glory, but (as an additi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to their felicity) that they are made <hi>Kings and Prieſts unto God, that they may reign (with Chriſt) upon the Earth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For where they reign, Chriſt ſhall reign; <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Apoc.</hi> 5.10. <hi>&amp;</hi> 20.4.</note> where his Throne is erected, there they are enthroned, <hi>To him that overcometh, <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Apoc.</hi> 3.21.</note> will I grant to ſit with me in my Throne, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sing and rejoyce, O Daughter of Sion; <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Zech.</hi> 2.10.</note> for lo, I come, and I will dwell in the midſt of thee, the Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And the Lord ſhall inherit Judah, <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Verſ.</hi> 12.</note> his portion, in the holy Land.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And his feet ſhall ſtand in that day upon the mount of Olives, which is before Jeruſalem.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Zeeh.</hi> 14.4. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 9.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And the Lord ſhall be King over all the Earth; in that day ſhall there be one Lord,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Jer.</hi> 30.9.33.15. <hi>Ezech.</hi> 34.33, 34.37.22, 24. <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.14. <hi>Mich.</hi> 4.7. <hi>Zeph.</hi> 3 17. <hi>Zech.</hi> 2.20.6.13.</note> and his name one.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Many more Scriptures might be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to confirm this Goſpel-truth, that the ſame Lord Jeſus Chriſt (who did aſcend into Heaven) ſhall come again to
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:35245:59"/>reign upon the Earth, <hi>Luk.</hi> 19.12. But if theſe do not ſatisfie, neither will credit be given if an Angel ſpeak from Heaven, or one ſhould riſe from the dead to affirm it: For my own part, I do not know any point of Faith throughout the whole Book of God more clearly proved then this in hand; as certain as he aſcended, and is now receiving his Kingdom, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luk.</hi> 19.11, 12.</note> ſo ſure will he return again to reign in his Kingdom; Read <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 72. And theſe and many more Scriptures do ſuperabundantly rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie this aſſertion.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> 1. What then remains on our part, but firſt to believe this truth of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing here to reign? we can do him no greater honour then to believe his Word; nor no greater diſgrace then to reject and refuſe ſo great a cloud of Witneſſes (of himſelf, his Prophets, and Apoſtles.)</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> 2. To pray fervently as himſelf hath taught us, <note place="margin">Mat.</note> 
                     <hi>Thy kingdom come,</hi> for though it is true that neither this nor any other mercy ſhall be detained from us one minute longer then the appointed ſeaſon; <hi>Yet know O houſe of Iſrael,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Ezech.</note> (ſaith the Lord) <hi>I will for this be enquired of.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> 3. And thrice bleſſed thoſe that are counted worthy to be the Lords
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:35245:59"/>Remembrancers, to watch, wait for, and conſtantly expect the coming of this King of Glory. <hi>Bleſſed is that ſervant, <note place="margin">Mat.</note> whom his Lord when he cometh ſhall find ſo doing; <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Iſai.</hi> 30.18</note> Yea, bleſſed are all they that wait for him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly, how and in what manner ſhall this King (our Chriſt) come to reign upon the Earth?</p>
                  <p>Firſt, he ſhall come in Majeſty, Power, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.30 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.9</note> and great Glory, not in the form of a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, not riding upon a Colt the foal of an Aſs; not to be laid in a Manger, abuſed, condemned, and crucified, but now the voyce is, <hi>Gird thy Sword upon thy thigh, <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45.3, 4, 8.</note> O moſt mighty with thy glory and thy Majeſty, and in thy Majeſty ride proſperouſly; All Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſmell of Myrrh, his Aloes and Caſsia out of the Ivory Palaces. He ſhall alſo have dominion from ſea to ſea, <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pſal.</hi> 72.8.</note> and from the River to the ends of the Earth, yea all Kings ſhall fall down before him, <note place="margin">11.</note>all Nations ſhall ſerve him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly, <note place="margin">2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.7 <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.31 25, 31. <hi>Zech.</hi> 14.5. <hi>Jude</hi> 14.</note> 
                     <hi>He ſhall come attended with all the Angels in Heaven, and all his Saints that ever were, now are, or ever ſhall be; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſuch a King, never ſuch a train.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thirdly, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.27 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.52.</note> 
                     <hi>He ſhall come ſwift as the Light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, in a moment, in the twinkling of an eye, at unawares;</hi> O dear Chriſtians, watch for your lives.</p>
                  <pb n="110" facs="tcp:35245:60"/>
                  <p>Fourthly, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat.</hi> 24 30 <hi>Apoc.</hi> 1.7. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.8 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.13</note> 
                     <hi>He ſhall come in Clouds, and flaming fire;</hi> look carefully to your works, actions, and converſation; for this fire will try every mans work of what ſort it is.</p>
                  <p>Fifthly, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat.</hi> 24 30 <hi>Apoc.</hi> 1.7.</note> 
                     <hi>He will come in view of all the world, and every eye ſhall behold him;</hi> And what wilt thou do? or how wilt thou be able to look on his glorious face, that canſt not now endure the ſight of his Saints?</p>
                  <p>Sixthly and laſtly, <hi>He will come in perſon,</hi> with the ſame body that was born of the Virgin, crucified upon the Croſs, raiſed from the dead, and aſcended into Glory; only here's all the difference, it will be a Spirituall, Immortal, Glorious Body, but the ſame Body; If we believe that he was a perfect man, and had a real Subſtantial Body here on earth, and that he hath ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted the ſame Body to the right hand of the Majeſty on high, then certainly he ſhall come in perſon here to reign in the ſame Body with his Saints; for proof hereof many Scriptures might be alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged; I ſhall only produce two, and they are very full and clear; the firſt is in the firſt of the <hi>Acts, <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Acts</hi> 1.11.</note> verſ.</hi> 11. and it is the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Angels, which alſo ſaid, <hi>Ye men
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:35245:60"/>of Galilee, why ſtand ye gazing up into Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, This ſame Jeſus which is taken up from you into Heaven, ſhall ſo come in like manner as ye have ſeen him go into Heaven.</hi> I am even amazed, that men profeſſing godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſhould have a vayl ſo thick upon their hearts, and their underſtanding ſo wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully obſcured, as to reject the ſerene brightneſs of this impregnable Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond Scripture, is the firſt to the <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.16. <hi>For the Lord himſelf ſhall deſcend from Heaven with a ſhout, &amp;c.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.16.</note> there needs no further proof; if theſe two convince not, what will?</p>
                  <p>If any ſhall yet continue in darkneſs and unbelief of this ſo neceſſary glorious truth, thus meaſured by the line of the Word, and weighed in the ballance of the ſanct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uary, it is becauſe there is no light in them.</p>
                  <p>The uſe that I would have my fellowbre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren to make of the perſonal Reign of Chriſt, is this, if ever we expect to ſee his face with joy, if ever we hope to be ſharers in his Glory, at his perſonal coming, in his Kingdom; let us get a large proportion of his ſpirit in our hearts; his perſonal pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence will be no comfort to us then, unleſs
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:35245:61"/>we are filled with his ſpirituall preſence now; <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gen.</hi> 43.5.</note> 
                     <hi>Ye ſhall not ſee my face</hi> (ſaith <hi>Joſeph</hi>) <hi>except your Brother be with you.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Can we think of entertainment in his Royal Palace without the wedding gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? the Lord make us wiſe betimes.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, the next thing to be enquired into, is, where this King of Glory will e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſh his Throne at his coming; and this hath been proved already (in general) to be upon the earth, but more particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I affirm (becauſe the Word of truth affirms) it will be in the Valley of <hi>Jehoſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phat;</hi> for ſo the Prophet <hi>Joel</hi> ſpeaks in plain words;
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Joel</hi> 3.2.</note> 
                     <hi>I will alſo gather all Nations, and will bring them down into the Valley of Jehoſaphat, and will plead with them there; Thither cauſe thy mighty ones to come, O Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">11.12</note>
                     <hi>Let the Heathen be wakened, and come up to the Valley of Jehoſaphat, for there will I ſit to judge all the Heathen round about;</hi> the Heathens muſt come up to the Valley, the Saints muſt come down.</p>
                  <p>And it will be worth our labours to conſider the reſt of this third Chapter of <hi>Joel,</hi> which will give much light to this truth; for after the Lords Throne is thus erected in the Valley of <hi>Jehoſaphat,</hi> it is
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:35245:61"/>ſaid, that the Lord will dwell in <hi>Zion,</hi> and that there ſhall be abundance of rich bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings there, <note place="margin">17, 18.</note>
                     <hi>And that for ever, as long as the Moon endureth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But becauſe the Valley of <hi>Jehoſaphat,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 72. <hi>Dan</hi> 7.14.</note> as it now is, hath not capacity, or extent to receive the <hi>New Jeruſalem,</hi> therefore the Prophet <hi>Zachary</hi> tells us, that it ſhall be wonderfully enlarged by the dividing of the Mount of Olives. <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Zech.</hi> 14.4</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And the Mount of Olives ſhall cleave in the midſt thereof toward the Eaſt and toward the Weſt, and there ſhall be a very great Valley; For the valley of the Mountains ſhall reach unto Azal; <note place="margin">Verſ. 5</note>All the land ſhall be turned as a Plain from Geba to Rimmon, <note place="margin">10.</note>— and it ſhal be inhabited in her place;
<note place="margin">11.</note>And men ſhall dwell in it, and there ſhall be no more utter deſtruction; But Jeruſalem ſhall be ſafely inhabited;</hi> and how ſhould it be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, when the Prince of Peace ſhal reign (in Glory) in the midſt of it?</p>
                  <p>This then is the place of which the Lord ſpeaketh, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65 10. <hi>Rev.</hi> 24.4.</note> 
                     <hi>I will rejoyce in Jeruſalem, and joy in my people, and the voyce of weeping ſhall be no more heard in her, nor the voyce of crying:</hi> here Lord let my ſoul flouriſh with thee and thy Saints, according to thy Word, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.21.</p>
                  <pb n="114" facs="tcp:35245:62"/>
                  <p>Fourthly, the fourth thing to be diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, is, when (this Lord of Glory and King of Saints) will come to reign in this his Kingdom on Earth; and firſt, it is plain, that it was not in the dayes of his humiliation; for as he is anſwering his Diſciples queſtion about his coming to Judgement, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.25.6.</note> he tells them the time of it is then when all the Virgins (ſeeing the ſigns, and hearing the voyce or cry) Go forth to meet him, coming as a Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom, to marry his Church, that is, the whole body of his Saints (which will be then compleated and) brought together into one place, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.28. <hi>Joh</hi> 10.16</note> where, in the view of all the world, the Marriage will be glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly ſolemnized.</p>
                  <p>And ſecondly, it is as plain, that this Glorious Reign cannot be after the day of Judgement; for then there would be a change in Heaven; <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.24.</note> ſince it is clear, that after Chriſts Reign, and ſubduing of all his enemies, he muſt give up the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to his Father.</p>
                  <p>Then thirdly, it cannot be the ſpirituall Reign of Chriſt (in that way as moſt dream) which they conceive is now in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and that Chriſt will never come to Reign any other way (ſave onely in
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:35245:62"/>greater purity) then he doth now by his Spirit.</p>
                  <p>Which fond imaginations, as they have not the leaſt ſubſtantial Pillar from the word of Truth to ſupport them: ſo the contrary is plain and evident from the clear current of that pure fountain: name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that the Lord Jeſus Chriſt will come then, and not till then, to take to himſelf his great Power and Reign, when all the ſigns that are to precede his coming, are viſibly diſcovered, which I am ſure are not yet, as ſhall be ſhewed in its place.</p>
                  <p>Again, the Spirit was given in a moſt glorious eminent manner, (far exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing preſent diſpenſations) when the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles Generally (and Saint <hi>John</hi> more particularly) waited for, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Act.</hi> 3.20, 21. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.23. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.17. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1 7.</note> and yet expected this Glorious Perſonal Reign of Chriſt, as abundance of unerring Witneſſes do teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie, but in ſpecial the preſent Scripture that I am now opening, namely <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.15. which plainly declareth that the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal
<note place="margin">* See <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.7.</note> Reign of Chriſt is to begin when the ſeventh Trumpet is ſounding; at that time (and not before) when the ſeventh Trumpet begins to ſound,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rev.</hi> 10.7.</note> ſhall this great Myſtery be accompliſhed.</p>
                  <p>And certain I am, that the Spirituall
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:35245:63"/>Kingdome of Chriſt was gloriouſly emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, before any of the ſeven Angels be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to ſound; and therefore it cannot be only the ſpiritual Kingdom of Chriſt that is here ſpoken of, and ſo the time is not yet in being of this Reign of Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>As therefore we muſt not caſt off our expectation of, nor our diligent conſtant watching, waiting for this Perſonal Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious manifeſtation on the one hand, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with that evil ſervant, <hi>My Lord de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layeth his coming,</hi> and ſo ſplit our ſelves up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the deſperate rock of carnal ſecurity;</p>
                  <p>Neither muſt we run upon that other ſhelf of a vain ungrounded conceit, that he is already come, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.23, 24, 25, 26, 27.</note> whereof our Lord him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf hath given us fair warning, the Lord give us hearts to receive and embrace it. It is not then the ſpiritual Reign w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> we now enjoy, but the perſonal, glorious, truly ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Reign, which we ſhall ſhortly enjoy, that is, the Life, and Crown, and Hope, and Comfort of many precious enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Saints, who have found ſuch ſweet ſupport, ſuccour, and ſolace from this ſure Pillar of divine truth, that all the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſions of Sathan in this luxurious, giddy Age, hath not been able to ſhake.</p>
                  <p>The ignorance of this ſoul-raviſhing
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:35245:63"/>Goſpel-truth is that horrible Gulph that hath ſwallowed up thouſands, who (find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the words of truth ſuch glorious things ſpoken of this day of the Lord, but through ignorance in this Myſtery, and the cunning ſlights of Sathan, who tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forms himſelf to an Angel of Light) are deluded in their ſence, and all their intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectuals, beleeving that Chriſt is come al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, and doth Reign already, whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on they conclude to throw away all Ordinances; for, ſay they, Chriſt hath commanded us to uſe them till his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and no longer, Do this till I come; hold faſt till I come; Occupy till I come; Nay, ſo far hath this reſtleſs ſpirit of error prevailed with ſome, as to beleeve that Chriſt hath already Reigned, that he hath already given up the Kingdom to his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and that now God is all in all, that they live in God, that they are God, &amp;c. And now this Prince of darkneſs hath plaid his part to purpoſe; now he hath poſſeſſed them, not only with a diſtaſt of Ordinances, and ſlighting of them, but now away go Scriptures, Chriſt and all, they are a lye, an Allegory, he a ſhadow, a Type, &amp;c. and now Sathan hath his will, having deceived them ſo far, as to
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:35245:64"/>deny the Lord that bought them; for he well knows that there is no other name given under heaven to bring ſalvation, but this Chriſt whom they thus reject; and now he is cock ſure of them, and now they are ripe for any miſchief, drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, whoring, ſwearing, curſing, blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheming, any thing.</p>
                  <p>And that which exceeds admiration, this curſed Serpent hath ſo wonderfully led them away captive at his will, that they beleeve theſe abominations are law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and not ſinful at all; Nay, amongſt many of them the moſt bloody execrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and moſt deſperate wickedneſs is counted the higheſt attainment.</p>
                  <p>And all this ariſing (principally) from their ignorance of this wonderful Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Chriſts Perſonal Reign.</p>
                  <p>Now here the poor Saint (wondring at the free diſtinguiſhing Love of God, in leaving ſuch through ignorance, to wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low in all kind of filthineſs, and revealing this profound Myſtery ſo ſweetly and clearly to him) Cryes out, My heart is fixed, O God, my heart is fixed; nothing (through thy ſtrength) ſhall ſhake my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution; then, and not till then will I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve my Lord is come, when I ſhall ſee
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:35245:64"/>the departed Saints raiſed, the living changed, thine ancient People called, Antichriſt and his Babel deſtroyed, the whole Creation reſtored, univerſal peace eſtabliſhed, the world combined, Satan chained, the Mount of Olives divided, <hi>Jehoſaphats</hi> Vale enlarged, the holy City erected, the Marriage Royal ſolemnized, the Saints immortalized, and gloriouſly enthroned, the Nations all ſubdued; then, and not till then ſhall Goſpel Ordinances be aboliſhed, or rather contracted into thoſe Goſpel-Exerciſes that ſhall abide to all eternity, as love and praiſe, and joy unconceivable, till theſe glorious wonders be clearly manifeſted. I ſhall keep cloſe to the Mountains of Myrrh, and the Hils of Frankincenſe, where I have ſo often enjoyed the beloved of my ſoul from whoſe chaſte embraces and heavenly (continued) delights, I muſt not (through the riches of his love I ſhall not) be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed by the fond conceits of any deluded Notioniſt.</p>
                  <p>Though they tell me he's here, there, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.</note> nowhere, I ſtir not; though thouſands are deluded, I flinch not, <note place="margin">Verſ. 23.</note> though they ſay he is in the Deſart, I move not; <note place="margin">Verſ. 24.</note>in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Chambers, I believe it not; <note place="margin">Verſ. 26.</note>I know the
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:35245:65"/>coming of my Lord will be more glorious then ſo: <note place="margin">Verſ. 27.</note>which coming is now at hand, and the preciſe time, though no mortal creature doth know, yet the Saints are ſo far acquainted with his minde and will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed, that they can tell he will come.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. When ſinners are in their higheſt jollity, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.43 44.</note> and will take them in the midſt of their carnal ſecurity when they little think of it, he will come and break the houſe upon them, and deſtroy all their mirth for ever.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. He will come when wicked Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters are laying Principles of Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.45.</note> and contriving miſeries to the poor Saints.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.12, 13. <hi>Z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ch.</hi> 14.5.</note> He will come when the number of his Elect are compleated; he will bring all his Elect with him when he comes; he cannot come while one Saint is unborn, uncalled.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. He will come at midnight, when moſt of the Virgins are aſleep, and the one half of thoſe ſleepy Virgins (like falſe profeſſors) do either hide their Talents,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.5, 6.</note> or are unfruitful, unholy in their conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation; their veſſels empty, which will make themſelves moſt miſerable.</p>
                  <p>So that between the drowſineſs, and
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:35245:65"/>ſtupidity of the wiſe, and the barrenneſs and hyprocriſie of the fooliſh Virgins; <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luk.</hi> 18.8.</note> the Lord makes a great queſtion whether or no he ſhall finde Faith on the Earth at his coming.</p>
                  <p>I do therefore in the name and fear of the Lord, adviſe you my dear fellow members, who ſhall ſhare with me in that exceeding eternal weight of glory, be diligent to employ and improve your Talents.</p>
                  <p>As every man hath received the gift, <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.10.</note> even ſo miniſter the ſame one to another, as good ſtewards of the manifold grace of God.</p>
                  <p>Wherefore gird up the loynes of your minde, be ſober and hope to the end, <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.13 <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.35, 36.</note> for the grace that is to be brought unto you at the Revelation of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. He will come when many of his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants are waiting, watching for his coming, diligently employed and buſie in the work of their Lord, — Lord, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.37.</note> why ſhould not I be found ſo doing?</p>
                  <p n="6">6. And laſtly, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.32, 33, 34.</note> he will come in that ſame Generation wherein the fig-tree buddeth; that is, when all the ſigns are accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that are mentioned in his word.</p>
                  <p>Fifthly, And theſe ſigns are either re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote or immediate.</p>
                  <pb n="122" facs="tcp:35245:66"/>
                  <p>The firſt ſort, Are 1. the riſe, raign, and decay of Antichriſt.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, The Churches exile, and ſlaughter of the Witneſſes.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, Wars, Treachery, Villany, Cruelty, Perſecution, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, Idolatry, Hereſy, Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and all kind of abomination.</p>
                  <p>Fifthly, Falſe Prophets that ſhall affirm he is come already, that he hath reigned, given up the Kingdom to his Father, that he is here, there, not at all, deny his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity, &amp;c. Theſe and many others are already accompliſhed.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond ſort of ſigns that do more immediately precede his coming, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.12. Dr. <hi>Browns</hi> Enquiry, <hi>pag.</hi> 313.</note> are,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The drying of the great River <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phrates,</hi> one of whoſe ſtreams are already dryed up, and how ſoon the reſt may be, is uncertain.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The Sun darkned, ſome think this will be a wonderful Ecclips, or ſome more extraordinary obſcurity: <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.29. <hi>Joel</hi> 2.31. <hi>&amp;</hi> 3.15.</note> Which others conceive is meant of Turk and Pope, the latter pretending to be the glorious light of the world, whoſe falſe raves have by degrees been extinguiſhing theſe many years upon the bleſſed diſcovery of the pure heavenly light of the Goſpel; before
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:35245:66"/>which true light all his juglings have been detected, as once <hi>Simons</hi> were by the preaching of <hi>Philip;</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Acts</hi> 8.9.</note> and at laſt ſhall be univerſally obſcured, all the gliſtering ſtars of this defiled heaven (of <hi>Rome</hi>) fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling as untimely fruit, when at the ſame time the other grand enemy of Jeſus Chriſt (who bears for his Creſt, the <hi>Moon</hi>) that hath ſo greedily hunted and delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in blood, ſhall be overwhelmed and ſwallowed up in blood.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The third ſign immediately preceding this glorious perſonal appearance &amp; reign of our Lord, is the ſecret ſign diſplayed, whether this be <hi>Elias</hi> or the Lord Jeſus himſelf in the clouds, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.30.</note> reſtoring all things to their primitive purity and perfection before he deſcend to the Earth; <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.26.</note> or what elſe it may be, I ſhall not preſume to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine, as having no cleer Scripture-Light to direct me; and I ſhould be loth to deliver any thing but with good war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant from the Law and the Teſtimony, eſpecially in a point of ſuch waight and concernment.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. The world ſhall be purified by fire, all combuſtible matter muſt be burnt up;
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor</hi> 3.12. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.6.7.</note> 
                     <hi>Peter</hi> (in alluſion to the old world) cals this a periſhing, that is, all wood, hay, and
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:35245:67"/>ſtubble muſt periſh in this fire, while the gold, ſilver, and precious ſtones ſhall abide: If we be not (dear Chriſtians) found of this ſort, what ſhall we do? how ſhall we ſtand, <hi>when the Lord ſhall be revealed with his mighty Angels in flaming fire?</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.7.8.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>For further illuſtration and confirmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this glorious truth, I ſhall now par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly cleer by Scriptures, thoſe fifteen remarkable Changes, which as ſo many Trophees of Victory ſhall attend this Prince of prayſes, at his taking to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf this his great power and Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty.</p>
                  <div n="1" type="subsection">
                     <pb n="125" facs="tcp:35245:67"/>
                     <head>1. <hi>The Saints Deceaſed Royal Jeſus brings,</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THis will be the firſt Act of this King of glory according to the expreſs Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of the Spirit; <note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.14.</note> 
                        <hi>For if we believe that Jeſus died and roſe again, even ſo them alſo which ſleep in Jeſus will God bring with him.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And this will be a total (not a partial) Reſurrection of all departed Saints, not the Martyrs only as ſome conceive, not only thoſe that have loſt their lives for Jeſus, but the Scripture is plain and full, that whoever they be that ſleep in Jeſus, <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Apoc.</hi> 20.4.</note> God will bring with him; not only thoſe <hi>that were beheaded for the Witneſs of Jeſus,</hi> but all thoſe alſo <hi>which had not worſhipped the Beaſt, nor his Image, neither had received his mark upon their foreheads, or in their hands; and they lived and reigned with Chriſt a thouſand years.</hi> Theſe are they
<note place="margin">* <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.9, 10. <hi>Pro.</hi> 8.31. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.2.</note> that are ſo exceedingly tranſported with that more glorious condition of reigning with Chriſt upon the Earth: for as the joy and delight of Chriſt from Eternity was placed with his Saints on Earth; ſo the Saints (filled with the ſame ſpirit) place their joy and delight with this glorious King, in his high exalted ſtate on
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:35245:68"/>that Earth (and in that part of the Earth) where he was ſo ſhamefully abuſed and ſo cruelly crucified.</p>
                     <p>When therefore I ſhall ſee (with theſe eyes) my bleſſed Redeemer in the clouds attended with all his holy Angels and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted Saints, then and not till then, ſhall I ſee the end of Ordinances, and all thoſe glorious Propheſies and bleſſed promiſes fulfilled and accompliſhed, which concern this high point of my belief in the perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal reign of my Redeemer; I would not for ten thouſand worlds be deprived of this Light which leads to the glory of this bleſſed day.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="subsection">
                     <pb n="127" facs="tcp:35245:68"/>
                     <head>2. <hi>The Reſt Releaſed, mount on Angels wings.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>OUr bleſſed Jeſus (O moſt wonderful loving Jeſus) counts not his joy en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire, nor his glory compleat while any one of his beloved Lambs is abſent, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he makes it his great requeſt to his Father, and our Father, <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.24.</note> O (ſaith he) <hi>that they alſo whom thou haſt given me, be with me where I am, that they may behold my glory which thou haſt given me:</hi> 'Tis granted ſaith the Father (our moſt gracious infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely loving Father) and accordingly <hi>Paul</hi> is informed, <hi>That we which are alive,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.17.</note> and remain, ſhall be caught up together with them in the clouds, to meet the Lord in the Ayr; and ſo ſhall we be ever with the Lord.</hi>
'Tis true, the raiſing thus the dead Saints, <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.51.</note> and changing the living Saints, is ſuch a My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery as moſt wil give no credit to; for who indeed can take delight in this doctrine, but thoſe that ſhall ſhare in the glory of it? it hath no relliſh upon other mens palats, they cannot digeſt it, though never ſo cleer in Scripture; but God hath revealed it to many of his dear ones by his Spirit in his word, which plainly tels them, <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.31.</note> That <hi>he will ſend his Angels with a great ſound of a Trumpet, and they ſhall gather together his
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:35245:69"/>Elect from the four winds, <note place="margin">
                              <hi>Zech.</hi> 14.5.</note> from one end of Heaven to the other.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And can I believe my Lord is yet come to reign, while I ſee poor Saints ſcattered here and there in various ſtraights and fiery tryals? Away with thy conceits, deluded Notioniſt, and ſhallow prophane man; my Lord comes not in the Deſart, nor in the ſecret chamber, but when he comes to take the Kingdoms of the world to his own Government, thou ſhalt ſee (it may be to thy terror) that word of <hi>Zechariah</hi> fulfilled, <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Zech.</hi> 14.5.</note> 
                        <hi>The Lord my God ſhall come, and all the Saints with thee.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="subsection">
                     <pb n="129" facs="tcp:35245:69"/>
                     <head>3. <hi>To Iſrael mourning ſounds a glorious call;</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>WHen all eyes ſhall ſee him, <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.7. <hi>Zech.</hi> 12.10. <hi>Ezech.</hi> 37.21.</note> poor <hi>Iſrael</hi> muſt not be excluded; they alſo ſhall (to their unſpeakable joy and comfort) behold him whom they have pierced, <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Zech.</hi> 14.2.</note> even then when they have great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt need of him, when their new poſſeſſed City ſhall be taken, their houſes rifled, their women raviſhed, and all miſerably enſlaved; in this time of ſo great trouble, <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.1. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.26. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 4.3.43.5, 6.</note> ſuch as never was ſince there was a Nation, ſhall they behold <hi>Michael</hi> the great Prince; that bleſſed deliverer, who ſhall turn away ungodlineſs from <hi>Jacob;</hi> and now all <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſhall be ſaved, <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Jer.</hi> 30.10. <hi>Joel</hi> 3.1.</note> even every one that is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten among the living in <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> for now the ſinging of Birds is come, and that bleſſed voyce is heard in their ears, <hi>Awake,
<note place="margin">
                              <hi>Iſai.</hi> 26.19.60.1.</note> and ſing ye that dwell in the duſt: Ariſe, ſhine, for thy light is come, and the glory of the Lord is riſen upon thee:
<note place="margin">
                              <hi>Zeph.</hi> 3.17.</note> The Lord thy God in the midſt of thee is mighty; he will ſave, he will rejoyce over thee with joy, he will reſt in his love, he will joy over thee with ſinging.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Multitudes of Scriptures might be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced for the confirmation of this truth, but theſe may ſuffice (or nothing will) eſpecially conſidering that not one Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:35245:70"/>nor indeed any Author of credit that I know of doth ſeem to deny it. This then in brief is my judgement (with many deer Saints) grounded upon the word of truth, concerning this wonderful work of the Jews converſion.</p>
                     <p>Firſt, That they ſhall have an outward Call.</p>
                     <p>Secondly, That they ſhall be inwardly converted.</p>
                     <p>The former is thought to be at hand, if not already in being; ſince it is well ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved by Merchants of credit and others, that they have theſe two or three years been gathering wonderfully, from places more remote towards <hi>Paleſtina;</hi> the Lord ſeeming now to make good his word; firſt, <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5.26. <hi>Zech.</hi> 10.8.</note> in moving them to come in perſon to the Land of their Inheritance, according to theſe Promiſes,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Verſ.</hi> 6.</note> 
                        <hi>I will hiſs for them and gather them, for I have redeemed them; and I will ſtrengthen the houſe of</hi> Judah, <hi>and I will ſave the houſe of</hi> Joſeph, <hi>and I will bring them again, to place them.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>And I will make them one Nation in the Land upon the Mountains of</hi> Iſrael,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ez<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ch.</hi> 27.22.</note> 
                        <hi>and one King ſhall be King to them all;</hi> for,</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>When the Lord ſhall build up Zion, <note place="margin">
                              <hi>Verſ.</hi> 24. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 102.16.</note> he ſhall appear in his Glory.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="131" facs="tcp:35245:70"/>
                     <p>Therefore thus ſaith the Lord, <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ezeck.</hi> 39.25, 26.</note> 
                        <hi>now will I bring again the captivity of</hi> Jacob, <hi>and have mercy upon the whole houſe of Iſrael.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>And the ranſomed of the Lord ſhall return, <note place="margin">
                              <hi>Iſa.</hi> 35.10.</note> and come to Zion with Songs, and everlaſting joy ſhall be upon their heads, they ſhall obtain joy and gladneſs, and ſorrow and ſighing ſhall flee away.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And thus will he perform the ſecond more glorious work upon their ſouls, for a through converſion. And now I do hearti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſire for the confirmation of Saints, and for the confutation of ſuch as deny the glorious perſonal Reign of Chriſt, that they will ſeriouſly conſider, and weigh thoſe cleer proofs of Scripture that do ſo fully eſtabliſh this truth, <hi>viz.</hi> That when the Jews ſhall be thus wonderfully con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Jer.</hi> 33.14, 15, 16. <hi>Joel</hi> 3.1, 2.</note> even then and not before ſhall this King of glory take to himſelf his great power and Reign; what can be more plain and clear then this, <hi>In thoſe days, and at that time,</hi> (ſee thoſe other Scriptures,) now will this glorious Myſtery be fulfilled which hath been ſo largely held forth by all the Prophets; <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rev.</hi> 10.6, 7.</note> the ſeventh Angel is now ſounding, who ſwears that time ſhall no longer be delayed; but the
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:35245:71"/>Lord Jeſus that high and mighty one ſhall gird his ſword upon his thigh, and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully bring in this his ancient people, to whom ſhall all Saints be joyned with tranſcendent glory.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Wilt thou admit ſuch a one as I into this glory Lord!</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="subsection">
                     <pb n="133" facs="tcp:35245:71"/>
                     <head>4. <hi>To Babel burning an eternal fall.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>SIons</hi> reſtauration, muſt be <hi>Babels</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion; the ſame bleſſed day that brings forth <hi>Jeruſalems</hi> ſafety and felicity, will alſo produce <hi>Romes</hi> ruine and everlaſting miſery; I do not undertake which of theſe ſhall precede, whether the Jews Call, or <hi>Romes</hi> Fall; I believe they will neither of them be long a doing; it may be as ſudden as our change ſhall be; <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Zeph.</hi> 1.18. <hi>Joel.</hi> 3.4.</note> he will certainly make a ſpeedy riddance; ſwiftly and ſpeedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly will he return <hi>Romes</hi> recompence upon the accurſed heads of all her children.</p>
                     <p>But that which the word of truth is full and clear in, is, that <hi>Rome,</hi> Antichriſt, and all their adherents, <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.8.16.17. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 17.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.18.2. <hi>&amp;c. Jer.</hi> 51.8. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                        </note> ſhall certainly be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed; and that I may proſecute my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, or rather the deſign of the Spirit of God: it is plain that Antichriſt, and <hi>Rome,</hi> ſhall be deſtroyed even then, and not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, the Lord Jeſus ſhall come in Perſon;
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.8.</note> he is now conſuming him with the Spirit of his mouth, but he ſhall give up the ghoſt at the brightneſs of his coming.</p>
                     <p>But ſince this is the day of Antichriſt's conſumption in which we live, it behoves all true hearted Saints diligently to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der what the will and minde of the Lord
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:35245:72"/>is concerning us, how he would have us be acted in order to the accompliſhment of this great deſign.</p>
                     <p>Firſt, we muſt joyn in prayer with our fellow brethren under the Altar, <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rev.</hi> 6.9, 10.</note> and give the holy One of <hi>Iſrael</hi> no reſt, till <hi>Babylon</hi> be conſumed, and <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> be made a praiſe in the Earth.</p>
                     <p>And ſecondly, we muſt ſet hand and heart, purſe and perſon to the work, even the great work, the ſtrange Act that he is doing for, and by his Saints; yea, let every one that is the redeemed of the Lord, ſay, I will have a hand in her deſtruction; <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Jer.</hi> 51.1.2. <hi>&amp;c. Pſal.</hi> 137. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.9.</note> yea, bleſſed, yea, happy ſhall he be that hath his hands deepeſt dyed in the blood of her children.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="subsection">
                     <pb n="135" facs="tcp:35245:72"/>
                     <head>5. <hi>The world combined, hath a fatal blow.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THis is the fifth remarkable change, that will help to celebrate the tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphs of the glorious day; for as the (long enthralled) Jews and <hi>Iſraelites</hi> are entred into their ancient Land, and have newly got Poſſeſſion of (the preſent) <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> their potent Enemies, Turk, Pope, &amp;c, (who have long detained them in a miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ſlavery) ſhal raiſe huge Armies to purſue them, <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Dan.</hi> 11.45.</note> and ſhal <hi>plant their Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles in the glorious holy mountain;</hi> (ſee this fully <hi>Ezek.</hi> 38.4, 5, 6, 9.15, 16. and Chap. 39.6.)</p>
                     <p>And ſhall begirt their new-obtained City, <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ch.</hi> 14.2.</note> which they ſhall ſpeedily ſtorm and take, and reduce theſe moſt miſerable diſtreſſed people into ſuch dreadful cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.1. <hi>Z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ch.</hi> 12.10 11.</note> as the like was never heard of ſince there was a Nation, even to that ſame time; but in the midſt of theſe ſad ſtraights, fearful horror and diſmal darkneſs, when nothing but black deſpair (or a ſecond more miſerable ſlavery then ever) is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them; the great Prince of the Kings of the Earth ſhall appear in ſome wonderful manner to them, <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.1.</note> and ſhal go
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:35245:73"/>forth and fight againſt thoſe Nations, and put ſuch terror into their hearts, and ſuch courage into the hearts of his unarmed people, <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Iſa.</hi> 14.2.</note> that <hi>they ſhall take them captives, whoſe Captives they were, and they ſhall rule over their oppreſſors.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="subsection">
                     <pb n="137" facs="tcp:35245:73"/>
                     <head>6. <hi>Satan confined to his den below.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>HIs preſent condition is a Princely Rule in the ayr, and in the hearts of the children of diſobedience; but in theſe Halcyon days will that bleſſed voyce be heard amongſt the Saints, <hi>Now is come ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation and ſtrength, <note place="margin">
                              <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.10 20.1.</note> and the Kingdom of our God, and the power of his Chriſt; for the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſer of our brethren is caſt down.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>For the Angel ſhall binde and ſhut him up in the bottomleſs Pit,</hi> to which he ſhall be confined for a thouſand years, during which reſtraint he ſhall not be able, no, not to tempt his own vaſſals, but they ſhall willingly ſerve the Saints for the preſervation of their lives, till the thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand years be fulfilled, <note place="margin">Verſ. 3.</note>
                        <hi>And after that he muſt he looſed a little ſeaſon:</hi> Of which I ſhall ſpeak in its place.</p>
                     <p>Some have fancyed that Satan hath been already bound, and the thouſand years are already expired, but without any ſhadow of truth: ſince there hath not been the leaſt intermiſſion of Satans rage and fury, ſince the Book of the <hi>Revelation</hi> was written.</p>
                     <p>For what with the groſs Idolatry of Pagans, obſtinate blindneſs of the Jews,
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:35245:74"/>wonderful defection of Turks, ſtrange Errors, Sects and Hereſies of Chriſtians, abominable Superſtition, Idolatry, Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and all kinde of wickedneſs, with bloudy perſecution of Saints by Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt; <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Alſtedius</hi> Dr. <hi>Hake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will, Apol.</hi> pag. 476.</note> which things cannot poſſibly ſtand with the confinement of Satan; and conſequently this Propheſie is yet unful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled: and the time of the binding up of this Bandog will be the glorious trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant ſtate of Saints, when they ſhall be marryed to Chriſt the univerſal Monarch of this great Univerſe.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="subsection">
                     <pb n="139" facs="tcp:35245:74"/>
                     <head>7. <hi>The whole Creation finds a full Releaſe.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>FOr now this ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> ſhall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat his work, <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.19.</note> and reduce the whole frame of Nature to its primitive purity and perfection, which by the ſin of the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> hath been ſo long ſubjected to vanity and corruption; this is that great Deliverer; and this time of his perſonal Reign wil be the bleſſed ſtate (as of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption of our bodies from ſin, <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Acts</hi> 3.21.</note> ſorrow &amp; corruption, ſo) of the reſtitution of all things (the Elements and all that are produced by them) to that goodneſs wherein they were firſt created: how often have we like Parrots, prated over in our Popiſh Liturgy, this heavenly Doctrine which to this day we underſtand not? <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pſal.</hi> 67 4.</note> 
                        <hi>O let the Nations be glad and ſing for joy, for thou ſhalt judge the people righteouſly, and govern the Nations up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Earth. Selah.</hi> Mark that; but now Saints have experience of this bleſſed My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Jer.</hi> 35.5.</note> that at the ſame time when this <hi>King ſhall reign and proſper, and execute judgement and juſtice in the earth, <note place="margin">
                              <hi>Ezech.</hi> 34.23.24.</note> then ſhall the earth bring forth her encreaſe;</hi> when <hi>David</hi> the great Prince ſhall reign here in higheſt glory, then and not till then ſhall the whole Creation (brought into this
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:35245:75"/>glorious Liberty of the Sons of God) fill the Univerſe with abundance of all rich bleſſings.</p>
                     <p>I have little to ſay to thoſe, who know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nothing of this wonderful Myſtery of the glorious Reign of our King, and know as little of the meaning of <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.19, &amp;c. Yet becauſe they muſt ſay ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, are pleaſed in their grave wiſdoms to affirm, that this glorious liberty (with the children of God) which the whole Creation ſhall enjoy, is nothing but the annihilation of the creature, as if all Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures (which in their kinde do (wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully) endeavor the preſervation of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves) ſhould yet groan and earneſtly long to be made nothing: what is this, but to ſpeak daggers, and introduce a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Atheiſm?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="subsection">
                     <pb n="141" facs="tcp:35245:75"/>
                     <head>8. <hi>And every Nation flouriſhes with Peace.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>HOw can it be otherwiſe when the Kingdoms of the world are ruled and governed by the Prince of Peace? what the glorious Peace of the Saints ſhall be, hath been in part (and ſhall be more fully) declared. But there will be univerſal peace over all the earth; for all the wicked of the world ſhall as earneſtly ſeek peace as ever the <hi>Gibeonites</hi> ſought it of the <hi>Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites;</hi> when the great ſeducer of mankind is ſhut up in priſon, his Vaſſals will neither have skil nor courage to ſtand in oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt the Saints; for he that hath the diſpoſing of all hearts, will ſo mould their ſpirits, that they ſhall be glad to crouch for ſafety at the Saints feet; and bleſſed be the Name of our exalted King, he hath already given his people in this Land a taſte hereof, when in many places the proudeſt enemie thinks himſelf in a ſafe condition that can obtain the favor of a child of God to ſerve himſelf and his forfeited eſtate.</p>
                     <p>But in this glorious Reign of Chriſt it will be univerſally ſo; <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pſal.</hi> 72.8.</note> for <hi>when his Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion ſhall reach from ſea to ſea, even to the ends of the earth; then they that dwell in
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:35245:76"/>the Wilderneſs ſhall bow before him, and his enemies ſhall lick the duſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The Kings of</hi> Tarſhiſh <hi>and of the Iles ſhall bring Preſents;
<note place="margin">10.</note>the Kings of</hi> Sheba <hi>and</hi> Seba <hi>ſhall offer gifts,
<note place="margin">11.</note>yea all Kings ſhall fall down before him, all Nations ſhall ſerve him.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>This is that bleſſed time, when the Righteous ſhall flouriſh, and abundance of Peace ſo long as the Moon endureth; <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Mic.</hi> 4.3. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 11.6, 7, 8, 9.</note> then, and not till then <hi>ſhall they beat their Swords into Plowſhares, and their Spears into Pruning-hooks, no more contention, no more war for ever.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="subsection">
                     <pb n="143" facs="tcp:35245:76"/>
                     <head>9. <hi>The Mount aſunder cleaves t' enlarge the Plain.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>IF all the Propheſies that are fulfilled already concerning Chriſt were per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed in the very Letter; <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pſal.</hi> 8.2. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 22.18. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 7.14. <hi>Zech.</hi> 9.9.</note> I deſire any man to ſhow a ſubſtantial Reaſon why thoſe that are yet unacccompliſht ſhould belookt upon in a myſterious obſcure way; till ſuch a reaſon be given, I muſt look upon this (as upon all other Propheſies) to be fulfilled in the ſame way as others have been, and therefore muſt expect (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Word) that this day of Wonders will produce this Wonder a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the reſt, that the Mount of <hi>Olives</hi> that ſtands over the Valley of <hi>Jehoſaphat</hi> ſhall cleave indeed, <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Zech</hi> 14.4</note> to enlarge that Vale to a ſufficient capacity for the reception of the New <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> it is clear, <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ver.</hi> 10.</note> that it ſhall reach from <hi>Geba</hi> to <hi>Rimmon;</hi> but of what extent that will be, is (I think) un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known; only this: it ſeems to extend over the whole Land of <hi>Paleſtina;</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pſal.</hi> 60.6.</note> what elſe means the Royal <hi>Pſalmiſt, I will divide</hi> Shechem, <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Verſ.</hi> 8.</note> 
                        <hi>and mete out the Valley of</hi> Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coth; <hi>Moab is my waſhpot, <note place="margin">
                              <hi>Pſal.</hi> 87.3, 4. and 108 7, 8, 9.</note> over</hi> Edom <hi>will I caſt out my ſhooe,</hi> Philiſtia <hi>triumph thou be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of me;</hi> and that of the Prophet,</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>In that day will I raiſe up the tabernacle of</hi>
                        <pb n="144" facs="tcp:35245:77"/>David <hi>that is faln, <note place="margin">
                              <hi>Amos</hi> 9.11, 12.</note>—that they may poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs the remnant of</hi> Edom, <hi>and of all the Heathen,—they ſhall poſſeſs the Mount of</hi> Eſau, <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Obad.</hi> 19.20, 21.</note> 
                        <hi>and they of the Plain</hi> Philiſtia, <hi>&amp;c. And Saviours ſhall come upon Mount</hi> Sion <hi>to judge the Mount of</hi> Eſau,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Iſai.</hi> 10.29. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>and the Kingdom ſhall be the Lords.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>All which compared, makes good the word of <hi>Zechariah,</hi> That the dividing of this Mount of <hi>Olives</hi> ſhall produce a very great Valley; <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Zech.</hi> 14.4.</note> till which Valley appear in its luſtre and beauty, not any of the noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Giddy brains ſhall ſtagger my faith, to conceit, That my Lord is alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy come to Reign.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <pb n="145" facs="tcp:35245:77"/>
                     <head>(That Vale of Wonder where the Lord muſt Reign)</head>
                     <p>AS once the eyes of <hi>Eliſha's</hi> ſervant were opened to ſee the Mountains full of Horſes and Chariots of fire; <note place="margin">2 <hi>Kings</hi> 6.17.</note> ſo certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly were the eyes of this Prophet in a wonderful manner enlightened to ſee the glory of the Lords Day, <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Joel.</hi> 3.14.</note> the Day of his great Power in this mighty Valley of <hi>Jehoſaphat;</hi> at which glorious apparition he raiſeth up his voyce (as one tranſport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) with this heavenly rapture.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Multitudes, multitudes in the Valley of Deciſion, for the Day of the Lord is neer in the Valley of Deciſion:</hi> but what will the tranſcendent joy of this Prophet be (with all the bleſſed Prophets and Saints of Chriſt) when this Day of the Lord is come in the Valley of Diciſion, when we ſhal ſee all the heavenly Hoſt gathered to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in this ſpacious Mount-dividing Valley, <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45. <hi>Matth</hi> 25.31. <hi>Jude</hi> 14. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.14. <hi>Joel</hi> 3 2.</note> the Lord of Glory riding in his Glory and Majeſty, attended with all the holy Angels in heaven, and all thoſe My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riades of Saints that ſleep in Jeſus this mighty Potentate!</p>
                     <p>How unconceiveably glorious, how wonderfully ſpacious will this Valley of <hi>Jehoſaphat</hi> then be which muſt contain
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:35245:78"/> 
                        <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="145" facs="tcp:35245:78"/> 
                        <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="146" facs="tcp:35245:79"/>all the Saints and Angels in heaven, with all both good and bad that are found living upon the earth: this is no private fancy, but the expreſs words of the Spirit of God.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>I will alſo gather all Nations, and will bring them down into the Valley of</hi> Jehoſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phat, <note place="margin">Verſe. 11.</note>
                        <hi>and will plead with them there—Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble your ſelves, and come all ye Heathen, and gather your ſelves together round about; thither cauſe thy mighty Ones to come down, O Lord; Let the Heathen be wakened and come up to the Valley of</hi> Jehoſaphat, <note place="margin">12.</note>
                        <hi>for there will I ſit to Judge all the Heathen round about.</hi> None ſo blind as thoſe that will not ſee.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="subsection">
                     <pb n="147" facs="tcp:35245:79"/>
                     <head>10. <hi>The glorious City from Gods Throne doth glide.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>EXcept by clear Scripture it be diſpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, I muſt believe, &amp; therefore affirm,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.2. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 14.1, 2</note> that the City deſcribed by Saint <hi>John</hi> is a material City, that the Carpenters Son hath been theſe 1600 years preparing it for his Saints, and that the cleaving of the Mount of Olives producing that won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful ſpacious plain (already proved) is to receive this glorious City of twelve thouſand furlongs,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.16.</note> or one thouſand five hundred miles compaſs, wherein his Saints ſhall raign in glory with this Jehovah our Righteouſneſs as long as the Sun and Moon indureth.</p>
                     <p>If it be ſaid (by a miſtake of <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.9, 10.) That the holy City is call'd the Bride; I muſt anſwer plainly it is not ſo: but on the contrary, if the 9. and 10. Verſes be compared with the 24. we ſhall find them manifeſtly diſtinguiſhed: and it appears plainly that the deſign of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit is, to ſhew the Apoſtle the City where the Bride dwelleth;
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45.14. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65 18. <hi>Ezech.</hi> 14.11.</note> and if we ſhall further conſult theſe Scriptures, it will be yet more clear, that the City is one thing, and the Bride, the Saints, the glorious Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants in that City another thing.</p>
                     <pb n="148" facs="tcp:35245:80"/>
                     <p>But if it ſhould be granted, that the City is call'd the Bride, there would be little gained by it as to the oppoſite of this Point, becauſe it is ordinary in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to term the Inhabitants of the City the City it ſelf, as <hi>Matt.</hi> 11.20, 21, 22, 23. ſure it will not be affirmed, that the build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of <hi>Capernaum, &amp;c.</hi> are threatned to be thrown into Hell: Let the Prophet <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiel</hi> decide this Controverſie from the mouth of the Lord,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ezech.</hi> 37.27.</note> ſaying, <hi>My Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle alſo ſhall be with them; yea, and I will be their God, and they ſhall be my people; this is that royal Palace into which the Bride, with her Virgins, ſhall enter to ſolace themſelves with our King in unconceivable ſpiritual de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights for ever.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="11" type="subsection">
                     <pb n="149" facs="tcp:35245:80"/>
                     <head>11. <hi>The Nuptial ditty <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſhers in the Bride.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THe Ancient people of the Lord, the natural ſeed of faithful <hi>Abraham,</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their tedious time of divorcement, <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Iſai.</hi> 62 2, 3, 4, 5. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2.19, 20.</note> ſhall not only be eſpouſed as formerly, but now in view of all the world marryed with tranſcendent joy in higheſt Glory to the King of glory. This is the Royal Bride; the Gentiles Saints or Churches are the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins her Companions. All the Angels in Heaven joyn in Conſort to celebrate the Nuptials in that triumphant ditty, <hi>Alleluja, <note place="margin">
                              <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.6, 7.</note> for the Lord God omnipotent reighneth; Let us be glad and rejoyce, and give honour to him; for the marriage of the Lamb is come, and his wife hath made her ſelf ready; ſo ſhall ſhe be brought unto the King in raiment of needle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>work;
<note place="margin">
                              <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45.14, 15.</note> the Virgins her companions that follow her, ſhall be brought unto thee; with gladneſs and rejoycing ſhall they be brought, they ſhall enter into the Kings Palace.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>There is a great queſtion, (but of no great importance) whether the fulneſs of the Gentiles ſhall come in before <hi>Iſraels</hi> converſion; for my own part, I am ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in this, that in reſpect of a full conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, the work among the Gentiles ſhall precede; but after the Jews effectual Call,
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:35245:81"/>ſo glorious will that diſpenſation be, <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Iſai.</hi> 60 3.</note> That <hi>the Gentiles ſhall come to their light, and Kings to the brightneſs of their riſing.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Yet when all is known and underſtood which the word diſcovers of this wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Myſtery, what a ſmall ſpark is it to the exceeding unconceivable glory of that day of wonders! and who would hazard his intereſt in the glory thereof; for all the bewitching, painted, ſeeming glories of this luxurious Age!</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="12" type="subsection">
                     <pb n="151" facs="tcp:35245:81"/>
                     <head>12. <hi>Thus Saints regaining an immortal ſtate,</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>HOw miſerably are they handled, (by men of corrupt minds) that ſtand for the honour of Chriſts Kingdom, as though it were carnal delights and earthly plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures they lookt after; if any ſuch there be, they will ſee their vanity and folly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps when 'tis too late.</p>
                     <p>The Saints are of another ſtamp, and are hereby chiefly diſcerned from hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites by ſeeking holineſs, rather then hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs; it is the pure, ſpiritual, immortal, glorious ſtate of Chriſts Kingdom that they believe, and profeſs and expect; and that which makes their ſpirits dance, and their ſouls to leap for joy, is the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of being faſhioned like his glorious body, when being free from corruption, <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.21.</note> they ſhall never ſin againſt God any more; not any kinde of pleaſure can ſtand in competition (in their pure affections) with deſire of freedom from ſin; their King hath taught them, and they have learned to know, <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Luk.</hi> 20.35.</note> That <hi>they which ſhall be accounted worthy to obtain that world and the reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from the dead, neither marry nor are gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in marriage, neither can they die any more; for they are equal unto the Angels.</hi>
                        <pb n="152" facs="tcp:35245:82"/>This is that bleſſed ſtate of immortality that Saints believe,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.11. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.54.</note> and with the bleſſed Apoſtle preſs hard after; <hi>When this cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption ſhall put on incorruption, and this mortal ſhall put on immortality, and death ſhall be ſwallowed up of victory.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.23.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>This adoption is that redemption of our bodies that now we wait for, <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Luk.</hi> 22.30 <hi>Iſai.</hi> 62.9.</note> and ſhall then enjoy, when we <hi>ſhall eat and drink at Chriſts table in this glorious Kingdom:</hi> There will be eating and drinking, but not as now; for in this ſtate of mortality, other crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures loſe their lives to ſupport ours, for ſo is the word <note place="margin">* <hi>Acts</hi> 10.13. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 65.21.</note>: in the ſtate of immortality the fruit of the Vine, the food appointed <hi>Adam</hi> in Paradiſe.</p>
                     <p>And only the ſtate of Eternity, is ſuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by God himſelf.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="13" type="subsection">
                     <pb n="153" facs="tcp:35245:82"/>
                     <head>13. <hi>In glory reigning while the Sun bears date.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THe Lord Jeſus Chriſt is not now in his own proper and peculiar Throne; <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.21.</note> his preſent ſtation is at the right hand of the Majeſty on High, even in his Fathers Throne; but the glorious Throne that he hath purchaſed with his precious bloud, he will ſhortly erect upon this Earth for himſelf and his beloved Saints; then ſhall he have and enjoy the actual return of that requeſt of his,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.24.</note> 
                        <hi>That where I am they may be alſo;</hi> and this the Saints in Heaven are wondrouſly affected with, and do therefore exceedingly rejoyce in the conſideration of this glory which they (with their fellow brethren) ſhall enjoy (as an addition to their preſent glory) with Chriſt in his Throne upon the Earth: <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.9, 10.</note> for then, and not till then, will the glory of our King be compleat, when the great voyces of all the heavenly Hoſt ſhall be heard, (in the words of the Scripture I am now opening) <hi>the Kingdoms of this world are become the Kingdoms of our Lord and of his Chriſt, and he ſhall Reign for ever and ever.</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.15</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>And this Kingdom thus eſtabliſht by, and for <hi>Jehovah</hi> our Righteouſneſs, <hi>ſhall be alſo given to the people of the Saints of the
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:35245:83"/>moſt High, <note place="margin">
                              <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.27.</note> whoſe Kingdom is an everlaſting Kingdom, and all Dominions ſhall ſerve and obey him.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And thus the Saints being gathered in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to one fold (even into that holy City the new <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> ſeated in the Valley of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoſaphat</hi>) and there marryed to Chriſt our everlaſting Husband, do alſo (like the marryed condition here) obtain the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious name of our Royal Husband; for even then, <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Jor.</hi> 33.16.</note> 
                        <hi>She ſhall be called the Lord our Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="14" type="subsection">
                     <pb n="155" facs="tcp:35245:83"/>
                     <head>14. <hi>The Nations bending, Virgins voyces raiſe.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THis poſture they ſhall moſt gladly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Zech.</hi> 14 3. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 12. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 16.</note> who are eſcaped the ſlaughter of the great day, and the plagues thereof: For <hi>every one that is left of all the Nations which came againſt</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>ſhall even go up from yeer to yeer to worſhip the King the Lord of Hoſts and to keep the Feaſt of Tabernacles.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>What manner of worſhip the Lord will have from theſe Nations, I know not; <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pſ.</hi> 72.11.</note> but this I know, that <hi>all Kings ſhall fall down before him, all Nations ſhall ſerve him;</hi> ſome kinde of homage and worſhip they muſt perform without the holy City; for there <hi>ſhall in no wiſe enter into it any thing that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fileth, <note place="margin">
                              <hi>Rev.</hi> 
                              <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap>.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>7 <hi>Math.</hi> 25.4</note> — But they which are written in the Lambs Book of Life;</hi> Theſe are thoſe bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Virgins who have their Lamps of a holy converſation gloriouſly burning, and a ready ſupply of grace in their ſouls, <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.2. <hi>Math.</hi> 25. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 6. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 10.</note> whereof their pure veſſels are full; though theſe ſometimes ſlumber and ſleep, yet their hearts are awake; &amp; every noyſe they hear, they expect to be the midnight cry for the Kings coming, and are inſtantly up and ready, and ſo in they go (with this glorious Bridegroom) into the marriage-Chamber, where they meet with ſuch a
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:35245:84"/>Feaſt, ſuch ſoul-raviſhing delights, that are not poſſible to be conceived, much leſs poſſible to be uttered.</p>
                     <p>And now their hearts and voyces being tuned to one celeſtial Key, <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.3.</note> they begin that new Song which will never wax old, but with renewed ſweetneſs in all hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly delights, joy ſhall ariſe from praiſe, and praiſe from joy to all Eternity. <note place="margin">Rouſ. Pſal.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>And no man could learn that Song, but they that were redeemed from the earth.</hi> Mark that; <hi>Redeemed from the earth; theſe are they which were not defiled with women, for they are Virgins.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="15" type="subsection">
                     <pb n="157" facs="tcp:35245:84"/>
                     <head>15. <hi>(All Duties ending) with Joy, Love, and Praiſe.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THe ſame bleſſed hand that firſt inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted Goſpel Ordinances, <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Iſai.</hi> 60.1.</note> will now himſelf put an end to them;
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Cant.</hi> 4.6.</note> for now the Sun of Righteouſneſs is riſen, and diſpels all clouds, diſſipates all miſts; now breaks the gladſome Day, and ſhadows fly away; Preſumptiouſly Arrogant is that hand that ſhall dare to anticipate this work, in caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing off thoſe Ordinances, which is the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and peculiar work of him that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed them, <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Luke</hi> 19.13. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.26. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.25.</note> and commanded the uſe of them till his coming; then, and not till then, all theſe ſhall ſee their period, except thoſe that ſhall abide to all Eternity; for ſome Goſpel Ordinances muſt never ceaſe, but ſhall then be eſtabliſht in their perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; when all other Ordinances ſhall ceaſe, Joy cannot ceaſe, <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pſ.</hi> 16.11.</note> 
                        <hi>In thy Preſence is fulneſs of joy, at thy right hand there are pleaſures for evermore:</hi> Chriſt hath promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed that when he ſees his Saints again, their hearts ſhal rejoyce; then Joy ſhal be compleat, <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Joh.</hi> 16 22</note> and this Joy ſhall no man take away from the Saints.</p>
                     <p>So for that Goſpel-Ordinance of Love, that ſhall be permanent; Charity never faileth; all other Ordinances ſhall ceaſe,
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:35245:85"/>but Love ſhall then ſhine in its true luſtre, <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.8.10. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 61.3.62.7.9.</note> and full perfection; and then for Praiſe, it ſhall then be the garment of the Saints; Jeruſalem <hi>ſhall be made a praiſe in the earth; the Saints ſhall eat and praiſe the Lord, and drink in the Courts of his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs.</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Jer.</hi> 33.11.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The voyce of Joy, and the voyce of Gladneſs, the voyce of the Bridegroom, and the voyce of the Bride, the voyce of them that ſhall ſay, Praiſe the Lord of Hoſts, for the Lord is good, for his mercy indureth for ever, and of them that ſhall bring the Sacrifice of Praiſe into the Houſe of the Lord.</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.3.2. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 52.8.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>Ah, what a little glympſe of that excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent glory are theſe narrow-mouth bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles now capable to apprehend! but then we ſhall ſee him as he is, and that is the fulneſs of glory.</p>
                     <p>And thus I ſuppoſe theſe 15. wounderful Changes are clearly proved by the Word of God, as Concomitants, or cloſe Atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants to the glorious appearance of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt: as alſo (for the ſilencing of idle Notioniſts) that the Lord cannot take to himſelf his great Power and Raign till all theſe Changes appear; then, and not before will the voyces be heard, and the words of the Text be accompliſhed, <hi>The
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:35245:85"/>Kingdoms of this world are become the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms of our Lord, and of his Chriſt, and he ſhall reign for ever and ever.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The ſixth thing propoſed, is, the ends of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt coming to reign upon the Earth; amongſt many glorious ends that we may believe, I ſhall briefly mention a few.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. The end that the Lord Jeſus propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth to himſelf, is, to be gloriouſly exalted in his Royal Throne of higheſt Majeſty, even in that place where he was ſo ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and ignominiouſly abaſed, abuſed, and cruelly crucified; He ſuffered over, (or neer) the Valley of <hi>Jehoſaphat,</hi> and there (as hath been proved) he will exalt his Throne,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Zech.</hi> 12.10.</note> and there they that pierced him ſhall behold him, and be in bitterneſs of ſoul becauſe of him.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ioel.</hi> 3. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 17.24. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 10.16. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.10.11.</note> Another end is to gather all his Saints together into that place (which ſhall be the great Sheepfold) that there they may behold his tranſcendent Glory; and that there he may ſee his ſeed, and the travel of his ſoul, and be ſatisfied.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. A third end is to take an account of his ſervants, how they have imployed, and improved his talents; for this is that
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:35245:86"/>day of judgement, <note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.8. <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.4.</note> wherein the Lord Chriſt will reward his ſervants, and enſlave his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, the extent whereof will be a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand years, the longeſt day that ever any man lived one Earth; for within this day <hi>Adam, <note place="margin">
                              <hi>Ezech.</hi> 34.17. <hi>&amp;c. Mat.</hi> 25.</note> Methuſalem,</hi> yea all men have died; and only Chriſt (with his Saints) ſhall live the whole day; in this day he will judge between cattel and cattel, admitting wiſe, rejecting fooliſh Virgins.</p>
                     <p>For the accompliſhment of theſe and ſuch like ends, <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.28.</note> unto them that look for him, ſhall he appear the ſecond time without ſin unto ſalvation.</p>
                     <p>The ſeventh thing to be conſidered, is, the events ſucceeding the ſecond appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of our Lord in this his day of power, in which after he hath reigned with his Saints a thouſand years in full beatitude, ſuch wonderful Changes will enſue, as will make a ready entrance to that great change when changes ſhall be no more.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>. <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.7. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 8.</note> As firſt, Satan ſhall be looſed for a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ſeaſon, wherein he will ſo beſtir him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in all quarters of the Earth, exciting his vaſſals, (that have gladly ſerved the Saints this thouſand years) to ſhake the yoak from off their necks, which they (as his ſworn ſervants) ſhall readily yield to, and this will produce,</p>
                     <pb n="161" facs="tcp:35245:86"/>
                     <p n="2">2. The ſecond Change, which will be the combination of theſe his Inſtruments, whoſe number is as the ſand of the Sea, and in confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of their great ſtrength, they ſhall ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>round the beloved City, &amp; think (by their huge multitudes) to devour it at once; but how little does this trouble the Saints within? all tears were wiped away from their eyes long ago; they know not what belongs to ſorrow or trouble; for the Prince of peace, and Author of eternal felicity is among them; if they can hurt him, they may harm them, but both being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the reach of theſe poor deluded creatures, they are only making way for their own eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal ruine, for while they are thus beſieging the Camp of the Saints,</p>
                     <p n="3">3. The world is fired about their ears, <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Verſ</hi> 9. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.10. <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.11, 12.</note> &amp; with it themſelves are devoured; and this produceth the final concluſion of this great day: for now,</p>
                     <p n="4">4. The Lord is ſeated in his great white Throne, before whom the Earth and the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven vaniſheth.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. Then ſhall the dead, ſmal and great, be raiſed &amp; ſtand before his great Tribunal upon his left hand, as ſo many curſed goats, <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Math.</hi> 24 32.</note> veſſels of wrath fitted to deſtruction, where they ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the final ſentence of eternal condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which is a perpetual ſeparation from the preſence of Gods love, to be tormented with reprobate Angels and men, (the objects of his
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:35245:87"/>wrath and fury) to all eternity: oh what will they do in this eſtate of eternity! oh that they would now conſider of it! <hi>Why are not the ſinners in Sion now afraid? <note place="margin">
                              <hi>Iſa.</hi> 33.14.</note> why doth not fearfulnes now ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe the hypocrites? who among us ſhall dwell with the devouring fire? who among us ſhal dwel with e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting burnings?</hi> 'Twil be in vain then to cal to the Mountains &amp; Rocks for a hiding place.</p>
                     <p n="6">6. But the Saints are ſecurely hid in the great Rock, and ſure Refuge of his people, who are long ſince acquitted by vertue of their marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age with the Kings Son, <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.27. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.14.</note> who now preſents his Spouſe pure &amp; ſpotleſs, a glorious Church, not having ſpot or wrinkle, or any ſuch thing; and ſo having alſo juſtified them before An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels and men, he makes a free ſurrender of his Office of Mediator with his purchaſed Spouſe, into the hands of his and our Father,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.24.28.</note> who is the eternal infinite Ocean of that fulneſs of happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <note place="margin">1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.2. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.12.</note> which we muſt (and well may) admire, but ſhal never fully underſtand, till we come to ſee him as he is, &amp; know him as we are known.</p>
                     <p>O thou infinite Ocean of tranſcendent ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs! for this Jeſus ſake whom thou ſo deer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly loveſt, raiſe up thy Saints, by the divine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence of thy eternal Spirit to ſuch a heighth and eminency of faith, zeal, love, holineſs, and all heavenly qualifications, that we may be able to comprehend with all Saints, <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.18, 19.</note> 
                        <hi>what is the bredth, and length, and depth, and heighth,
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:35245:87"/>and to know the love of Chriſt, which paſſeth know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that we may be filled with all the fulneſs of God;</hi> to behold thy bleſſed face in that day with joy.</p>
                     <q>
                        <lg>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Come Sions ſons with Sions ſongs,</hi> 
                              <note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Pſal.</hi> 145.45.14, 15.</note>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Attend your Royal King;</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Joyn conſort in coeleſtial throngs,</hi> 
                              <note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.6, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>.</note>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>His wondrous reign to Sing.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Heark Virgins, that's the midnight cry,</hi> 
                              <note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.6.</note>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>The Bridegroom is at hand</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>With burning Lamps, full veſſels by:</hi> 
                              <note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Verſe</hi> 10.</note>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Stand lovely Virgins, ſtand.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>
                              <hi>That's he who with ten thouſand Saints</hi> 
                              <note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Jude</hi> 14.</note>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>In thoſe bright clouds appears:</hi> 
                              <note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.10.</note>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>We joyn, ſo ceaſe all ſad complaints,</hi> 
                              <note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.7.</note> 
                              <note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.17.</note>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>All troubles, toyl and tears.</hi> 
                              <note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Iſai.</hi> 56.19.</note>
                           </l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Now like his glorious body we</hi> 
                              <note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.21.</note>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Shall all be faſhioned</hi> 
                              <note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Rev.</hi> 7.9.14.</note>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>With Robes, and Crowns of Majeſty,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>As Kings be furniſhed.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Thus to</hi> Jehoſaphats <hi>fair Vale,</hi> 
                              <note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Joel.</hi> 3.2, 11, 12.</note>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>We with our King deſcend:</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Where vanquiſht foes, faint, feeble, pale,</hi> 
                              <note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Pſal.</hi> 72.11.</note>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Muſt at his Throne attend.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </lg>
                        <pb n="164" facs="tcp:35245:88"/>
                        <lg>
                           <l>
                              <hi>The day is come, <note place="margin">
                                    <hi>Micah.</hi> 4.1.</note> the Lord muſt reign,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>The Saints muſt judge the world,</hi> 
                              <note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.27.</note>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Satan confin'd, <note place="margin">
                                    <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.2.19.20.</note> his curſed train</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Into confuſion hurl'd.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>
                              <note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.19, 20, 21, 22.</note> 
                              <hi>The groaning creature from that ſnare</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Which long entangled them</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Set free, <note place="margin">
                                    <hi>Iſai.</hi> 56.26.</note> with Saints in glory ſhare,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Of new</hi> Jeruſalem. <note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Acts</hi> 3.21.</note>
                           </l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Theſe ſweet refreſhing times, <note place="margin">
                                    <hi>Acts</hi> 3.19.</note> O Lord,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>From thy ſweet preſence ſpring,</hi> 
                              <note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16 11.</note>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>With hearts and voyces Saints accord,</hi> 
                              <note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.17.</note>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Thy glorious reign to ſing.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </lg>
                     </q>
                     <p>What remains then, <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.16.</note> but that all the Saints who expect this appearance of our Lord, do with the four and twenty Elders fall down and worſhip God,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Verſ.</hi> 17.</note> ſaying, <hi>We give thee thanks O Lord God Almighty, which art, and waſt, and art to come, becauſe thou haſt taken to thee thy great Power, and haſt reigned.</hi> For this work, this wondrous work, <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Iſai.</hi> 52.9, 10.</note> is ſo certain, that the Spirit of the Lord preſents it (like many other Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies) as already done.</p>
                     <p>Great ground of rejoycing is this to Saints, as it is ground of terror and vexation to the wicked; there's not more ſad news in the world then this to the ungodly, this will be a dark day to them, according as it follows (for I ſhall but name the reſt.)</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="18" type="verse">
                  <pb n="165" facs="tcp:35245:88"/>
                  <head>The eighteenth Verſe. <hi>And the Nations were angry, and thy wrath is come, and the time of the dead, that they ſhould be judged, and that thou ſhouldeſt give reward unto thy ſervants the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and to the Saints, and them that fear thy Name ſmal and great, and ſhouldeſt deſtroy them which deſtroy the earth.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Here the portion of the Saints is far different from that of the dead, and earthy-minded men, and therefore there muſt be different returns from them: While (then) the Nations are an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry at the wrath and judgements of that Lord whom they have ſo much ſleighted, let the Prophets and Saints, and them that fear the Name of the Lord, exceedingly triumph; for the time is at hand that they ſhall be ſupera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundantly rewarded for all their pains and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours of Love and Charity, for all their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches, ſcorns, and affronts that the world hath caſt upon them for all their ſufferings, and cruel mockings, and all manner of perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; for it is to them that the following words pertain.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="19" type="verse">
                  <head>The ninteenth Verſe. <hi>And the Temple of God was opened in heaven, and there was ſeen in his Temple the Ark of his Teſtament;</hi>—</head>
                  <p>This is the lot and portion of the Righteous, which becauſe we cannot conceive or under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, I ſhall paſs over in ſilence, hoping that our ſpirits will be raiſed to admire what can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:35245:89"/>be expreſſed in word, or conceived in the heart, preſſing forward by a Chriſtian conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation to the ſweet fruition of that glory which will be the ſure portion of thoſe that have part in the firſt Reſurrection, while the wicked (that continue to do wickedly) have nothing to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect, or hope for in that day, but that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the Spirit cloſeth this Chapter.</p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>And there were lightnings, and voyces, and thundrings, and an Earthquake, and great hail.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <p>This will be the terrible portion of thoſe of whom the Apoſtle <hi>Jude</hi> ſpeaketh; <hi>Behold the Lord cometh with ten thouſand of his Saints, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecute judgement upon all, and to convince all that are ungodly among them, of all their ungodly deeds which they have ungodly committed, and of all their hard ſpeeches which ungodly ſinners have ſpoken againſt him.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Jude</hi> 14.15.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>The mouths of wicked men will then be ſtopped and put to ſilence, though now they bark and belch forth blaſphemies (at pleaſure) againſt the Saints; yet will it then be proved to their faces, that all their wicked actions, and hard ſpeeches are done and ſpoken againſt him, whoſe doctrine they now reject, whoſe yoak they will not now bend to, whoſe perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Reign they contemn as a Fable: but then, will they, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ke</hi> 19.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> nill they, this voyce ſhal reach them;</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But thoſe mine Enemies which would not that I
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:35245:89"/>ſhould reign over them, bring them hither and ſlay them before me.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And this will be ſuch a ſlaughter, where they will be ever killing and never dead, but ſhall live in death to all eternity.</p>
                  <p>As this is ground of wo and alas to the wicked ſort, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.10.</note> againſt whom the door is now ſhut, never to be opened any more, never more tenders of Grace, never more offers of Mercy in the Goſpel, but howling and wailing with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ceaſing world without end.</p>
                  <p>So is it true matter of unſpeakable joy to all Saints, no ground of Joy like this, it comes with a <hi>Rather; <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Luke</hi> 10.20.</note> But rather rejoyce becauſe your names are written in heaven:</hi> This is the poor ſouls fulneſs of joy, <note place="margin">1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.3, 4.</note> to know his intereſt in that ſociety that ſhall continue rejoycing to all eternity.</p>
                  <p>I give a word of advice (in the wordsof the Spirit) to every man that hath this hope in him,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.3.</note> to purifie himſelf, even as he is pure; for ſince our expectation is ſuch, <hi>what manner of perſons ought we to be in all holy converſation &amp; godlineſs, <note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.11, 12</note> looking for, and haſting unto the coming of the day of God; wherefore gird up the loyns of your mind, be ſober, and hope to the end for the grace that is to be brought unto you at the Revelation of Jeſus Chriſt: <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.13. <hi>Luk</hi> 2.36.</note> And ye your ſelves like unto men that wait for their Lord when he wil return from the wedding. Bleſſed are thoſe ſervants whom the Lord when he
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:35245:90"/>comes ſhall find watching; <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30.18.</note> yea bleſſed are all they that waite for him.</hi> Its no matter (deer Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians) how much pains we take in the way, nor what our trouble and miſery is; <hi>for I reckon that the ſufferings of this preſent time are not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be compared with the glory which ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed in us:</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.18.</note> When Chriſt our King ſhall ſay, <hi>Well done thou good and faithful Servant, <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.21.</note> enter thou into the joy of thy Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>How then ſhould our hearts be tranſported with holy Raviſhments in expectation of this his Appearance, ſinging in Conſort, with the Heavens, Earth, Sea, Fields and Trees, (in the ſweet Singers heavenly Rapture) <hi>For he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pſa.</hi> 96.</note> for he cometh to judge the Earth; he ſhall judge the world with Righteouſneſs, and the people with his Truth: Even ſo come Lord Jeſus, come quickly.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:35245:90"/>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
